<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A conference between an orthodox Christian and a Socinian in four dialogues : wherein the late distinction of a real and nominal Trinitarian is considered / by H. de Lvzancy ...</title>
            <author>De Luzancy, H. C. (Hippolyte du Chastelet), d. 1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 250 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36727</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2417</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31382</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11955424</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11955424</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51496</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36727)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51496)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1004:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A conference between an orthodox Christian and a Socinian in four dialogues : wherein the late distinction of a real and nominal Trinitarian is considered / by H. de Lvzancy ...</title>
                  <author>De Luzancy, H. C. (Hippolyte du Chastelet), d. 1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 134 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Warren for Thomas Bennet ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Trinitarians.</term>
               <term>Socinianism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51496:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51496:1"/>
            <p>A <hi>Conference</hi> Between an Orthodox Chriſtian AND A <hi>SOCINIAN.</hi> IN FOUR DIALOGUES. Wherein The late diſtinction of a <hi>Real</hi> and <hi>Nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Trinitarian</hi> is Conſidered. By <hi>H. DE L<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ZANCY,</hi> B. D. Vic. of <hi>Dovere.</hi> and <hi>Harwich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Warren,</hi> for <hi>Thomas Bennet,</hi> at the <hi>Half-Moon</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1698.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:51496:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51496:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>IT is hard to determine which is the greateſt misfortune, either to give an eaſy aſſent to whatever Doctrine is propos'd to us, or value our ſelves upon pretended difficulties, and deny inconteſtable Articles, becauſe they are not altogether free from them? It ſeems to me as dangerous an errour to disbelieve, as to believe every thing: The one being the effect of a prodigious weakneſs, and the other of an incredible preſumption; both equally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with Reaſon, which cannot but be ſenſible, that as there are things viſibly falſe to the meaneſt Capacity, ſo there are thoſe which the greateſt pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tration cannot reach, and yet are certainly true.</p>
            <p>This carries ſo much evidence along with it, that it is granted in all our Moral and Philoſophical in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiries. We are witneſſes of innumerable events, the cauſes of which we gueſs at, but can give no clear account of. The ſprings of moſt tranſactions in the World are hid from Mankind, and lie in an unfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thomable obſcurity, plain to none but him <hi>to whom Darkneſs is as light as the Day.</hi> The ſame muſt be ſaid of our ſearch about natural objects. Nature ſo obvious every where, has yet ſecret receſſes which all our ſagacity cannot penetrate. We are agreed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb facs="tcp:51496:3"/>its operations; but as for their principles they have been diſputed of from the beginning, and will be to the end of the World. The Men of thoughts and reflexion concluding daily, that there are on all ſides mighty difficulties and never to be overcome.</p>
            <p>But it is ſtrange that this ſhould be granted with ſo much equity and freedom in that ſort of Matters, and deny'd of Religion; which being of a higher and more abſtruſe Nature, and of a far greater Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity than all the Dictates of Men, ſhould by its own weight ſilence all Objections, and put poſitive Mortals in mind that a tranſcendent Object ceaſes not to be, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we cannot take an exact view of it, and that a Divine Propoſition loſes not the Character of Truth, becauſe we form difficulties againſt it.</p>
            <p>And yet this is the eaſe of <hi>Socinianiſm.</hi> The Gentlemen who have ſuffer'd themſelves to be led into it, deny the <hi>Myſteries</hi> of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> inſiſting on their unreaſonableneſs, pretending that they are not oblig'd to believe that of which they have not a clear Notion; and with a ſort of aſſurance which becomes no Man, and them leaſt of all; charging the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Doctrine with the ſcandalous imputations of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction and nonſence. This is the deſign of their laſt Collection of Prints; the perpetual deſcant in converſation, and a contrivance to keep the diſpute alive, till that being ruin'd, they muſt of neceſſity ſet up ſomething elſe.</p>
            <p>But indeed either we argue to give life to a party, or elſe we act ſincerely, conſcientiouſly, and with a deſign to find out and eſtabliſh the Truth. If the firſt, <hi>God is greater than our Hearts, and knows all things.</hi> He will puniſh ſo mean and ſo ſordid an end which does not vindicate, but proſtitute Religion. But if
<pb facs="tcp:51496:3"/>the laſt, I muſt beg leave to ſay, that there is neither Truth, Piety, or Modeſty in all that noiſe. Is it come to that, that I muſt call a Doctrine unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, becauſe my Reaſon is weak and cannot under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand every part of it? Do I own my doubtfulneſs and ignorance in all other things, and am only ſecure and clear-ſighted in this? Or admit Myſteries in moſt of Nature's Operations, and exclude them only from Religion? Happy Man who can tye the Hands of his Creatour, and force him to impoſe nothing on his belief but what is plain and intelligible!</p>
            <p>What high ſtrain of good manners is this to call that Non-ſence and Contradiction, which the Church of God from the very beginning of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> to this time, and in all the parts of the World where it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, has ſo highly reverenc'd? As if our guides in Spiritual Matters had been no more than a company of Mad-men, who have fill'd our Heads with crude, impertinent and contradictory Notions.</p>
            <p>This is ſo much the worſe in theſe Gentlemen, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they cannot but be acquainted, that Philoſophy was never, and is not to be appeal'd to in theſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes: The certainty of our belief depending on a nobler and more infallible Principle, even the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of God ſpeaking in the Sacred Scriptures. The Fathers never doubted but that Difficulties would ever be rais'd in the treating of our Myſteries, but thought this ſufficiently over-rul'd by the very conſideration of God's own determination in that Revelation which he has made of himſelf. Whether theſe Gentlemen will or no, this muſt be the laſt reſolution of this great Controverſy. Let them think of it in earneſt, and they will agree with me that it cannot be otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>This method I follow'd and urg'd again and again
<pb facs="tcp:51496:4"/>to a Friend, for whoſe ſake I writ and publiſh'd the <hi>Four Letters.</hi> They ſeem'd to me to have made ſome impreſſion on him; and as he is a Perſon of Candor, he own'd that it was beyond his Ability to Anſwer, but would expect what the <hi>Socinian</hi> writers had to ſay to them. After ſome time an Anſwer came out: But as I muſt do them the juſtice to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that they have us'd me in it with a great deal of civility, and ſhow'd that deep ſtudies had not ſpoil'd in them good breeding; a fault too too com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in Learned Men! So I am forc'd to complain that they have not ſo much as touch'd any one part of my Book. But taking no care either of vindicating the unwary Aſſertions of their Authors, or anſwering thoſe ſubſtantial Arguments which were laid before them; they ſerv'd me as they had done others before, contenting themſelves with a handſome declamation about their new and chimerical diſtinction of <hi>Real</hi> and <hi>Nominal Trinitarians;</hi> inſiſting on the incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſibility and contradiction of the Chriſtian Doctrine; and, what is pleaſant enough, arguing againſt its unreaſonableneſs, without ſo much as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amining any one of the plain Reaſons given for it.</p>
            <p>My Friend then was arm'd with two n w Topicks. He would call upon me, and ask me whether I was a <hi>Real</hi> or a <hi>Nominal Trinitarian?</hi> He would main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that his Reaſon could not yield to what is unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, or be bound to aſſent to what is Contradictory or at beſt Incomprehenſible. I thought then my ſelf oblig'd for his ſake in particular, and in general for the good of the <hi>Chriſtian Cauſe,</hi> to which we are all debtors, to take a view of theſe two Engines of the <hi>Socinian</hi> make. This is the occaſion of the following Papers, in which this diſtinction is examin'd, the
<pb facs="tcp:51496:4"/>diſpute between them and us brought back to the true ſtate of the queſtion, <hi>viz.</hi> the Authority of the Sacred Writings, The nature of Faith and Reaſon, and the Superiority of the firſt over the laſt eſtabliſh'd, and the bounds of both aſſign'd. I hope that having no other end in this but doing good, they will ſatisfy him for whom they are written, and work on thoſe whom a miſtaken Conſcience has made to perſiſt in ſo dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous an errour.</p>
            <p>All this is treated by way of Conference and Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues: A manner of Writing uſual in the Primitive times, as appears by <hi>Juſtin Martyr, Theodoret,</hi> St. <hi>Jerom,</hi> &amp;c. And famous amongſt us by ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral late excellent Books of that kind. It has that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, that being properly an imitation of Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, all is eaſy and natural in it. A Reader is not put on the rack by that intenſe ſtudy, which a tedious Argument requires. And even the Repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Digreſſions which in a Conference are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidable, have ſomewhat in them which is very taking. I have been as ſparing as I could of cita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, hard words, or any thing which might obſcure or perplex the Subject. For beſides the Solidity of our Reaſonings, there muſt be an exquiſite plainneſs, and familiarity in Dialogues, which if an Author can attain, nothing more is to be deſir'd in that ſort of Writing.</p>
            <p>But before I conclude this, I muſt ſay that of all Writers theſe Gentlemen ought not to value them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, becauſe they have rais'd a great deal of duſt which their own prejudice hinders them from laying. They complain of difficulties, and at every word cry out <hi>Unreaſonable, Contradictory, Incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible:</hi> Whereas no People who attempted to put our
<pb facs="tcp:51496:5"/>Holy Religion out of doors, ever oppos'd to it a more <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ereaſonable, Contradictory, and Incomprehenſible Syſtem than they have done.</p>
            <p>I will not ſpeak of their Incomprehenſible explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſuch as are that of <hi>Joh. 1.</hi> that of <hi>Phil. 2. Coloſſ. 1. Heb. 1.</hi> &amp;c. which no Man in his right ſenſes can make any thing of, and are a direct Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction to the other part of the Divine Oracles. But I will only beg of them to reconcile their robbing <hi>Chriſt</hi> of his Divinity, to the <hi>adoring of him, praying to him,</hi> and making him an object of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip.</hi> I ſhould be glad they would ſhew us, how it is conſiſtent with Reaſon, that <hi>A meer Man, A meer Creature,</hi> ſuch as they make <hi>Chriſt</hi> to be, can offer himſelf a ſufficient Expiation, a propitiatory Sacrifice for the Sins of the whole World. This the Author of the <hi>Brief Hiſtory</hi> has granted. This is reported to have been acknowledged by Charitable Mr. <hi>F.</hi> at his death. This Mr. <hi>T.</hi> one of their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſo largely commended by the Author of the laſt Anſwer to My Lord of <hi>Worceſter's</hi> late Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Holy Trinity,</hi> has plainly call'd an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagance. <hi>I am miſtaken,</hi> ſays he, Chriſtianity not Myſter. <hi>pag. 25. if either the</hi> Socinians, <hi>or the</hi> Arrians <hi>can make their Notions of a DIGNIFY'D AND CREATURE-GOD CAPABLE OF DI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VINE WORSHIP, appear more reaſonable than the extravagancies of other Sects, touching the Article of the Trinity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When they have juſtify'd all this, and a great deal more which may be objected to them; then, and not before, they may lay claim to, and ſtand by their pretended Inconſiſtencies. But till that is done, they muſt only be look'd upon as a remarkable inſtance of
<pb facs="tcp:51496:5"/>humane infirmity, which not contented to rely on that ſolid Foundation, which the Redeemer of the World and his Apoſtles have left us, ſettles in a barren and dry Ground where no Water is. There is no Man but what can eaſier pull down, than build up. Let us but want Humility, and abound in our own Sence, which is as often our Sin, as our Misfortune, and we ſhall eaſily have objections in ſtore againſt the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith. But then we leave the Rock to build on the Sand And when we have done all that we can by our fine diſcourſes, it will be Sand ſtill: The Structure will tumble to the ground, and <hi>great will be the fall of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If theſe Gentlemen think fit to ſay any thing to theſe Papers, they are humbly intreated that they will not uſe them, as they did the <hi>Four Letters;</hi> that is, put out an Anſwer where nothing either directly, or indirectly is anſwer'd. If they only write to ſatisfy me that they are Men of Learning, and Maſters of all the Graces of Elocution, I am convinc'd of it already, and they may ſpare themſelves that trouble. 'Tis not ſo much Language and Oratory, as Argument and Reaſon which we expect at their hands.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:51496:6"/>
            <head>Books Printed for <hi>Thomas Bennet,</hi> at the <hi>Half-Moon</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard.</head>
            <p>REmarks on ſome late Writings of the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh <hi>Socinians,</hi> in <hi>Four Letters,</hi> done at the Requeſt of a <hi>Socinian</hi> Gentleman. By <hi>H. de Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zancy,</hi> B. D. Miniſter of <hi>Doverc.</hi> and <hi>Harwich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Inſpiration of the New Teſtament aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and explained; in anſwer to the <hi>Six Letters of Inſpiration</hi> from <hi>Holland,</hi> &amp;c. By Mr. <hi>Le Moth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Conference with a Theiſt,</hi> in two Parts. By <hi>W. Nicholls,</hi> Rector of <hi>Selſey</hi> in <hi>Suſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Certainty and Neceſſity of Religion in General; or the firſt Grounds and Principles of Humane Duty Eſtabliſhed. In eight Sermons at Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi>'s Lecture for the Year 1697. By <hi>F. Gaſtrell,</hi> B. D. and Studient of <hi>Chriſt-Church Oxon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Certain Conſiderations for the better Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> with a Preface by <hi>James Harrington</hi> Eſq;</p>
            <p>A Sermon Preach'd before the Honourable Houſe of Commons, on the Anniverſary Faſt, for the Martyrdoom of King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt. By <hi>E. Langford</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>A Sermon before the Lord Mayor, Judges, and Aldermen, at the Cathedral of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> on the thirtieth of <hi>January,</hi> 1697. By <hi>S. Eſtwick,</hi> B. D. and Chaplain of <hi>Chriſt-Church Oxon.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In the Preſs.</head>
               <p>Twelve Sermons upon ſeveral Occaſions. By <hi>Robert South.</hi> D. D. Never before Printed.</p>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Bentley</hi>'s Deſſertation upon the Epiſtles of <hi>Phalaris,</hi> &amp;c. and the Fables of <hi>Aeſop</hi> Examined. By the Honourable <hi>Charles Boyle,</hi> Eſq;</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogues">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51496:6"/>
            <head>A <hi>Conference</hi> Between an <hi>Orthodox Chriſtian</hi> AND A <hi>SOCINIAN.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="dialogue">
               <head>The Firſt DIALOGUE.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socinian.</speaker>
                  <p>WELL! I ſee, there is no end of diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; and if that ſpirit once poſſeſſes Men, they have the misfortune never to know when to have done. Yeſterday, at four in the afternoon the Doctor and your Friend enter'd
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51496:7"/>the liſts; It was Nine at Night, before they could be perſwaded to ſit down, and take their ſhare of a Curious entertainment which Mr. <hi>N.</hi> at whoſe Houſe they were, had prepar'd for them. Every thing was neat and fine, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany ſelect and good; and yet all this which makes Men Sociable and inclin'd to pleaſe one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, had no ſuch effect on theſe two great Spirits. They had much ado to forbear breaking out; and if they had been let alone, I really believe that they would be diſputing ſtill.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthodox.</speaker>
                  <p>Pray, what was the ſubject of this long diſpute?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>The great Controverſy of the Age, <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinianiſm;</hi> That which the Church of <hi>England</hi> endeavours to run down with ſo much vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency; and has been lately defended by ſeveral ingenious Men, whoſe Writings I am ſatisfy'd you are no ſtranger to.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>What could they ſay in all that time? They are both Men of Learning, and I ſuppoſe method too, without which Learning is of no uſe, and becomes only a large heap of rich Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terials without beauty or ſtrength, becauſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out order or diſpoſition.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>All that I could perceive of both ſides, was very little reaſon or Argument; But a World of heat and clamor; Perpetual reflections either on the Church or the <hi>Socinians,</hi> rude ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, and an inſufferable ſhifting and run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from one thing to another.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>Truly, this is the miſery of diſputes, which for want of good and ſincere management become a fatigue, and a labour not to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51496:7"/>Books come as much ſhort of it, as Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation. The Writers and the Readers are equally unfortunate in this, the one not giving that which they promiſe, and the other being diſappointed of that which they look for, and that is, Information.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>For this very reaſon I have almoſt vow'd to diſpute no more. I will hate the very Name of Controverſy; and no Book of that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhall find Room in my Library. Time may be ſpent much better than in endeavoring to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand an Author, who does not underſtand himſelf. An infinite Stock of Patience is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to bear with a dull, flat, and inſipid Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Nor was I ever made to be a Witneſs, to all their heats and follies, who load their Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary with ill Language, becauſe he is not of their Opinion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>I am not of your mind. That which is good cannot ceaſe to be ſuch becauſe it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus'd. Inquiry after Truth is the Nobleſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, as well as the moſt Natural inclination of Mankind. And diſputing is the way which leads to it. It is by comparing Argument with Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, and Reaſon with Reaſon, that at laſt it does appear. In the State of Weakneſs, that we are in, Thinking and Reflection are the only helps we have, and it is from ſtriking the ſteal and the flint together, that the bleſſed fire breaks out, which improv'd removes our darkneſs. We have very few Self-Evident Principles; and from them, we do not always draw true, and exact conſequences. The Mine muſt be open'd and digg'd with a great deal of Labour; till we come
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51496:8"/>to the precious <hi>Ore.</hi> But once found, it yields an ineſtimable treaſure. In a word, it is by the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition and difference of Men in their opinions, that we come to examine, reflect, inquire, and at laſt find out the Truth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>I grant all this: But when diſputing is ſo wholly perverted as to become a ſanctuary to Error: When two contending Parties are ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate as not to yield the leaſt Point: and it is no more whether what I ſay is true, but what I ſay muſt be true: When Books are fill'd up and grow to large volumes and yet nothing to the purpoſe: When all degenerates into heat and paſſion; I think it time to have done, keep my ſenſe of things to my ſelf, and meddle no more with diſputes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>What you ſay is too true. We have a large experience that ſeveral have Writ of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects which they never underſtood, and others have pretended to anſwer objections which they have wholly miſtaken. Like thoſe Tranſlators, Who have aſſaſſinated ſeveral Authors, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figur'd many admirable and Original Pieces, for want of underſtanding both the Language out of which they tranſlated, and their own, which they tranſlated into. It is alſo evident that Divine Matters have been treated with very little piety; As if God was not to be conſulted when Man preſumes to ſpeak of him, and the heart as well as the mind, was not to guide the hand of the Writer. But yet for all this, there are Books of this kind, which cannot be ſufficiently admir'd. ſo clear they are and yet ſo conciſe; ſo eloquent and yet ſo grave; ſo Candid and yet
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51496:8"/>ſo home, that it is hard to ſay, whether they are more commended by the preſent Age, or ſhall be more admir'd by poſterity.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>Pray where are thoſe <hi>Phoenix</hi>'s to be found? For they are ſo rare, that they really deſerve that name.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>Not ſo very rare neither. What Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Writings did the Reign of <hi>Charles</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond produce in Defence of the Unity and Peace of the Church? How was <hi>Popery</hi> treated in that of <hi>James</hi> the Second? With what ſolidity and clearneſs did our Divines argue with the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſaries of <hi>Rome,</hi> never ſtarting from the ſtate of the queſtion, or the main ſtreſs of the difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty propos'd? And in this of <hi>William</hi> the Third, when the <hi>Socinian</hi> Controverſy which had ſlept ſome years began to awake again, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe it ſelf ſome increaſe from the looſeneſs of Men's principles, and from ſome other unhappy Circumſtances unknown but to very few; How did the Church rowſe up, and with what Zeal, what Learning, what ſucceſs did they oppoſe the growing <hi>Hereſy?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>I own that ſome good Books have been written againſt the <hi>Nonconformiſts,</hi> and many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent ones againſt the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> But for your ſucceſs againſt <hi>Socinianiſm,</hi> it is indeed much to be admir'd. Is it not notorious that all your Writings have not brought one over to a Recantation; and that though the Sect does not thrive much in the Country where Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation is more rare, yet it viſibly gets ground in the Town? There is ſcarce a Wit but what is a <hi>Socinian.</hi> If <hi>Socinianiſm</hi> is a rank Poiſon, I can
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51496:9"/>aſſure you that the young Gentlemen ſwallow it with greedineſs. One whiſper'd me not long ſince, that it is got even amongſt ſome eminent <hi>Lawyers.</hi> Many of your Clergy themſelves are not free from the aſperſion. <hi>Socinianiſm</hi> is publickly diſown'd and hated; but privately much made of and careſs'd. I am afraid, if your Univerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties were ſearch'd, it would be found that the ſinful Weed grows there too.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>What you ſay is that which we now exclaim'd againſt, and that is Reflecting. But when all is done the trick is ſtale, and not like to take. There never was yet ſo deſpicable a Sect in the World, but what was willing to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuate that their numbers were far greater than what really they appear'd A piece of Vanity laugh'd at every where by Men of Sence! But in this the <hi>Socinians</hi> are unhappy. For they are <hi>a Sect</hi> and <hi>no Sect, a Body</hi> and <hi>no Body.</hi> Some particular Perſons have been Intoxicated with reading <hi>Socinus, Crellius,</hi> &amp;c. They have cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected and improv'd many of their Notions. Theſe they have put into ſeveral ſhort, and truly Elegant Writings; and having had the happineſs to be anſwer'd by Men every way Great, it gave a general curioſity to read what theſe Authors had ſaid, which ſhould arm ſo many famous Pens againſt them. This has perſwaded them into a belief that they have a croud of followers: And as formerly the <hi>Arrians</hi> in the diſputes againſt <hi>Arrianiſm,</hi> ſo in theſe againſt <hi>Socinianiſm,</hi> they fanſie that the whole World is become <hi>Socinian.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But I will preſume to ſay, that it is nothing but fancy. Men do not ſo eaſily part with the Faith
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51496:9"/>in which they were baptiz'd, and in which the hope of their Eternal Salvation conſiſts. They may give ſome ſway to curioſity, and the Gay Novelty may take for a while. But Conſcience returns, and will not ſuffer them to ſhake off at once all the Principles of our Holy Religion.</p>
                  <p>That the young Gentlemen greedily ſwallow the Poiſon, is a real miſtake. I confeſs, and it is much to be lamented, that ſeveral amongſt them are much debauch'd in their Morals, and that the rage of Luſt, and that of Wine, have ſtrangely obſcur'd their underſtandings. But, believe me, profane and diſſolute Perſons are no Honour to any Profeſſion whatſoever. If you are fond of ſuch an Addition, take them and call them <hi>Socinians,</hi> I promiſe not to be angry at it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>What you ſay is true in a great meaſure, but give me leave—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>But give me leave your ſelf to make an end of ſpeaking, to what you ſaid of the Wits of the Town. I ever had a Notion of Wit different from that of the Wits themſelves. They are careful to diſtinguiſh Wit from Sence. And with this poor Notion the Poets have courted, or anger'd the Pit theſe twenty years in their <hi>Prologues</hi> and <hi>Epilogues.</hi> As if he could be a Man of Wit who is not a Man of Sence. For Wit and Sence are inſeparable. An <hi>Efferveſcency</hi> of ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination, breaking out into ſome ſine Expreſſions is not Wit, but a ſort of lucky Madneſs. He that thinks and ſpeaks well, is exact and cohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, grave or florid according to his Subject, but always modeſt and inoffenſive, is to me the Man of Wit. Pray tell me how many of theſe are <hi>Socinians.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:51496:10"/>
                  <p>But for the Men of Sallies and unbounded Thoughts, who value themſelves upon Writing a few Verſes, and perhaps a ſmall Pamphlet; who think as they live, and live as they think; that is, moſt irregularly; I abandon them to you. They ſhall be <hi>Socinians</hi> if you pleaſe: I promiſe once more not to be angry at it. What ſort of Wit is that conſcientious Spark, who writ late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly an Apology for ſelf-murder? What think you of the Author of <hi>Chriſtianity not Myſterious?</hi> Or of the Writer of one of the two Epiſtles to Mr. <hi>Gailhard.</hi> I mean the ſecond, which is as wild and ill written, as the firſt is modeſt and fine. Put theſe alſo into the Catalogue, and then boaſt of your Conqueſts.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>I hope you are not of this Mr. <hi>Gailhard</hi>'s mind, who is for ſanguinary Laws to be enacted againſt us; and would have us meet at <hi>Smithfield,</hi> with the fate of <hi>Servetus</hi> at <hi>Geneva,</hi> and <hi>Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus Gentilis</hi> at <hi>Berne.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>I never heard of Mr. <hi>Gailhard,</hi> or of his deſign againſt you, till I read your Letters againſt him. But if there were ſuch Laws, you would ſtill be ſafe. For I dare ſay, neither you, nor your Friends, will ever be the Martyrs of <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianiſm.</hi> But to ſpeak ſeriouſly my thoughts, that Gentleman does not know what Spirit he is of. It is againſt that Religion of which <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the Author, to thirſt after the Blood of any Man. The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is admirably well acquainted with theſe methods of reclaiming People. Ours is a ſtranger to it, and takes a way much more agreeable, both to the nature of the Goſpel, and the condition of a Rational
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51496:10"/>Creature; and that is, to deliver the Truth which God hath truſted her with, adding to it all ſuitable Arguments of perſuaſion, and leaving the reſt to the Mercy and Providence of God. In a word, if exhorting, diſputing, arguing, perſuading, will not do, I know no other way, except excommunication: It being highly juſt, that the Church ſhould cut off an infected Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, which by an obſtinate oppoſition to her Doctrine, is like to ſpread the contagion through the other parts of the Body.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>It is not becauſe I am a <hi>Socinian,</hi> that I acknowledge this to be a truly <hi>Chriſtian</hi> temper: For it is the very Voice of Religion: But I hope you will not take it ill, if I tell you, that if you have no other way to aſſert, and propagate your Doctrine, than exhorting, perſuading, diſputing, I am afraid this deſign of yours, though good and honeſt, will at laſt prove un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſucceſsful.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>Why it ſhould be ſo I cannot imagine: For with a Rational Agent, what can prevail more than Reaſon? And with Learned Men, what more than Learning? What can you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe beſides diſputing, to bring them to the acknowledgment of their Errours?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>But you have diſputed ſo long, and yet to ſo little purpoſe, that it ſhews a deficiency in your very Method. Not only your ordinary Divines have been concern'd in the quarrel, but even Men of vaſt eſteem amongſt you, and yet what have they done? When I read their Books, and compare them with the <hi>Socinian</hi> Anſwers; or the <hi>Socinian</hi> Books with your Vindications and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51496:11"/>Apologies; Good God! How clearly do I ſee the ſtrength of our reaſons! You keep always in a Cloud, afraid of being ſeen; Whereas all is clear and ſafe about us.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>It is ſo far from that, that with People of Ordinary equity the quite contrary will appear. The <hi>Socinian</hi> Controverſy is certainly the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of all thoſe which ever exerciz'd the Church of God. The modern diſputes you are perfectly acquainted with, and cannot but be ſenſible that though many and large volumes have been writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten about them, yet they lie within a very nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row compaſs. Rob the controverted Points be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us, and the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> of the Trap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings of Diſcourſe, Digreſſions, and Clamors of their Authors, they are brought to a very plain and ſhort iſſue. Tranſubſtantiation, worſhip of Images, Purgatory, praying to the Saints, the Divine right of the <hi>Pope</hi>'s ſupremacy, and his pretended infallibility, are doctrines eaſily made to appear to be not only falſe, but even new in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf. As the ſubject is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely within our reach, ſo are the Arguments for and againſt them.</p>
                  <p>The ſame you muſt own of the unhappy dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences between us and the Nonconformiſts; and though much has been written on both ſides; yet at laſt whether the exceptions againſt the Publick <hi>Liturgy</hi> are ſolid? Whether a <hi>Schiſm</hi> may be grounded upon the impoſition of a few in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Ceremonies? Whether diſobedience to Epiſcopal Government can be juſtify'd, for which, without inquiring whether the inſtitution is Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, or not, there appears ſo Ancient, ſo Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51496:11"/>and ſo unconteſted a Tradition? Are queſtions of ſo eaſy a reſolution, that if there was nothing but Religion at the bottom, that War would quickly be at an End.</p>
                  <p>Read alſo the Catalogue of Ancient Hereſies, as they have been left us by Eccleſiaſtical Writers; ſuppoſing them all to be Hereſies, though indeed many are only Fooliſh and Simple Opinions; There is ſcarce one of any importance but as it relates ſome way or other to this great Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy. The reſt are trifles and dreams, which we now wonder how they could ever fall into, and buſy Rational Men's heads, as Poſterity will be amaz'd, when they come to examine the poor and ſilly differences of this quarrelling Age.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>But what of all this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>This is to ſhew you that in our debates with the <hi>Socinians,</hi> as the diſpute is, ſo are the Arguments of another nature, than thoſe in that ſort of Controverſies, which we have been ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of. The matter is abſtruſe and myſterious; We are not willing to ſpeak more of God, than he himſelf has taught us. This you call obſcuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and want of ſatisfaction: and becauſe the <hi>Socinians</hi> are perpetually reaſoning of an Increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and Incomprehenſible Subſtance, as they do of Finite and Created Beings; and are never weary of applying their notions of what they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, to what they underſtand not at all, and has no ſort of proportion to it; Then you ſay, that their writings are clear. I appeal to your ſelf whether you are not highly unjuſt to us? Nay, whether any one Controverſy in the World, was ever manag'd with ſo little Candor as this is by you?</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:51496:12"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>But pray how have you manag'd it? Forgive me if I tell you that the Church never ſhew'd ſo much Weakneſs in any thing as in this very particular. You are angry with us for Reaſoning too much: and you have Reaſon'd your ſelves out of doors. You pretended to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert a Trinity, and cannot tell us what that Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity is. You are <hi>Trinitarians</hi> indeed, but at the ſame time the ſad Aſſertors of a <hi>Trinity</hi> which is too much, or too little: Degenerates into <hi>Tritheiſm,</hi> or <hi>Sabellianiſm;</hi> and if receiv'd ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to ſome explications is <hi>Real,</hi> and Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous; and if according to others, is Nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and ſignify's nothing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>Truly, I wonder this was not yet come out. For you cannot now ſpeak to a <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian,</hi> but he brings in this right or wrong. The Author of the conſiderations of the ſeveral ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> made the beſt of it, and perſwaded himſelf that he had given us the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal wound. The Writer of the diſcourſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Real</hi> and <hi>Nominal Trinitarians</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes himſelf no leſs than the ruine of the Church if the fatal diſtinction is carry'd on, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd as it ought to be. He that dawbs with untemper'd mortar, and calls himſelf a <hi>Prebyter of the Church of England,</hi> is of the ſame mind. The whole Church, ſay they, Condemns the <hi>Real Trinitarians;</hi> and the <hi>Nominals</hi> being rank <hi>Sabelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> muſt of courſe be condemn'd too. Bleſſed diſcovery, which when truly examin'd is the greateſt piece of unſincerity imaginable!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>I muſt beg leave to interrupt you, and blame you for denying that which is clearer than
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51496:12"/>the Sun. Where lies then the unſincerity? Is it in affirming that you will not tell us what your Trinity is? Or is it in diſtributing you into <hi>Real and Nominal Trinitarians?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis in every part of the Allegation. Can any thing be more unſincere, than for you to tell us, that we oblige you to believe a <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> and are not willing to tell you what that <hi>Trinity</hi> is? Pray, were you ever Baptiz'd? Have you ever paid your Duty to God in the ſolemn uſe of our excellent Liturgy? Did you ever join in the <hi>Doxology,</hi> by which the Church in the Primitive Ages down to ours, put in the mouth of her Children a confutation of the <hi>Samoſate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian, Sabellian, Arrian, Neſtorian,</hi> and <hi>Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> Hereſies? Did you ever make a profeſſion of that Faith which you embrac'd in your Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, by reciting the <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> and <hi>Catholick</hi> Creeds? Did you ever read the Articles of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> or of any other Church in the World? For I poſitively averr that they do all and every one of them ſpeak and aſſert the ſame thing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>True: They tell us of a <hi>Trinity,</hi> but do not tell us what that <hi>Trinity</hi> is.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>Do they not tell you that God is one, That in that one adorable and Divine Nature are Father, Son, and Holy Spirit; That the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is God, the Son God, and the Holy Ghoſt God; and yet not three Gods, but one God? This is to tell you that there is a Bleſſed <hi>Trinity,</hi> and what that <hi>Trinity</hi> is.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>True again: But they do not tell us how God can be One and Three? How that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51496:13"/>
                     <hi>Trinity</hi> and Unity are reconcil'd? How every Perſon is God, and yet but one God? and if they do not ſay this, in effect they ſay nothing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>This is the arranteſt Sophiſm that ever was, or can be us'd in a diſpute. The Church aſſerts the thing becauſe God has aſſerted it. He has not been pleas'd to reveal the manner, and therefore the Church ſays nothing to it. All is built upon the Divine Revelation. Muſt we not believe that a thing is, when God has affirm'd that it is, becauſe he has not thought fit to make clear to us how it is?</p>
                  <p>Should I tell you that the Sun is a luminous Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, which by diſperſing its Beams over all the Creation, gives Light and Colour to every thing; and that the earth is impregnated by certain qualities, which with an admirable luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riancy cover it with Fruits and Flowers: Would you deny this, becauſe I do not acquaint you, how that Body is luminous, how the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of light mix with all things, and ſhew what they are? Would you deny the fruitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Earth, becauſe I cannot explain thoſe qualities by which it is impregnated?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>This reaches not at all the difficulty. For theſe are things of ſenſe, which I am ſatisfy'd to be, and to exiſt. Beſides, I am capable of Philoſophical inquiries, by which if I do not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly know the <hi>How,</hi> I come at leaſt very near it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>But this not only reaches the difficulty but wholly reſolves it. For your Philoſophical inquiries are but inquiries, things for the moſt part uncertain. But that wherein the ſtreſs of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51496:13"/>the difficulty lies, is the degree of certainty, by which we are aſſur'd that ſuch a thing is. And I ſay that the Divine Revelation, is infinitely more certain than the fulleſt teſtimony of Senſe; and that if I am ſatisfy'd that God has reveal'd a <hi>Trinity,</hi> I am more aſſur'd that there are Three Perſons in the Divine Nature, than I am aſſur'd that the Sun is a luminous, and the Earth a fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Body; though I could underſtand how the one ſhines, and how the other is actuated into ſo many ſeveral forms.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>Then now the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> will give you thanks: For this is the very <hi>Topick</hi> us'd in the famous caſe of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>This is one of the <hi>Socinian</hi> Common Places. But not to ſpend time about ſo little an objection, which will carry the digreſſion too far; let me tell you that a <hi>Topick</hi> may be good, but yet ill and falſly apply'd. In that diſpute be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them and us, we deny the Divine Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. We ſay, God has not reveal'd it. But to return:</p>
                  <p>You make a mighty noiſe with your diſtinction of <hi>Real</hi> and <hi>Nominal Trinitarians,</hi> and pretend that it is the natural reſult of ſeveral explications of the <hi>Trinity.</hi> To overthrow this at once, it is enough to ſay, that the Church owns no parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular explication of this <hi>Divine Myſtery;</hi> nor concerns herſelf with what private Authors have ſaid of it. The Church has ſpoke in general Councils, and National Synods. We have her Mind in her publick Confeſſions of Faith. She is ſo far from eſpouſing any ſort of explication, that ſhe ever thought that that great <hi>Myſtery</hi> could not be explain'd.</p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:51496:14"/>
                  <p>The Church ſuffers Men to write concerning theſe matters: St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> has given ſeveral con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable reaſons for it, in his Books on this very Subject, and in that <hi>de utilit. credend.</hi> The oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Hereſy, the improvement of Piety, the ſtudy of the Holy Scriptures, of which this makes ſo conſiderable a part, are the principal. But to think that the Church will ſtand by all the Opinions of private Writers, and own their errours and miſtakes, is a prodigious inadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency. What Church in the World can be ſafe, if made to anſwer for all the Authors of her Communion?</p>
                  <p>What becomes then of the objection? It is all overthrown in this one word. The Church has nothing to do with thoſe explications, which the <hi>Socinians</hi> fanſie they have ſo much expos'd. And as for the explications themſelves, I believe that if the Judicious <hi>Hooker,</hi> and the Learned <hi>Cudworth</hi> were alive, you durſt not ſo much as name them. The reſt are Men of great abilities, who can arm in their defence, no better Pens than their own.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>But do you put Biſhops, and eminent Biſhops too in the rank of private Perſons? Who can beſt ſpeak the ſence of the Church, but thoſe who are call'd by the Fathers, <hi>the Husbands of their Churches, the Keepers of the Canons, and the Succeſſors of the Apoſtles?</hi> Some ſeem to be <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts,</hi> and others ſeem to be <hi>Sabellians.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>Truly you have us'd the Biſhops in your Writings, as if they had been no more than private Perſons; the reflections on their <hi>Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips</hi> having been ſo ſharp and ſo many. <hi>His
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:51496:14"/>Grace</hi> the late Arch-Biſhop, whom by your own confeſſion you ought to have reverenc'd, was not free from your aſperſions. My Lord of <hi>Gloceſter</hi> has had his ſhare. In the lateſt anſwer to my Lord of <hi>Sarum,</hi> you forget the large <hi>Encomiums</hi> given him before. The Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> for whom the Learned World has ſo juſt a value, met in the anſwer to his late Book, with the ſame way of Entertainment. But laying all this aſide and anſwering your meaning; A Biſhop, with all the reſpect due to the Sacred Dignity, is ſtill a private Doctor. Nor can the Church be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable to his explications if they are contrary to her Doctrine. But what of all this? Our Biſhops are all <hi>Orthodox.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>I do not know what you mean by <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox.</hi> There is no <hi>Orthodoxy</hi> but Truth. They who teach Three Gods cannot be <hi>Orthodox;</hi> and this is done by the <hi>Real Trinitarians.</hi> The <hi>Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> believe and adore but one; and this is done by the <hi>Nominals.</hi> The greateſt part of the Church goes, I confeſs, that way, and therefore it is <hi>Orthodox</hi> becauſe <hi>Socinian.</hi> In ſhort, we may talk till Doom's day, and never be the Wiſer. The queſtion at laſt muſt be this, are you a <hi>Real,</hi> or a <hi>Nominal Trinitarian?</hi> If a <hi>Real,</hi> then we ſhall never be reconcil'd; If a <hi>Nominal,</hi> then we are certainly agreed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>What I have ſaid already ſeems to me to be ſatisfactory: But ſince you are not conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with it, let us examine the ſeveral parts of your diſtinction. What is the meaning of <hi>Real Trinitarians?</hi> But let me beg of you to anſwer plainly and directly.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:51496:15"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>I will anſwer in the very words of the Author of the Diſcourſe concerning them. He ſays, pag. 7. <hi>The Realiſts are denominated from their believing Three diſtinct Divine Spirits or Minds, who are ſo many Real ſubſiſting Perſons.</hi> Again p. 19. <hi>They are every day Challeng'd and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peach'd of Tritheiſm.</hi> And again p. 25. <hi>Them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves do ſometimes almoſt openly and explicitely own and profeſs their Tritheiſm.</hi> Their doctrine of the Trinity manifeſtly implies Three Gods.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>What is the meaning of <hi>Nominal Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitarians?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>They are they who maintain a Trinity which Conſiſts only in <hi>the ſeveral Names, Offices, Relations and Modes of Exiſtence of the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi> This was firſt taught by <hi>Noëtus</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellius;</hi> embrac'd afterwards by the aſſertors of the <hi>Homoouſios,</hi> and receiv'd by the Schools and Divinity Chairs ever ſince. This is the ſubſtance of what he ſays of the <hi>Nominals</hi> in the firſt part of the Diſcourſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>And this you make the Foundation of that difference which you imagine to be in the Church, and has of late fill'd up all your Prints.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes indeed, and with a great deal of Reaſon. You are all afraid of the diſtinction. It is of your ſide ſo notorious a giving up of the Cauſe, that we have parted with all our Old Arguments, and retrench'd our ſelves there, as in a place from whence we cannot be driven.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>Then pray, ſet your heart at reſt, and ſuffer your ſelves to be forc'd from it. For I preſume poſitively to averr that there is no ſuch
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:51496:15"/>thing in nature as theſe <hi>Trinitarians</hi> of your own making. You pretended already to a God of your own making: You wiſh'd for a Scripture of your own making: To make a <hi>Trinity</hi> too, is a little too hard. I ſay then, and pray forgive the ſharpneſs of the words, that all this is a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, a ſlander, and a calumny upon the Church.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>How much muſt you abate of your aſſurance, when I ſhew you in ſeveral late Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, that the Three Perſons of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> are Three diſtinct Infinite Minds, Spirits, and Subſtances? I appeal to your ſelf, whether this is not manifeſt <hi>Tritheiſm.</hi> For what is God, but an Infinite Mind, Spirit, or Subſtance?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>I have told you already, and tell you again, that ſuch expreſſions are wholly unknown to the Church; and therefore cannot with any candor be faſtn'd upon it. Oblige me ſo far as to ſhew me a Church in the World this day, or formerly, which uſes them; or elſe be pleas'd to own that you are guilty of a great deal of diſingenuity.</p>
                  <p>But though ſuch a denial is ſufficient, becauſe it is of a thing which you cannot, and dare not undertake to prove; yet it will be much clearer, if you give your ſelf the trouble to conſider, that ſuch a notion in the Chriſtian Church is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and has not the leaſt ground or appearance of truth. You are acquainted with the Sacred Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the New Teſtament, and no doubt have inform'd your ſelf, of the Confeſſions of Faith, of the Ancient Councils, the aſſertions of the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Fathers, the doctrine of the Schoolmen,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51496:16"/>the ſenſe of the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Church, even ſince the fatal ſeparation; and in the diviſion of ſo many Kingdoms, from the laſt in theſe two Ages, you know perfectly all the Articles which the Famous Societies of Proteſtants have declar'd to be the points of their belief. This ſuppos'd, I lay before you theſe plain and eaſy, but Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial Obſervations.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> That the Church of God, has always aſſerted the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of the Divine Nature as the Foundation of all Religion. It has been its great and diſtinguiſhing Character. You will tell me that the Philoſophers did ſo too; and that the <hi>Jews</hi> were witneſſes to all the World of this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Truth. I grant it. The Unity of God was the Fundamental Article of the <hi>Moſaical</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation. <hi>Pythagoras, Socrates, Plato, Ariſtotle,</hi> the <hi>Academicks,</hi> have ſpoke admirably well to it. But I ſay that <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> has been as far ſuperior to them in this point, as they themſelves exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the reſt of Mortals. For the <hi>Jews</hi> kept this to themſelves, without propagating it to others; and the wiſe Heathen confuting their doctrine by their practice, openly embrac'd <hi>Polytheiſm.</hi> None treated of God and his Divine Attributes, of which the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> is the Center, as the Holy <hi>Jeſus</hi> and his diſciples have done. This the Apoſtles ſpread through the World: This the Fathers taught indefatigably. <hi>One God, One Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Spirit, Mind, ſubſtance</hi> has been the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Voice of the Church. He is not a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> who believes not that God is one, and can be but one. If it were not too tedious I would produce ſome of their Authorities.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:51496:16"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>It is altogether needleſs. This is our very Doctrine. I am fully perſwaded of this, and infinitely pleas'd to hear you ſpeak ſo home to it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>I am afraid you will not be ſo well pleas'd with my ſecond obſervation, and it is this. That the ſame Church of God, which ſo Zealouſly aſſerted his <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> never did it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out aſſerting at the ſame time a <hi>Trinity</hi> of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in that <hi>One</hi> Divine Nature. No matter of fact which depends from Teſtimony, can be made to appear more inconteſtably true than this. You have a large Collection of Books at home. Let us ſtep to your Library, and I dare engage to convince you of this by the moſt exact induction of particulars, which can ever be made from the very <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> Creed to this time.</p>
                  <p>I ſay once more, and preſume to be poſitive in it, that the Church in delivering the Faith, ever taught the Exiſtence of God to be neceſſary and Eternal, and his <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> ſo perfect and entire, that it tranſcends what notion ſoever we have of Unity; even that which we call <hi>Numerical</hi> coming much ſhort of it: But at the ſame time ſhe taught and profeſs'd to believe and adore in that <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of Nature a <hi>Trinity</hi> of <hi>Hypoſtaſes</hi> or Perſons, the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit. Thus run the <hi>Apoſtolical,</hi> the <hi>Nicene, Epheſine,</hi> and <hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politan</hi> Creeds. Thus ſpeak the <hi>Ante-Nicene, Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene,</hi> and <hi>Poſt-Nicene</hi> Fathers. Thus all the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Schools, and all the now Churches in the World expreſs themſelves.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> But leaſt the belief of a <hi>Trinity</hi> of Perſons whoſe <hi>Coeternity</hi> and Coequality is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:51496:17"/>ſhould affect the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the Church has ſtated it in one and the ſame, indiviſible and inſeparable, ſimple and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compounded Eſſence. They are <hi>Coeternal</hi> and <hi>Coequal,</hi> becauſe <hi>Coeſſential.</hi> And they are <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſential</hi> becauſe Subſiſting in that Nature which cannot be multiply'd.</p>
                  <p>It is true to ſay of each Perſon that he is God; and yet it is falſe to ſay that they are Three Gods; The <hi>Trinity</hi> multiplying the Perſons, but the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> remaining the ſame, that is, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and moſt unconceivable <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> in the World. And therefore the Sacred Councils and the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have been carefull to the utmoſt to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh the <hi>Perſonality</hi> from the Nature; as afraid of multiplying the one, as of confounding the other.</p>
                  <p>You ſee then that the firſt member of your diſtinction is worth nothing. The charge laid againſt the Church in that particular is not only falſe but impoſſible. You have attempted to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide the Church of God into two Parties. The firſt you have accus'd of <hi>Tritheiſm,</hi> or of teaching the belief and Worſhip of Three Gods: Unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate in this, that the very expoſition of the Doctrine of the Church, the very reading of any one <hi>Creed,</hi> is an open confutation of what you have pretended to make us guilty of!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>I hope you will not take it ill, If I make ſome remarks as well as you. <hi>Firſt,</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that the <hi>Nicene</hi> and following Councils, ſpoke as you do, and that many of the <hi>Poſt-Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene</hi> Fathers, the Schoolmen and the preſent Churches agree with you in this, but I deny it of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:51496:17"/>the <hi>Apoſtolical Creed,</hi> which ought to have been the Form of all the reſt. Where can you find there a <hi>Trinity</hi> in <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity?</hi> Where can you ſee <hi>Coeternity, Coequality, Coeſſentiality,</hi> and all thoſe Famous Terms which the Church perſerv'd ever ſince? For my part I can perceive no ſuch thing. To this Creed we ſtand as to a rule left us by the Apoſtles themſelves. Suffer us to keep but that, and take you all the reſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> I challenge the <hi>Ante-Nicene</hi> Fathers; we ſay they are ſtrangers to your Doctrine. The Anſwer to Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> has made it invincibly appear. Have you taken notice how the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Author of that anſwer has diſcover'd the impoſtures of <hi>Pſeudo-Hermas,</hi> and the pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Epiſtles of <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Ignatius?</hi> What clear account he has given of the <hi>Nazarens, Mineans,</hi> and <hi>Alogi?</hi> And what a plain proof he has brought againſt your <hi>Trinity,</hi> and the <hi>Divinity</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> out of the Epiſtle of <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> to the Church of <hi>Corinth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Admitting all your allegations to be true; A <hi>Trinity</hi> in <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> Three Gods in one God, is a thing wholly unaccountable.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>The queſtion between you and me, is not whether it is unaccountable or not? The queſtion is whether thoſe whom you call <hi>Real Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitarians,</hi> have departed from the doctrine of the Unity of God, and have actually and manifeſtly, as you ſpeak, own'd their <hi>Tritheiſm?</hi> The matter of Fact, and not the Reaſonableneſs or Unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs of the thing, is the Point in diſpute. Your miſtake is Palpable. For the <hi>Trinity</hi> in <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> is not Three Gods in one God, a Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:51496:18"/>which the Church ever abhorr'd; but Three Perſons in one God, Three Subſiſtences in one Divine Nature. Pray name me one Man in the Church, even of thoſe who have moſt abounded in their own ſenſe, and ſpoke moſt looſly in the explication of our <hi>Myſteries,</hi> who was not as Zealous a defender of the Unity of God as your<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf can be.</p>
                  <p>This is then the moſt unpardonable want of Candor imaginable. You call me a <hi>Tritheiſt.</hi> I deny it. You prove it, becauſe I believe the Bleſſed <hi>Trinity.</hi> I own I do. Then you exclaim, I believe Three Gods, The Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit. I ſay, No! For though the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is God, the Son is God, and the Holy Ghoſt God, yet they are but one God. For God can be but one. The Divine Nature is incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Multiplication, Diviſion, or Augmentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. You may, and will urge again that this is very unreaſonable. I hope to ſhew you one day that it is highly Rational. But in the mean time I gain the point, and complain that you do me wrong, and are inexcuſable in charging me with deſtroying the Unity of God.</p>
                  <p n="2">2ly. You are poſitive that the Ante-Nicene Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers aſſerted the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> but not the <hi>Trinity.</hi> I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe you mean in our ſence of a <hi>Trinity,</hi> or elſe the miſtake is not pardonable. Origen <hi>and other Ante-Nicenes make out the</hi> Unity <hi>of</hi> God, <hi>in a</hi> Ternary <hi>of</hi> Perſons, <hi>though they did not believe the</hi> Equality. Says the Author of the Anſwer to Dr. <hi>Bull,</hi> pag. 22. unjuſt in this to <hi>Origen,</hi> and the reſt. I have ſome Remarks on that Anſwer which I deſign to make publick. What the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:51496:18"/>Author has ſaid concerning the Epiſtle of St. <hi>Barnabas,</hi> and thoſe of the Holy Martyr <hi>Ignatius,</hi> is far from invalidating their Authority. We muſt have more than ſuſpicions and bare denials to illegitimate a Book. They are certainly works of great Antiquity, and acknowledg'd to be ſuch by the ſucceeding Ages.</p>
                  <p>But what muſt we ſay of a Perſon, of his great erudition, who pretending to anſwer a Book full of all the Teſtimonies which thoſe early times could afford, quarrels only with two or three Authors, againſt whom he ſays nothing ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial; and is wholly ſilent to <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> St. <hi>Irenaeus, Clemens Alexandrinus, Tatianus, Milti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ades, Melito, Dionyſius of Alexandria, Tertullian, Lactantius,</hi> &amp;c. Is it enough to confute the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te-Nicene</hi> Fathers to ſay as this Author, pag. 7. <hi>That all their Glory is wholly due to the vanity of Modern Learned Men; who quote theſe Books, not becauſe they value them, but becauſe being an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient monuments known to few, and underſtood by fewer, he ſeems to be a great Learned Man, who can drop ſentences out of theſe antique Books.</hi> But this is mild and obliging, if compar'd with <hi>pag.</hi> 63. Where this Author, having ſaid that <hi>Trinitaria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm</hi> is not ſo much a Religion, as the Law of the <hi>Byzantine,</hi> or <hi>Conſtantinopolitan</hi> Emperours, ſtiles the then Doctors of the Church, <hi>THE</hi> PARASITES <hi>OF THESE TIMES, whom now in regard of their antiquity we call Fathers.</hi> You are not inſenſible how this might be taken up and expos'd? If <hi>Hoſius, Spiridio, Paphnutius;</hi> If the <hi>Gregories,</hi> the <hi>Baſils,</hi> the <hi>Cyrils,</hi> the <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rets,</hi> the <hi>Chryſoſtoms,</hi> the <hi>Hieroms,</hi> the <hi>Hilaries,</hi>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:51496:19"/>the <hi>Ambroſes,</hi> the <hi>Auſtins</hi> were the <hi>Paraſites</hi> of their times, where ſhall we find any Vertue, Piety, or Learning in this World?</p>
                  <p>But I am willing to over-look thoſe exceſſes, and tell you that it is a folly to wrangle with this or that paſſage; ſometimes to inveigh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Platoniciſm,</hi> and ſometimes to complain that thoſe Writings are loſt, which might have inform'd us better. To be plain, we have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough left, and from what remains of the times before the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> it appears that the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of God, and the belief of a <hi>Trinity</hi> of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in that one God, Father, Son, and Holy Spirit, was the belief of the Chriſtian Church. The <hi>Arrians</hi> indeed might challenge ſome of the then Fathers, who ſpoke more obſcurely, and were eaſier Miſinterpreted. But <hi>Socinianiſm</hi> has not the leaſt pretence to any. He muſt have forfeited all modeſty who aſſerts it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>But what have you to ſay to the <hi>Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical</hi> Creed? Is it not an evidence beyond all other evidences?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>Of what?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>Of the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of the Great God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>And ſo are all our Creeds from the firſt to the laſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>But it is an Evidence againſt your <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>Againſt that <hi>Trinity</hi> which you have falſly imputed to us, and that is, A <hi>Trinity</hi> of Gods: But not againſt a <hi>Trinity</hi> of Perſons in one God. What is the firſt aſſertion of that Creed? <hi>I believe in</hi> One <hi>God.</hi> For you affirm that it was anciently thus read, <hi>Anſ. to Doctor</hi> Bull <hi>pag.</hi> 16.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:51496:19"/>What is the ſecond, but an Explication of the firſt? This One God is the Father Almighty; His only begotten Son Jeſus Chriſt, and the Holy Spirit, Three Perſons in One God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>This is ſo dragg'd in, ſo ſtrain'd, ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural, that to any unprejudic'd Perſon, it will viſibly appear not to be the Doctrine deſign'd to be taught in the Creed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>I am apt to think that I can ſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally prove that it is. I believe the Creed to be truly <hi>Apoſtolical,</hi> notwithſtanding what ſome learned Men have ſaid againſt it; Not becauſe it was made by the Apoſtles themſelves, though nothing appears to the contrary, but by reaſon of its great Antiquity. Now when you and I diſpute about the ſence and deſign of that Creed, we have but one way to take, and that is, Firſt to ſee what the Scripture teaches concerning its Articles, which indeed are no more than an <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome,</hi> or Collection of the Principal Truths de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd by <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his Apoſtles. Secondly, To examine the Doctrine of the Fathers who liv'd before the Church thought it fit and neceſſary to make a larger Explanation of the Faith. Thirdly, To ſatisfy our ſelves of the ſence which the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately following Councils gave to that Creed in their Decrees.</p>
                  <p>All this is Highly reaſonable. For if the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture which has taught ſo expreſly God to be <hi>one,</hi> has alſo expreſly taught the <hi>Father</hi> to be God, the <hi>Son</hi> God, and the <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> God, then it is plain, that the ſence of the Creed is ſuch, and no other. The Authority of that Creed, or of any Creed whatever, is from the Scripture. It can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:51496:20"/>therefore be contrary to it, and that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Rule muſt be brought to that Primitive Rule from whence it is deriv'd. And alas! has not this been prov'd to you ſo often and ſo fully, that after a World of wrangling you have been dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven from your new and unnatural <hi>Criticiſms,</hi> and forc'd to ſhelter your ſelves under the weak de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of your <hi>Philoſophical</hi> diſceptations?</p>
                  <p>But if this Creed has no other ſence but that which you put upon it, <hi>The Father only God, The Son only Man, and the Holy Spirit only an Energy or Operation;</hi> How come the Fathers of that time ſo openly to contradict it? I will not do again, what has been ſo excellently done by the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Dr. <hi>Bull,</hi> who has oblig'd the Chriſtian Church with two Books, which indeed you may ſpeak or diſcourſe againſt, but can never ſubſtantially An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. Has he not undeniably prov'd out of their Writings, that thoſe Fathers believ'd the two Natures in Jeſus Chriſt. The Divine and the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man? That they have aſſerted his Pre-exiſtence, and if his Pre-exiſtence, then his Eternity, and if his Eternity, then his Conſubſtantiality with the Father.</p>
                  <p>If the ſecond part of the Creed is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of <hi>Chriſt</hi> only Man, How comes <hi>Irenaeus lib.</hi> 1. <hi>adverſ. Haereſ. c.</hi> 2. in delivering the Belief of the <hi>Catholick</hi> Church, or as he ſpeaks, of the Church all the World over, to call him <hi>Our Lord,</hi> Our God, <hi>Our Saviour, Our King, to whom every Knee ought to bow,</hi> &amp;c. How comes <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian,</hi> who has deliver'd this very rule of Faith, to talk as we do of the Bleſſed <hi>Trinity,</hi> deſignedly and poſitively againſt <hi>Praxeas,</hi> and ſay, <hi>that he is
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:51496:20"/>warranted by the Apoſtle to ſpeak of Chriſt as of him who is God, bleſſed over all for ever?</hi> If he believ'd the Holy Spirit to be only an <hi>Energy,</hi> How comes he to ſtile him, <hi>Tertium Numen Deitatis, &amp; ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium Nomen Majeſtatis, The Third Perſon of the Deity, The Third Name of Majeſty and Power.</hi> Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly <hi>Novatianus</hi> was acquainted with this Creed, and yet <hi>Lib. de Trin. c.</hi> 13. he tells you, <hi>that the Scriptures deliver ſo</hi> Manifeſtly <hi>Chriſt to be God, that ſeveral Hereticks,</hi> Divinitatis ipſius magnitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine &amp; veritate commoti, mov'd by the great ſence and truth of his Divinity, <hi>have confounded him with the Father.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But if we had no ſuch proofs as theſe, there is ſtill one which according to your late Principles you cannot oppoſe. I ſay, your late Principles, for you change every day.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>No! You do us wrong; we are ſtill the ſame.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>I may, at ſome time or other, have an occaſion to prove the defection of the Outlandiſh <hi>Socinians</hi> from <hi>Socinus;</hi> of you from the Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landiſh <hi>Socinians;</hi> and of your ſelves from your ſelves in your firſt and lateſt Prints. But let us not digreſs from the thing in diſpute. The proof which I ſpeak of is the great Council of <hi>Nice.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>What? That Council which has pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd, Eſtabliſh'd, and infected the World with its infidelity. As the Anſwer to Dr. <hi>Bull,</hi> judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly obſerves, <hi>pag.</hi> 25.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>That firſt <hi>Oecumenical</hi> Council which could not be ignorant both of the ſenſe of the <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> Creed, and of the Fathers whom they
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:51496:21"/>immediately ſucceeded. A Council ſo venerable for its Antiquity, ſo reverenc'd for the number of Holy and Learned Men, who voted in it, ſo highily honour'd by the following Ages to this day! Did they know the <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> Creed, or did they not? If you ſay, they did not, you over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw all that you can pretend from it. A Creed can neither be <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> or Univerſal which the Nicene Fathers were not acquainted with. And if they did, then your ſenſe of it is not that of theſe Primitive times. For they are ſo far from interpreting as you do, Jeſus Chriſt to be only Man, and the Holy Spirit to be only an <hi>Energy,</hi> or operation, that you know how poſitively, how earneſtly they aſſert them to be <hi>Conſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial</hi> to the Father. I may be miſtaken, but if this way of reaſoning is not plain, I don't know what can be plain.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>But what have we to do with the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Nice,</hi> or indeed with any Council whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever? We have innumerable objections againſt that and the following Councils.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>I confeſs you ſpeak as a <hi>Socinian</hi> of the firſt edition. Thus <hi>Socinus</hi> and his firſt Diſciples anſwer'd to thoſe great Authorities. Thus did your ſelves Write in your firſt Prints. The World indeed ſtar'd at you. But however it had an air, if not of reaſon, at leaſt of ſincerity. But a <hi>Socinian</hi> of the ſecond edition runs another way. I told you that you change every day. Pray open the Diſcourſe concerning <hi>the Real and Nominal Trinitarians.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>What then?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>There you may ſind your Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:51496:21"/>in that particular out of your own mouth. <hi>Pag.</hi> 4. The Author ſpeaking of the Great <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teran</hi> Council obſerves that a doctrine is not Hereſy, becauſe rejected by a great number of Learned Men, or by a National Council; <hi>But only when cenſur'd by a General Council. The Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church is never underſtood to ſpeak but by a General Council.</hi> pag. 5. <hi>Is not a General Council the Higheſt Court of the Church? Her Canons de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the Faith, her Anathema's Hereſy.</hi> And pag. 16. <hi>A General Council is the laſt Tribunal on earth from which there lies no appeal.</hi> pag. 4. He call this an <hi>Inconteſtable Argument.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now pray deal ſincerely and apply this to the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council. No body ever yet diſputed its univerſality. It was aſſembl'd under and by the firſt Chriſtian Emperor. It repreſented the whole Church. The Creed then of that Council determin'd the ſenſe of any preceeding Creed. Whatever you can ſay to the contrary is inſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficant, becauſe ſuch a determination comes <hi>from the higheſt Tribunal on earth, from which there lies no appeal.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Upon the whole the Church ever aſſerted a <hi>Trinity</hi> conſiſtent with the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of God, and an Unity inſeparable from a <hi>Trinity</hi> of Perſons in one adorable and Divine Nature. Where is then again, the firſt part of your Diſtinction? You charge us with teaching a <hi>Trinity</hi> which infers Three Gods. We ſay this is falſe, this is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, not only from the Nature of the thing, but alſo from an Authority which you dare not reject, becauſe you own your ſelves, that <hi>it is the higheſt Tribunal on earth, from which there can lie no appeal.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:51496:22"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>This ſeems home indeed: But yet not without exception: For the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> aſſerted by the <hi>Nicene</hi> and <hi>Poſt-Nicene</hi> Fathers, was only an <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of <hi>Monarchy:</hi> An <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of love and agreement: An <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of ſubordination, and ſubjection to him who is the firſt God. Such an <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> as is that of the Individuals of the ſame <hi>Species.</hi> This the Author of the Anſwer to Dr. <hi>Bull</hi> is poſitive in <hi>pag.</hi> 75. He charges the Fathers with this all over his Writing, and the greateſt part of it is ſpent in the confutation of ſuch ſtrange <hi>Hypotheſes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>Pray learn to miſtruſt your Books. For I may ſay without breaking the <hi>Cartel</hi> of honour, and civility agreed upon amongſt Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, as this Author ſpeaks both Pleaſantly and Elegantly, <hi>pag.</hi> 77. that not one word of this is true; and that ſuch an account of the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of God never came from the Church, but owes its birth to the School of <hi>Arrius.</hi> This Author, though a Perſon of great erudition, has ſuffer'd himſelf to be ſtrangely miſtaken; as any one may, who will take all the expreſſions, illuſtrations, reſemblances us'd by the Fathers in treating of the Bleſſed Trinity, for an exact account of their Doctrine. For there is a great difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween ſpeaking at large, and endeavouring to give ſome kind of a Notion of a <hi>Myſtery,</hi> and writing dogmatically concerning it.</p>
                  <p>I have a plain reaſon, which I humbly conceive is ſufficient to overthrow all this: And that is, that the Fathers in explaining how the Three Perſons are one God, never confin'd themſelves to the Terms of <hi>Numerical</hi> or <hi>ſpecifick <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</hi> This laſt is meerly Notional, and is no more
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:51496:22"/>than an act of the Mind, comparing and abſtract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from ſeveral Individuals. It does not really exiſt. The firſt though never ſo expreſſive ſtill comes ſhort of the incomprehenſible dignity and ſimplicity of the Subject.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>What <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> then did they aſſert?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>An <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> which no Nature but the Divine is capable of, which tranſcends all expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions or imaginations. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; ſays the Council of <hi>Epheſus.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; ſays <hi>Juſtin Martyr; Hoc ſolum ex ea comprehendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, quod comprehendi non poteſt;</hi> ſays St. <hi>Ambroſe.</hi> Thus ſpeak <hi>Baſil</hi> the Great, <hi>Nazianzen, Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory Nyſſen,</hi> and the generality of the Fathers. And yet this Author has ſpent 13 <hi>pages,</hi> to tell us that they believ'd a <hi>ſpecifick <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity;</hi> and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of Monarchy and order, an <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of love and agreement, a Conſubſtantiality like that of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral pieces of Gold, and of a Star to another Star. As if theſe trifles deſerv'd the name of Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible, and if we could ſay of any of them as <hi>Eulogius Patriarch</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Not bringing thoſe things which are ſo far above our thoughts to the ſcrutiny of human Reaſonings.</hi> Do all theſe <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nities</hi> tranſcend the capacity of Human Nature? Are they above the reach of an inquiſitive Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, or a profound Divine?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>I confeſs that you ſtartle me, and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to have no great opinion of the firſt part of the diſtinction: I ſee you are no <hi>Tritheiſts,</hi> but then you muſt of courſe fall into <hi>Nominaliſm</hi> or <hi>Sabellianiſm,</hi> and that is as bad. I am afraid, that part of the charge will ſtick cruelly againſt you.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:51496:23"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>The notion of <hi>Nominal Trinitarians</hi> is, if poſſible, more extravagant than the other. Can you think in good earneſt that the Ancient or modern Church, if ſuch an expreſſion may be us'd, for the Church is always the ſame: Can you think, I ſay, that the Church in the firſt and in theſe laſt Ages, oppos'd <hi>Sabellianiſm,</hi> with ſo much Zeal and Vigor, that is, that very im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety which you faſten on her, and condemn'd it, with ſo unanimous a conſent, and yet would make it the foundation of her Faith? The vaſt labours of the Fathers, and of all the Doctors who ſucceeded them, aim'd at this, to aſſert a Real diſtinction of Perſons againſt <hi>Sabellius,</hi> and their <hi>Conſubſtantiality, Coequality</hi> and <hi>Coeternity</hi> againſt <hi>Arrius.</hi> And you come reſolutely to tell us, that for all that the Church is <hi>Sabellian,</hi> and teaches <hi>Sabellianiſm.</hi> How heartily would you laugh at a Man, who ſhould come to tell you, that he has attentively read all the <hi>Socinian</hi> Prints, and finds at laſt that they believe the Holy <hi>Trinity</hi> and the Divinity of our Saviour?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>Had they ſaid ſo much for theſe two Articles as you have for <hi>Sabellianiſm</hi> in all your Books, I proteſt, I could not laugh at it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>Let us ſee then what is <hi>Sabellianiſm,</hi> and if found in the Church, I promiſe to give up the cauſe. But if not, I expect that you will have the juſtice to own that to charge us with it, is a crying unſincerity. We cannot have the ſenſe of <hi>Sabellius,</hi> better than from <hi>Dionyſius</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> the other <hi>Dionyſius</hi> of <hi>Rome, Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius,</hi> St. <hi>Baſil, Nazianzen, Ruffinus,</hi> &amp;c. You will Learn from them that <hi>Sabellius,</hi> own'd the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:51496:23"/>Divine Nature, but confounded the <hi>Hypoſtaſes</hi> or Perſons and maintain'd one only Perſon, or Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſis the Father. And that when they objected to him the different operations of the Son, and Holy Spirit, he anſwer'd, that they were only denominations of the Father reſulting from his ſeveral appearances, or offices to us. If you miſtruſt this account, take what the Author of the diſcourſe ſays, pag. 16. <hi>In a word,</hi> ſays he, the <hi>Noëtians and Sabellians held that God is but one ſubſiſting Perſon, yet that with reſpect to things with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him he may be call'd, as the modern Nominals now ſpeak, three Relative Perſons.</hi> The one <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting Perſon of God ſuſtains the three names of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son, and Spirit, which being the Relations of God towards things without him, he is ſo many Relative Perſons in a Claſſical Critical ſenſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now I will do more for you than you can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect. I will not confine you to our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors. But I dare you to produce any one Man in the Church of God, who ever underſtood thoſe matters and ſpoke at this rate. But if you do not, as I am poſitive that you cannot, what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes of your diſtinction, and with what face can it be us'd any more?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>I will not go out of the Kingdom, no, not out of <hi>London</hi> for it. Dr. <hi>South</hi> ſhall be the Man. You will not deny that he underſtands the ſenſe of the Church. He ſays himſelf animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſ. <hi>ch.</hi> 8. <hi>pa.</hi> 242. <q rend="inline">And this I affirm to be the current doctrine both of the Fathers and the Schools concerning the Perſons of the Bleſſed <hi>Trinity,</hi> and the conſtantly receiv'd account given by them of a Divine Perſon, ſo far
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:51496:24"/>as they pretend to explain what ſuch a Perſon is.</q> 
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 240. He tells you, <q rend="inline">That the commonly receiv'd Doctrine of the Schools concerning the Bleſſed <hi>Trinity</hi> is this. That the Chriſtian Faith has laid this ſure foundation, that there is but one God. That there is no poſitive real Being ſtrictly and properly ſo call'd in God, but what is God. That there can be no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition in the Deity with any ſuch poſitive real Being, diſtinct from the Deity it ſelf. And yet that the Church finding in Scripture menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Three to whom diſtinctly the Godhead does belong, has by warrant of the ſame Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. expreſs'd theſe Three by the names of Perſons, and ſtated their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonalities upon three diſtinct Modes of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence alloted to one and the ſame Godhead, and theſe alſo diſtinguiſh'd by three diſtinct Relations.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then <hi>pag.</hi> 241. To explain theſe modes of Subſiſtence and theſe Relations, he tells you, <q rend="inline">That they are neither ſubſtance nor accident. That they are not a Being, but only the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Being, and that they add no entity to it, ſuch as are dependance, mutability, preſence, abſence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And that they have no Exiſtence of their own after a ſeparation, or diviſion from the things or beings to which they do belong.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Having thus in general explain'd what a mode is, he applys it, <hi>pag.</hi> 242. And ſays that the Perſonalities by which the <hi>Deity</hi> ſtands Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſify'd into three diſtinct Perſons are call'd and accounted Modes .... That every Perſon is properly the Godhead as ſubſiſting with and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch a certain Mode or Relation.</p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:51496:24"/>
                  <p>Now put all this together, and ſee whether this is not the very Doctrine of <hi>Sabellius.</hi> Did not <hi>Sabellius</hi> ſay, that God is one, even the Father acting under ſeveral Names, ſuſtaining ſeveral Relations, by which he ſometimes is the Father, and ſometimes the Son? What does Dr. <hi>South</hi> ſay more? He muſt be very clear ſighted who can perceive any difference between theſe two <hi>Hypotheſes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>There is as much difference as between affirming and denying; between Light and Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. <hi>Sabellius</hi> admits only <hi>one</hi> Perſon in the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature; Dr. <hi>South</hi> Three. When <hi>Sabellius</hi> by the great evidence of Scripture is forc'd to own Three Perſons, and confeſs the Relations, He will have them to be Perſons <hi>only in a Claſſical Critical ſence,</hi> having no other but a <hi>Metaphorical</hi> being. He confounds the Perſons, and makes the Son and the Holy Spirit to be the Father.</p>
                  <p>Dr. <hi>South</hi> affirms them to be Perſons in a Real Sence, <hi>by an Eternal Communication of the Divine Nature,</hi> and ſo really diſtinct, that the Son can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be the Father; or the Holy Spirit, Father or Son; or the Father, Son, or Holy Spirit.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sabellius</hi> makes the Relations to be wholly <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſecal,</hi> as he ſuſtains the Three Names of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son, and Spirit, <hi>which being the Relations of God towards things without him, he is ſo many Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Perſons.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Dr. <hi>South</hi> affirms <hi>pag.</hi> 242. the Relations to be <hi>Intrinſecal,</hi> founded upon thoſe Internal Acts by which one Perſon produces another, or proceeds from another. He tells you, that God may ſuſtain an extrinſecal Relation founded upon
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:51496:25"/>ſome external act iſſuing from him, as <hi>Creation, Preſervation,</hi> &amp;c. Which adds to the Deity on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly an <hi>extrinſecal</hi> denomination, as of <hi>Creator, Preſerver,</hi> &amp;c. But that this leaves <hi>an Internal incommunicable Character eſſentially inſeparable from the Deity.</hi> That it may be ſaid, that God might never have been a Creator: But that it cannot be ſaid that he might never have been a Father; the former being only an effect of his will, <hi>but this latter the neceſſary reſult of his Nature.</hi> This you have, <hi>pag.</hi> 243.</p>
                  <p>But that which ſinks for ever this miſerable imputation of <hi>Sabellianiſm</hi> or <hi>Nominaliſm,</hi> call it which you pleaſe, is the noble Principle which this Learned and worthy Man has laid down. <hi>Animadv. p.</hi> 245. in which as in the reſt he has truly ſpoke the ſence of the Church.</p>
                  <q>Upon the whole matter, in diſcourſing of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> two things are abſolutely neceſſary to be held and inſiſted upon. One, that each and every Perſon of the Bleſſed <hi>Trinity</hi> entirely contains and includes in himſelf the whole Divine Nature The other, that each Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is incommunicably different and diſtinct from one another.</q>
                  <p>I thought you look'd diſſatisfy'd when ſpeaking of this famous diſtinction of <hi>Realiſts</hi> and <hi>Nominals,</hi> I us'd the words of ſlander, calumny, diſinge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity; Let me now beg of you to give it a name.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>Truly I muſt be forc'd to tell you, that I ſaw this diſtinction urg'd ſo often, our late Prints ſo full of it, and honeſt Mr. <hi>E.</hi> valuing himſelf ſo highly upon it, that I thought it was
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:51496:25"/>more ſolid than really it is. I will take time to conſider of what you have ſaid to it. When I have next the happineſs to ſee you, you ſhall have my Thoughts of it. In the mean time ....</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>No: I cannot leave you yet. I muſt before we part, complain of another injuſtice which your Friends have done us.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>What is that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>That which My Lord Biſhop of <hi>Sarum</hi> calls in his Paſtoral Letter, <hi>the heavieſt of all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations; that they ſubmit to his Lordſhip's whole doctrine which differs in nothing from what the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians profeſs'd in all their Writings.</hi> That is to ſay in plain Engliſh, that he is a <hi>Socinian.</hi> A cruel and barbarous ſort of a compliment to a <hi>Catholick,</hi> and an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Biſhop! They do the ſame in effect to My Lord of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> in their laſt Anſwer to his <hi>Lordſhips</hi> Book, <hi>pag.</hi> 62. To the Univerſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> to Dr. <hi>South,</hi> whom they call in deriſion <hi>Brother South,</hi> as they had done Dr. <hi>Wallis, Father Wallis.</hi> In the Anſwer to My Lord of <hi>Chicheſter</hi> they ſpeak very plain, <hi>pag.</hi> 27.</p>
                  <q>It is, ſay they, by this Declaration of our meaning, that all our Books, <hi>Paſt, or to come,</hi> are to be interpreted. We never intend to oppoſe any Body in the Article of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> but the <hi>Tritheiſts,</hi> or <hi>Realiſts,</hi> who are Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks to the Church as well as to us, nor in the Article of the Divinity of our Saviour, but the <hi>Eutychians,</hi> who make the Communication of Idioms to be Real, and not only Verbal, which is an Heterodoxy condemn'd in divers General Councils.</q>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:51496:26"/>
                  <p>That word, <hi>General Councils,</hi> which they eſteem'd ſo little before, is now of great value. They tell this very Biſhop, <q rend="inline">that they do not in the leaſt ſuſpect that he will diſown the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Doctrine, and be of a Party of Hereticks, who have been Condemn'd by ſo many Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Councils.</q>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>Well: and where lies the injuſtice of all this? If the <hi>Socinians</hi> are become <hi>Orthodox,</hi> and embrace the Doctrine of the Church, is it not an honour to theſe Great Men to have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon'd them into this Submiſſion? I remember that in ſome of our Prints, we have call'd the Biſhop of <hi>Sarum</hi> the <hi>Euſebius</hi> of the Age. As the Famous <hi>Euſebius</hi> brought over many Biſhops to the ſubſcribing the <hi>Homoouſion;</hi> Is it the heavieſt of all imputations to his <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> that he has perſwaded the <hi>Socinians</hi> out of their Errors? Muſt you your ſelf take it ill, that Perſons, of whom I have heard you often give a great Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, ſhould return to the Faith and Obedience of the Church? All that I diſlike in thoſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements is, the <hi>Books paſt, or to come.</hi> For the <hi>Books paſt,</hi> ſpeak no ſuch thing, and I fear the <hi>Books to come</hi> will not much mend the matter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>I did not expect that you would not be ſerious in ſo mighty a concern as this. I confeſs that it would be to me, and to all good Men, an incredible ſatisfaction to ſee an end of this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy. But I tell you, there is no ſincerity in all this. They are no more return'd to the Sence and Faith of the Church than you are. They build ſtill upon that fooliſh diſtinction of <hi>Realiſts,</hi> or <hi>Tritheïſts,</hi> and <hi>Nominals,</hi> or <hi>Sabellians.</hi> The
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:51496:26"/>firſt is a Monſter of their own making. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> other is a ſhelter to their <hi>Heterodoxy</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> they maintain a <hi>Trinity</hi> which is no <hi>Trinity</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſtrive to advance error under her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Pillar of Truth. In ſhort; If the <hi>Trinity</hi> believ'd and taught by the Church is <hi>Sabellia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ſm,</hi> they are your humble ſervants. It is that that they would cover <hi>Socinianiſm</hi> by. But how can they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve as the Church, when the doctrine which they pretend to return to, is that to which the Church is irreconcilable?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>How muſt they do then to convince you that they ſincerely deſire a peace and are come over to you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>By writing with that reſpect which is due to Biſhops of whom in the Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Edwards, pag.</hi> 13. they own the inſtitution to be of Divine right. Let them receive the <hi>Catholick</hi> Creeds, that of the Great <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> the <hi>Doxology,</hi> and the Articles of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lang.</hi> Then and not before I will believe that they are ſincere.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>Theſe are large ſtrides. I am not for running ſo faſt. Suffer me to take my leave of you. I will think on what we have diſcours'd, and then you ſhall hear from me. Adieu.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="dialogue">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:51496:27"/>
               <head>The Second DIALOGUE.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>I had promis'd my ſelf the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſeeing you before this.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>Truly I deſign'd it, but was reſolv'd not to do it, till I had been as good as my word; that is, till I had conſider'd what we diſcours'd of ſome days ſince. For whatever you may think of me I have a ſenſe of Religion. I am fully convinc'd, that there is a God to whom I owe all my ſervice, and a future ſtate of happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and miſery, on which I cannot reflect with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a mighty concern. I am not ſo much an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy to my own intereſt as to cheat my ſelf of the one; and willfully to fall into the other.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>What is the reſult then of your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>To ſpeak ſincerely my Thoughts, I am come off from the diſtinction of Real and Nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Trinitarians;</hi> and do you the juſtice to own that it appears to me to be ill grounded. Though I believe at the ſame time that he who firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented it, did it, <hi>bona fide;</hi> and had the occaſion gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him by the inadvertency of your own Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. But there are ſtill two difficulties in my way which I cannot overcome. I would not be thought to ſuſpect your Learning, or Candor; But I am afraid you cannot reſolve them.</p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:51496:27"/>
                  <p>The firſt is this. If you are neither for a Real, nor a Nominal <hi>Trinity;</hi> then you are for no <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> at all. For there is no <hi>medium</hi> between them. The ſecond is, that in what ſenſe ſoever you hold a <hi>Trinity,</hi> I cannot believe it. A <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> of Perſons of which every one is God, and yet but one God, is to me the moſt abſurd noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the World. I have ſtudy'd the matter with as much application as I can. But to me it ſtill appears to be a perpetual affront to Reaſon, and good ſenſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>Give me leave to tell you that the firſt is no difficulty at all. The Church believes a Real <hi>Trinity;</hi> Not in that ſenſe of <hi>Real,</hi> which your Friends have made ſo much noiſe about, and ſo unjuſtly imputed to us, which infers three Gods; But in that ſenſe which in the aſſerting three Divine Perſons, preſerves ſtill the Unity of the Divine Nature. To ſpeak plainly, and prevent that wrangling to which obſcurity gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally leads Men; what the Church propoſes to our belief conſiſts in this.</p>
                  <p>The Unity of God is ſo clearly prov'd both by Reaſon, and the Authority of the Sacred Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, that there is not in the World a truer, or a plainer aſſertion than this. <hi>God is one, and can be but one.</hi> But the ſame Sacred Writings ſpeaking of the <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>Son,</hi> and the <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> and giving thoſe Characters of them by which they appear incommunicably diſtinct from one another; It makes this ſecond aſſertion. <hi>The Father is not the Son, or the Holy Spirit. Nor the Son the Father, or the Holy Spirit. Nor the Holy Spirit, Father, or Son.</hi> But the Scripture being
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:51496:28"/>expreſs and poſitive in giving to every one of theſe Perſons the Name, Nature, Attributes, and Operations of God, there ariſes a third aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion. <hi>The Father is God, the Son God, and the Holy Ghoſt God.</hi> But the firſt of theſe propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſtanding unmoveable, and God ceaſing to be, if he ceaſes to be one; All at laſt are reſolv'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Fourth; That <hi>in that ONE adorable and Divine Nature are Father, Son and Holy Spirit, every one God, and yet but ONE God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is the Real <hi>Trinity</hi> which the Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves; which the Apoſtles have taught; For which the Martyrs dy'd; and notwithſtanding all the oppoſitions of <hi>Hereticks</hi> has obtain'd, and will obtain to the end of the World. I cannot read the Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory, but I adore the veracity of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and ſee in that very particular the fullfilling of his promiſe to the Church, that <hi>the Gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt Her.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Your ſecond difficulty is as eaſily reſolv'd as the firſt. For how can that be an affront to Reaſon and good Senſe, which God has com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded us to believe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>There muſt be a great deal more in it, than what you have laid down. Vaſt many Books have been written on this Subject. You are not ignorant how from the firſt and interme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate ages of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> to this time, it has been the ground of irreconcilable diſputes. I do not ſpeak only when the Emperours eſpous'd the Cauſe, and this or that Opinion prevail'd, becauſe it was the Religion of the Court: But I ſpeak of the retirements of the Schools, where the diſpute was furious; and the Doctors more ſet
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:51496:28"/>one againſt another, than <hi>Marius</hi> and <hi>Sylla, Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> and <hi>Pompey.</hi> This grand and Myſterious Contradiction, has given birth to infinite Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions, which like the <hi>Hydra</hi>'s head, multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply daily without number. The <hi>Socinians</hi> in that Print of theirs, call'd <hi>A Letter of Reſolution concerning the Doctrines of the Trinity and Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> pag. 10. have charg'd this home upon you. <q rend="inline">The Author tells you roundly, that there is no fewer than fifteen diviſions amongſt you; each diviſion conſiſting of two Parties at the leaſt, ſome of them of four or five. So that they are in all, about forty Parties of them.</q> A ſtrong Argument by the way againſt the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of the Church!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>What I have propos'd to you, is the ſimplicity of the Revelation. God has reveal'd ſo much, and in that there is enough to ſatisfy our ſelves. The diſingenuity of the Author of that Letter appears in this, that he talks of divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and Parties, and pretends to enumerate them; whereas there never was any about this.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>Can you think that a Learned Perſon, as this Author is, durſt have the confidence to aſſure ſuch a thing, if he had not very good grounds for it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>Call it what you pleaſe: I dare to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verr that he has none at all. But to make this clear, I muſt needs tell you, that in a Revelation two things are to be conſider'd. The one is the thing reveal'd; as in this caſe, <hi>the Father is God, the Son God, and the Holy Spirit God, and yet not three, but one God.</hi> The other is the manner how theſe things are, which are reveal'd? How the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:51496:29"/>Father is a Father, how the Son is a Son, how the Holy Spirit proceeds from Father and Son? How every one of theſe is God, and yet but one God? I dare ſay that there has not been, nor can never be a more univerſal agreement than there has been in the firſt. Had we been contented to adore and believe, there had never been any Schiſms or Diviſions in that particular. But Man will be curious, pretend to unfold <hi>Myſteries,</hi> and clearly ſee into his Nature, <hi>who has made darkneſs his Pavilion round about him.</hi> He muſt of courſe receive the puniſhment due to his Preſumption, and inſtead of that noble pleaſure which reſults from knowing, meet with all the ſad conſequences of a confident ignorance.</p>
                  <p>Any one moderately acquainted with Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Learning, will ſee that this has been the conduct of the Church, to ſtick to that firſt part as certain and undoubted, and not at all to meddle with the other as full of danger. This is viſible in all the confeſſions of Faith of the Primitive Councils, which are full in aſſerting the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of God, and the <hi>Trinity</hi> of Perſons, and all upon the certainty of the Divine Revelation: But pretend to no kind of explication of the HOW, or manner of it.</p>
                  <p>I confeſs that private Doctors have done it, and that with heats not becoming the matter in diſpute. The Schools have given way to a World of impertinent queſtions, and have been as impertinent in their reſolutions as imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence can be. They have commented upon one another, and ſtill the Commentary has been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurer than the Text. But when all is done,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:51496:29"/>they have ſtuck firmly to the doctrine reveal'd, and unanimouſly agreed in this, though they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreed in there explications about it.</p>
                  <p>I ſhould look upon it as the greateſt Miracle that ever was done, if they had explain'd that which is inexplicable. Is there no ſuch thing as the Heavens, becauſe ſome Philoſophers have main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd that they were Fluid, and others that they were Solid bodies? Is there no ſuch thing as the Earth, becauſe that ſort of Men have wrangl'd about its figure and motion? The ſame may be ask'd of Form and Matter, and indeed of all the Phaenomena's of Nature, concerning which Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors have given us ſome good and ſolid Reaſons, others nothing but fanſies and dreams. This is the great weakneſs of <hi>Socinianiſm.</hi> The Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of that perſwaſion reject a moſt important Truth, in which all Chriſtians but themſelves agree, becauſe they cannot underſtand the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of it. <hi>We cannot tell,</hi> ſay they, <hi>how it is, therefore it is not.</hi> And they pretend to argue ſtrongly when they affirm that there are diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and ſubdiviſions amongſt us about it: Whereas there is really none but in the explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, our aſſent to the truth of the thing being firm and unmoveable. We ſaid ſomething of this Nature the other Day, but you have taken no notice of it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>This ſine Diſcourſe is all a grand mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake. We do not reject the <hi>Trinity</hi> becauſe we underſtand it not; but becauſe we underſtand it. We let the <hi>HOW,</hi> or manner alone. 'Tis the thing it ſelf which we exclaim againſt. You wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip you know not what. Did you give your ſelves
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:51496:30"/>leiſure to think, and not thwart the very firſt impreſſions of a Rational Soul, this very grand contradiction would ſtare you in the Face. <hi>Three that are but one!</hi> What need is there here of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning? Three Perſons every one God, and all but one God! May not I tell you what <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſays in another caſe, <hi>Advoco te, O Anima, natura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter philoſophantem, non qualis erudita es in Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophorum Scholis,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I appeal to thee, O Soul, not ſuch as thou haſt been taught in the Schools of Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, but with thoſe impreſſions which Nature has given thee!</hi> Are one, and one, and one, Three, or is it but one?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>Your citing of <hi>Tertullian</hi> puts me in mind of a paſſage of <hi>Boëtius</hi> brought in by the Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter</hi> in his vindication of this very doctrine, <hi>pag.</hi> 65. The Catholick Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity</hi> is this, ſays <hi>Boëtius,</hi> the Father is God, the Son is God, and the Holy Ghoſt is God, but they are not Three Gods but one God. And yet the Biſhop pleaſantly obſerves, that the <hi>Socinians</hi> may wonder at it; this very Man ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving written a Learned Book of <hi>Arithmetick.</hi> And ſo for all this eloquent exclamation of <hi>Tertulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> that Father was a Zealous aſſertor of the <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> that is, of one, and one, and one not being three, but one. So were a World of Learned Men in thoſe days, who though cultivated by a Philoſophical inſtitution, had not yet for all that taken their leave of the firſt impreſſions of Nature. But to come to the point.</p>
                  <p>If the difference between us were of numbers, or of any created ſubſtance, I would cry out con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction as loud as your ſelf. I would call
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:51496:30"/>the firſt Man that I ſee in the ſtreet, and pray him only to tell. But this is quite of another Nature. It has no foundation on any thing that we know. The queſtion is of the Nature of God, between whom and us there is an infinite diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion. We cannot Reaſon of him, from any thing which we find in our ſelves, or in our fellow Creatures. God is ſo far above our ſmall and weak perceptions, that except he is pleas'd to acquaint us himſelf what he is; We muſt remain in our ignorance. If God then tells us that he is one and Three; If what we ſay of him, is that which he has ſaid of himſelf; Muſt we preſume to talk, or ſo much as to imagine any contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>I admire your prudence, but I cannot commend your ſincerity. You are ſenſible on what rocks they ſplit, who pretended to prove the <hi>Trinity</hi> not contrary to Reaſon. I think that the B. of <hi>G.</hi> Dr. <hi>S.</hi> Mr. <hi>H.</hi> and others have ſufficiently ſmarted for it. I will engage for them, that they will return no more to ſuch kind of ratiocinations. You take another way, and reſolve all into God's Authority. I grant that what God ſays muſt be true. Nothing is true but according to that conformity which it has to the mind of God. But God has ſaid no ſuch thing of himſelf that he is one and Three. <hi>Trinus &amp; unus.</hi> I deny that he has.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>King Agrippa believ'ſt thou the Prophets?</hi> May not I ask you, do you believe the Scriptures. It is in that Sacred Book that God ſpeaks to us. It is there that he aſſerts it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>I believe the Scriptures to be the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:51496:31"/>Word of God, and as we have ſaid in the brief Notes on the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creed, <hi>a Divine, an infallible, and compleat rule both of Faith and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</hi> But I deny that there is any ſuch thing in the Scripture.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>I am glad to hear you ſpeak ſo juſtly and ſo reverently of the Sacred Writings, which part will you have me to prove? The Unity of the <hi>Godhead,</hi> or the <hi>Trinity</hi> of Perſons in that one Divine Nature.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>You may ſpare your trouble in proving the firſt. We are the great Aſſertors of it. It is from thence that we take the name of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> Though you are obſtinately bent to call us <hi>Socinians.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>Your aſſuming that name is an invaſion of the rights of all Chriſtians. Nay it is an affront to all the wiſe and ſober part of Mankind. You call your ſelves <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians,</hi> juſt as the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> in a poor little corner of <hi>Africa</hi> call'd themſelves the <hi>Catholick</hi> Church. Will you then have me to prove that in the Scripture the Father is call'd God, the Son God, and the Holy Spirit God?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>You may ſpare your ſelf that trouble too. I know all the places that you can alledge. You have repeated them a hundred, and a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred times. If you call this a proof, any thing in the World may be a proof.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>Pray let me lay them before you, and let us fairly ſee what exceptions you have againſt them. It is not Candid, no, it is not civil, to tell an Adverſary that you know all that he has to ſay to you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>I may take the Liberty to be poſitive in
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:51496:31"/>that particular. I have an anſwer ready which I am ſure you cannot take ill. I am ſenſible that you will produce ſeveral Texts; but as it has been urg'd again and again by us, and in particular againſt Mr. <hi>Luzancy,</hi> in the Anſwer to his four Letters, <hi>pag.</hi> 42. <q rend="inline">They are Texts clogg'd with abundance of uncertainties. 'Tis deny'd with great vehemence, by the ableſt Criticks of the <hi>Trinitarian</hi> Perſwaſion, that ſome of theſe Texts were originally ſo read as they are now Publiſh'd in our common Bibles; Nay, ſome of them were not read at all in any Bible till five or ſix hundred years after the Deceaſe of the Apoſtles, and other Sacred Penmen. But whether anciently read, or thus read, yea, or no; there is none of them, but is more fairly capable of a ſence conſiſtent with the <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of God, as 'tis taught by the <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> and <hi>Nominals,</hi> and is actually ſo inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted by divers of the moſt allow'd and cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated Interpreters of the Church. Who ſees not here that to introduce and believe <hi>Monſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities</hi> on ſuch a craz'd foundation as this, is to give up common ſence without a tolerable cauſe for it? Whereas indeed there can be no cauſe ſo great as may induce us to part with it. 'Tis to admit and defend contradictions, and that in a capital Article of Religion when we need not. 'Tis to Sacrifice the cleareſt and moſt important dictates of Reaſon, not to any neceſſity, but to our ſecular intereſts, or wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſs:</q> And has not the Author of the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Reſolution</hi> told you plainly, that you have given up all your places of ſtrength?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>There is in what you have ſaid, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:51496:32"/>and Argument. <q rend="inline">To introduce and believe <hi>Monſtroſities</hi> on ſuch a craz'd founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: To give up common Senſe without a tolerable cauſe for it: To admit and defend contradictions, and that in a Capital Article: To ſacrifice the cleareſt and moſt important Dictates of Reaſon to our ſecular intereſts, or wantonneſs.</q> All this is Declamation. That ſort of Imbelliſhments are very rude and ſevere. As if Conſcience were all of the <hi>Socinian,</hi> and none of the Church's ſide. I know how you would exclaim, if we talk'd to you at this rate. The reſt ſeems to be Argument. But in this I muſt confeſs, that I admire at your vehemency, as vou call it, when there is not a ſingle word of Truth in the Allegation.</p>
                  <p>Forgive me if I ſay that it is falſe, that thoſe Texts are clogg'd with abundance of uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. The Form of our Baptiſm in the name of the Holy and Bleſſed <hi>Trinity</hi> is clear, Genuine, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick; and ſo far from being clogg'd with uncertainties, that all the Fathers, all the School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, all the Modern Interpreters have acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd it. I wonder what you mean by the ableſt <hi>Criticks</hi> of the Trinitarian Perſwaſion. This is perpetually in your Writings. But you are very careful not to name any of them, and I commend you for it. I would beg it as a favour of you that in your next Print, you would name ſome of theſe ableſt <hi>Criticks,</hi> and ſhew us what uncertainties they have found thoſe Texts charg'd with. I am ſatisfy'd that if it had not been for <hi>Hugo Grotius,</hi> and one or two more, whom you have ſadly miſrepreſented, your
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:51496:32"/>cauſe muſt have ſtarv'd for want of ſuch Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities as theſe.</p>
                  <p>It is falſe again, that the ſubſtantial Text which we alledge to prove the Divinity of the <hi>Son,</hi> and <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> were read at any time other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than they are now. You ſay that ſome of them were not read at all, till 5, or 600 years after the deceaſe of the Apoſtles. This has as little Truth as the reſt. There is but one and no more which you have pretended to diſpute, and that is, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.7. and you cannot but know that it has been cited by St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> and is in the famous Edition of the Biſhop of <hi>Oxford,</hi> whom Father <hi>Simons,</hi> though of another com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, calls deſervedly, the Learned Biſhop of <hi>Oxford.</hi> It was in that of <hi>Pamclius.</hi> It is to be found in the Catalogue of the Texts, cited by the Great <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> and Printed in the lateſt Edition of that Father. It had been us'd before by <hi>Tertullian</hi> againſt <hi>Praxeas.</hi> And both St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> and St. <hi>Hierom</hi> complain'd that the <hi>Arrians</hi> had ras'd this Text out of all the Copies which they could come at. The laſt part of the verſe, <hi>and theſe Three are One,</hi> not being capable of the petit novel interpretation of their agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in one, but being look'd upon by the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents who were more ſincere in their diſputes than we are, as a direct proof of the conſubſtantiality of the Divine Perſons.</p>
                  <p>You ſay that there is none of them but what is more fairly capable of a ſenſe conſiſtent with the Unity of God as is taught by the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> and <hi>Nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals.</hi> I have convinc'd you already that there is no ſuch thing in the Catholick Church as <hi>Nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:51496:33"/>Trinitarians:</hi> and the exception is needleſs; ſince we maintain with all Chriſtians that the <hi>Trinity</hi> of Perſons is no contradiction to the Unity of the Divine Nature.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>But ſuppoſing your Texts to be true; they are ſtill conteſted Texts. They are not ſo clear as to be capable but of one ſenſe. You give them one, and I give them another. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps they may admit of a third. Thus you build demonſtrations on things really very uncertain. Then you thunder in our Ears <hi>Scripture, Scripture,</hi> whereas at the bottom you ſay nothing, by uſing Texts capable of different ſenſes. I commend you for reſolving this great controverſy into the Authority of the Sacred Writings; but then as it has been ſaid to Mr. <hi>Luzancy,</hi> pag 42. <hi>The Revelation for it ought to be moſt clear: ſo clear that a fair and ingenuous Reaſoner will not conteſt the poſitiveneſs and evidence of the Revelation.</hi> You underſtand a Text your way, and I do it mine, and ſo there is an end of your Method.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>You will not name us thoſe ableſt Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, of whom you ſpeak ſo much in your Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings. You keep them in the dark as the <hi>Deus in Machina</hi> of the old <hi>Heathens,</hi> that their ſudden appearing may the more ſurprize. But I fear you are one of them, you come at once to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peach the Chriſtian World, and tell this preſent age and thoſe that are paſt, that the Texts us'd by them may be true, but they are conteſted and ſo worth nothing. Is the conteſting then of a Text enough to have it rejected? Is my ſenſe oppos'd to the ſenſe univerſally receiv'd by the Church of God enough to turn that ſenſe out of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:51496:33"/>Doors. Whither will this wild way of arguing hurry a Man? Do you perceive the conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of ſuch a Principle? By this an <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> a <hi>Deiſt,</hi> or any Heretick-in the World is ſecure. It is but giving another ſenſe to a propoſition than what it naturally has. And when you argue with never ſo much clearneſs from Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, he will tell you, there is no propoſition in the World but what is capable of ſeveral ſenſes. What you ſay may be true: But it is conteſted, and I conteſt it. This is your ſenſe of the thing, but it is not mine.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>You both miſtake and miſrepreſent me. I have no ſuch thoughts. By conteſtation, I mean ſuch an oppoſition as is well grounded. It is not enough to ſay, 'tis not my ſenſe; but I muſt have ſubſtantial Reaſons to ſay ſo. I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, as I have told you already, <hi>a Text ſo clear, that a ſair and an ingenuous Reaſoner will not conteſt the poſitiveneſs of the Revelation.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>That is, you demand no Text at all. For whoſoever will contradict it, will think himſelf a fair Reaſoner. Do not all the <hi>Socinians</hi> believe that they are the faireſt Reaſoners in the World. Are they not cry'd up by their party for Men of mighty Reaſon. Your ſelf are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that you are a fair and ingenuous Reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. Thoſe ſilly <hi>Criticiſms</hi> which you have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truded upon all the Texts of Scripture are look'd upon by you, as great efforts of Reaſon. So that this can be no rule at all but is a ſhameful begging of the Queſtion. Every Conteſter will call himſelf a fair Reaſoner.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>What! Is there no ſuch thing then as
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:51496:34"/>fair reaſoning? Is there not in Men an equitable diſpoſition to judge of, and aſſent to the Truth?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes certainly; but you have it not. There are vaſt many Texts produc'd to aſſert the Divinity of the Son and Holy Spirit. For we do not only alledge one or two ſolitary places of Scripture. But we maintain alſo this to be the Foundation of Chriſtianity, and taught in the Scriptures, <hi>Plainly, Frequently, Irrefragably.</hi> Which is the way to reaſon fairly in this caſe?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> It is to ſee the ſenſe which offers it ſelf in the Texts which we produce. Give me leave to bring in an inſtance or two, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.5. St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking of Chriſt, ſays that <hi>he is over all, God bleſſed for ever.</hi> The natural ſence of the propoſition is, that he is truly God. <hi>Over all,</hi> and <hi>Bleſſed for ever,</hi> being the Notion which we have of an Eternal Being. You cannot without an incredible violence make any other ſenſe of that propoſition. The ſame is <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Who being in the Form of God thought it not robbery to be equal with God.</hi> That which the propoſition naturally offers is that <hi>Chriſt is God.</hi> None but a King can ſay that he thinks it not robbery to be equal with a King. None but he who is God can pretend an equality with God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> I muſt ſee whether that ſence which offers it ſelf ſo naturally to me, has the ſame effect on other People. It is a mighty confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to me that I take a propoſition right, when the wiſe, the good, the inquiſitive part of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind takes it as I do. Now our Texts have not only the advantage of a natural evidence; but they have alſo another, and that is the conſent
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:51496:34"/>of the Chriſtian Church. The Church of God has ſpoke as we ſpeak, underſtood as we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, believ'd as we believe. It is the Voice of the Sacred Councils in their Deciſions, of the Fathers in their Writings, of the Univerſities in their Chairs, and of all Chriſtians in their Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Prayers, and Adorations.</p>
                  <p>You own'd it to me, and you ſaid that it was the ſence of the <hi>Socinians,</hi> that <hi>the Scripture is an Infallible, Divine, and Compleat rule of Faith, and Manners.</hi> But it can never be ſo, if there is not an univerſal ſence in thoſe propoſitions in which the Faith is deliver'd. For to whom is it a rule? even to all Chriſtians. And how can Chriſtians follow this rule if there is not a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſence in which they may be united? But what is that ſence, but that which appears to the Church in the propoſitions, and become the ſence of the Church? A ſence of ſo much the more weight and Authority, becauſe no Scripture is of private interpretation. This with all Men who pretend to any acquaintance in thoſe Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, is <hi>fair and ingenuous Reaſoning.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>I thank'd you once for an Argument in the behalf of <hi>Tranſuaſtantiation,</hi> and now I do it for <hi>Tradition.</hi> The denial of it is a Proteſtant Principle.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>You are ſo preſs'd by the evidence of what I offer'd, that becauſe you cannot anſwer, you would endeavour to divert it. Know then by the way, that Proteſtants deny, and that on very good grounds, <hi>Tradition</hi> to be the laſt and ſupreme judge of Controverſies; But maintain <hi>Tradition</hi> and particularly ſo Univerſal and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conteſted
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:51496:35"/>as it is in this particular, to be the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>teſt humane evidence in the World. The unanimous conſent of the Church in a point of Faith is not to be oppos'd by any ſober <hi>Chriſtian.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But to return. Let us ſee what is <hi>your fair and ingenuous way of reaſoning?</hi> You are ſo far from the method propos'd by me, that you reject the natural ſence of the Texts. Some, you muſt give me leave to ſay it, you have openly falſify'd. As for inſtance, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.5. You will not have it, <hi>God Bleſſed,</hi> but, <hi>God be bleſſed for ever,</hi> againſt the Faith of all Copies, againſt the Authority of all Writers. Some you have loaded with little <hi>Criticiſms,</hi> as <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6. Upon others you have trumpt new, unnatural, and incoherent explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.1. And followed Dreams of Yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, unknown to the Church of God, or to any one Writer in it. Others you have eluded with poor <hi>Allegories,</hi> as <hi>Col.</hi> 1.16. In a word, there is ſcarce a part of Scripture but what you have put to the Rack; and then you come to tell us of <hi>fair and ingenuous reaſonings,</hi> of your elaborate Prints to prove the Unity of God, which no Chriſtian ever deny'd. The <hi>Trinity</hi> of the Divine Perſons appears ſo viſibly in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Writings; that if you deſign to deal as a fair or ingenuous reaſoner, you muſt either em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the doctrine, or reject their Authority.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>I will do neither, I am perſwaded of the truth of the one, but not at all of the other. Obſerve what the ingenious Author of the Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Luzancy</hi> has ſaid to him, <hi>pag.</hi> 44, 45, 46. I will put it in as few words as I can, and yet I hope without loſing any thing
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:51496:35"/>of the force of the Argument. <q rend="inline">You charge that upon the Scripture, which is no Scripture at all, and you oblige us to believe as the word of God, that which is no word of God; but only your inferences from it. You draw concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, thoſe concluſions you reſt in, and though they are no Articles of Faith, becauſe only the work of your reaſon, yet you propoſe them as Faith to us. I would fain ask whether your reaſon is more infallible than ours: Or whether you have a privilege which we have not of making inferences? The <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> is no doctrine of Scripture but only an inference from it. May not I have the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty either to make a contrary inference to yours, or to review your deductions; to judge the conſiſtency or contradiction of theſe inferences. I honour the Scripture, but I am not oblig'd to receive your Argumentations?</q> Theſe are not indeed his words, but I am ſure it is his ſence. Get out of this as well as you can.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orth.</speaker>
                  <p>But pray what is all this to the purpoſe? I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an aſſent due to a plain and expreſs propoſition an inference? Or if you will call it an inference, is it not the natural reſult of that plain propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? And muſt not whoſoever has any ſhare of underſtanding give the ſame aſſent to it which I do. What are all our perceptions but infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, and all our talk and converſation but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions? The Plow-Man does it as much as the Philoſopher; and there are propoſitions of that evidence, that if offer'd to all Mankind; all Mankind will agree in them. The queſtion is not here between your Reaſon and mine. Nor
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:51496:36"/>do I pretend to more infallibility than you in reaſoning. But I ſay that Reaſon is ſo much the ſame in you and me, that a plain and expreſs propoſition being offer'd us, you and I muſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually aſſent to it. If you do not, you wrong Reaſon, and are unjuſt to it.</p>
                  <p>I confeſs that when that which is propos'd is obſcure, intricate, and capable of ſeveral ſences; the concluſions may be different, and I cannot without injuſtice deny, that you ſhould examine the conſiſtency, or contradiction of my deducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. But I maintain that moſt of the propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by which our Holy Faith is eſtabliſh'd, are of ſuch plainneſs that no equitable Man can fix any other ſence upon them, than what they offer themſelves. That I may not give you any oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of miſtaking me, for your Friends are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable at this, and if they can but lay hold on it, they preſently expatiate and loſe the queſtion: I mean no more than as to the exiſtence of the Revelation, that is, that there is ſuch a thing reveal'd, though not as to the manner of the thing, the HOW it is in it ſelf.</p>
                  <p>Not to multiply inſtances, take the places already cited, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.5. <hi>Whoſe are the Fathers, and of whom as concerning the Fleſh CHRIST came, who is over all, God bleſſed for ever.</hi> What is that which the propoſition offers? That CHRIST is a Man deſcended from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and that he is God over all, God bleſſed for ever. It is a plain, and as plain a propoſition as can be. But when I go further and ſay; Then there are two Natures in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> for as a Man he cannot be God; and as God he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:51496:36"/>be Man: He is Man becauſe <hi>concerning the Fleſh he came from the Father;</hi> He is God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Apoſtle ſays he is <hi>over all, God bleſſed for ever:</hi> I confeſs that this is an Inference; but it is an inference which reſults ſo plainly and ſo fully from the Nature of the propoſition, that it is as clear and as undeniable as the propoſition it ſelf. Again <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Who being in the Form of God, thought it not robbery to be equal with God.</hi> There is a plain propoſition that CHRIST is equal with God: and the inference is of the ſame nature and clearneſs as the propoſition. Therefore he muſt be God. For none but God can be equal with God.</p>
                  <p>1 Cor. 2.10. <hi>The Spirit ſearches all things, even the deep things of God.</hi> The Spirit knows all that God is, his Nature, his Perfections, even thoſe depths unfathomable to any created Being. You will not quarrel with the propoſition, and can you quarrel with the inference, which in effect is the ſame with the propoſition, and that is, that he is God, ſince none but God perfectly knows himſelf? Pray what inference is there in <hi>Act.</hi> 5.3, 4. when <hi>Peter</hi> in his Apoſtolical Zeal asks <hi>Ananias</hi> why <hi>Satan</hi> has fill'd his Heart <hi>to lye to the Holy Ghoſt? Thou haſt not ly'd unto Men, but unto God.</hi> If the Holy Ghoſt is not God, how could he lye unto God? You ſee the inference is drawn by St. <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf, and lies in the very Heart of the Propoſition.</p>
                  <p>How unreaſonable is this noiſe about inferences will appear if you take notice of the beginning of St. <hi>John</hi>'s Goſpel. Is Verſe the 14th an Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence? <hi>The Word was made Fleſh, and dwelt among us, and we beheld his Glory, the Glory as of the only
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:51496:37"/>begotten Son of the Father, full of Grace and Truth.</hi> Are the 1, 2, 3. Verſes an Inference? <hi>The Word was with God, The Word was God, The ſame was in the beginning with God. All things were made by Him, and without Him there was not any thing made that was made.</hi> Is <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.28. an Inference? <hi>And</hi> Thomas <hi>anſwer'd and ſaid unto him, my Lord, and my God!</hi> Let us deal candidly; if you call the <hi>Incarnation</hi> and the Union of the two Natures in <hi>CHRIST JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> an Inference; Is it not the plaineſt reſult of the plaineſt Propoſitions that ever were in the World.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>You are launch'd into a vaſt Sea of Diſcourſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>Oblige me ſo far as to ſuffer me to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt ſomewhat longer on this, and I will repay your Patience with a ſerious attention to what you have to ſay to it. Read 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.7. <hi>There are Three that bear record in Heaven, the Father, the Word, and the Holy Ghoſt, and theſe Three are One.</hi> When we talk of a Trinity of Perſons conſiſtent with the Unity of the Divine Nature, is it an Inference or is it not? Is not the Trinity of Perſons, and the Unity of the God head clearly expreſs'd in the Propoſition? You have made ſuch a wonder at the word <hi>Trinity,</hi> and been ſo rude as to call <hi>Trinity</hi> in Unity <hi>Jargon, Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, Nonſence.</hi> How can you reconcile all this with this noble Paſſage? Is not this a <hi>Trinity</hi> in Unity, not by way of Inference, but by a full and plain Aſſertion?</p>
                  <p>But why ſhould I be ſo earneſt to prove this againſt the <hi>Socinians,</hi> when they themſelves can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny it? For if our Doctrine conſiſts in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but inferences and concluſions which we
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:51496:37"/>draw as we pleaſe; What has made them ſo earneſt to diſpute theſe very texts, and with poor and little <hi>Criticiſms</hi> to endeavour to elude their force? If theſe Texts had not ſtar'd them in the face with an inconteſtable evidence, what ſhould make them ſo indefatigable in granting and deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, adding Comma's, changing or putting in particles, as if Truth wanted ſuch mean helps?</p>
                  <p>It ſhort there are two ſorts of inferences, the one near and immediate, ſuch as I have given you ſome inſtances of, which naturally flow from the thing propos'd and are of equal clearneſs with it. The other remote and not appearing ſo eaſily at firſt, but wanting the help of further inquiries and deductions. Concerning the firſt I may challenge your Reaſon of error. I may ſafely and truly ſay, you offer violence to Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. I may appeal to all Mankind in the caſe. But for the other. I muſt not ſo freely affirm it, nor ſay that my Reaſon is more infallible than yours. When I am oblig'd to run through a long courſe of deductions I may miſtake as much as you do.</p>
                  <p>The Church never pretended to any inferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces but of the firſt kind. If the Scripture propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes a <hi>Trinity</hi> of Perſons in the Unity of the <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head:</hi> If it repreſents theſe Perſons incommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cably diſtinct from one another; Their <hi>Conſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiality, Coequality, Coeternity,</hi> is a natural and a neceſſary conſequence. If it teaches me that <hi>CHRIST</hi> is God and Man, the Union of the two Natures in one adorable Perſon is an inference of the ſame ſort. If there is a Father from ever, and a Son from ever, and if a Spirit
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:51496:38"/>proceeds from ever; Eternal <hi>Generation,</hi> and Eternal <hi>Proceſſion</hi> are neceſſary deductions from thoſe great truths, and in a manner the ſame with the truths themſelves. I tell you once more, you muſt either admit our doctrine or reject the Holy Scriptures.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>I confeſs that what you have ſaid is well put together; and has a very good face; But ſtill I am far from being ſatisfy'd. There is nothing can make me believe a contradiction. Let it be found in Sacred or humane Writings, it is ſtill a contradiction. A contradiction is that to which all the World cannot reconcile me. You ſay, Revelation, and a Revelation which I own to be the rule of my Faith, is for it. I ſay, my Reaſon is againſt it. Revelation and Reaſon can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be contrary to one another. This would be a greater contradiction than the firſt. God cannot give me Reaſon in my Creation to be my guide, and unravel at the ſame time thoſe very Principles which he has made a part of my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tertullian de poenit. c.</hi> 1. ſays truly and Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantly, <hi>Res Dei Ratio; Reaſon is the buſineſs and work of God.</hi> It is by it that he has made us like him, after his own Image. And can it be ſo much as thought that that Divine and eſſentially Rational Being will contradict himſelf, defeat his own work, and reveal that which is contrary to the firſt impreſſions of Nature? You take a wrong way to convince me. You ſay God has reveal'd it, and therefore it can be no contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. You muſt firſt prove that there is no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction in the thing it ſelf, before you can ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy me that he has reveal'd it.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:51496:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>God then muſt go out of his own ways, and his Thoughts are to be accommodated to yours, or elſe cannot be receiv'd? You will preſcribe Laws to the Divine Majeſty. It muſt be made to bow to your weak conceptions, and the all wiſe Creator muſt ſtoop to a poor igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Creature. Pray, is this Reaſon or obſtinacy? You would fain ſtruggle with a Principle of that mighty clearneſs and ſolidity, that it commands an aſſent from all Men, and is really the true and laſt reſolution of all this great Controverſy. If God has reveal'd it, you may cry out contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction to the end of the World. There will ſtill be none, and you will only ſhew your weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Prove that it is not reveal'd, and then and not before the buſineſs is done, ſhew that your Reaſon has that character of Authority and Infalliblity which the Scripture has, and then talk of contradictions. Had you ever known a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny part of the Myſtery, if firſt it had not been Reveal'd? How then can you find out contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions in that which does ſo much tranſcend all your conceptions; of which you know ſo little; and which does not lie within the reach of our little Argumentations, but reſts wholly on the <hi>Baſis</hi> of the Divine Authority?</p>
                  <p>I beg of you to tell me, whether God cannot propoſe to us any thing to believe which is above Reaſon? And whether what is above our Reaſon can be ſaid to be contrary to it? In reſolving theſe two Queſtions, you anſwer your Self. The <hi>Trinity</hi> in <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> is a diſcovery made by God, which is above our Reaſon, and therefore can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be contrary to it. The contradiction can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:51496:39"/>come from the declaration of God: For God cannot contradict himſelf. The All-wiſe God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not utter a contradictory Propoſition. It is not ſeated in the thing it ſelf; for there is no ſuch thing as contradiction to be imagin'd in the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature. It comes therefore only from our weak Apprehenſions. And how we can place a contradiction in an object infinitely above all the power and reach of our Reaſon, be your ſelf judge?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>This is the common Subterfuge of your Writers. And this they are ſo pleas'd with, that they have made it a general Anſwer. Let them enjoy it to all intents and purpoſes. But I deny that God can oblige us to believe what is above Reaſon. This appears to me an Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unworthy of the thoughts which we have of God. To be plain: Whatſoever is above my Reaſon, is incomprehenſible to me. That which is incomprehenſible is nothing to me. I cannot believe what I cannot underſtand.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis becauſe you cannot underſtand, that you muſt believe. Faith is to over-rule your Reaſon. The way to underſtand is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve as <hi>Iſaias</hi> expreſſes it, <hi>ch.</hi> 7.9. according to the <hi>Septuagint.</hi> Faith is ſo far from being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive of Reaſon, that of the contrary ſide it improves and perfects it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>I wiſh I could be ſatisfy'd of the truth of this.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>If the nature of Faith and Reaſon were truly eſtabliſh'd, I am apt to think that a very great part of our diſputes would be at an end.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>Pray let us endeavour at it with Candor
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:51496:39"/>and Sincerity. It is late now; but you muſt promiſe me the honour of your Company at a ſmall Dinner to morrow; and after Dinner we ſhall talk fully to this.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>I hate afternoon ſtudies, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon diſputes. The Body then oppreſſes the Mind. Nor are the Spirits capable of that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe application which the clearing a difficulty requires. I give all the forenoon to my thoughts, the middle part of the Day to my ſelf, and the Evening to my Friends. At that time <hi>I</hi> will wait on you. Perhaps <hi>I</hi> may bring a Friend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>If he is your Friend, he will have nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Pedantry</hi> in his looks, nor harſhneſs in his manners. Do not fail.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>I will not.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="dialogue">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:51496:40"/>
               <head>The Third DIALOGUE.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>YOU ſee I am come according to my Promiſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>Not altogether; for you gave me ſome hopes that you would bring a Friend along with you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>I deſign'd it. But he had made an appointment which could not be diſpens'd with. Beſides, he being wholly in my ſentiments, it would have look'd as if I had intended to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>match you, and oppoſe two to one.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſhould not have been afraid of that. For I think that the defender of Reaſon has a mighty advantage. All Mankind is of his ſide. It is their Freehold; and if they part with it to believe impoſſibilities, they make a very fooliſh exchange.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> propoſes no impoſſibilities, and is ſo far from being an Enemy to Reaſon, that it is the moſt Rational Syſtem in the World. Things which actually exiſt cannot be ſaid to be impoſſible. Whatſoever it propoſes is of that kind; and though a great part of it tranſcends our comprehenſions; yet we ought not to deny it, but ſubmit to it with an humble reverence: Expecting a bleſſed Life wherein we ſhall know, what we now believe, and clear perceptions,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:51496:40"/>lucid and glorious thoughts ſhall make a part of that bleſſed ſtate which God has promis'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>I am perſwaded that there will be ſuch a ſtate, and that thoſe magnificent promiſes which God has made us, will be fully perform'd. We ſhall know then infinitely more than we do now: And if at this time, the finding out any Truth ſo ſenſibly affects us; how much more will it do ſo, when the glory of God ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd in us, and Truth ſhall not appear in ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd and divided beams, or by intervals, but as it is in its ineffable Spring? But for all that, I cannot be ſenſible that I muſt enſlave my Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and un-Man my ſelf in running after incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible objects, of which I can neither give, nor receive any tolerable account.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>You are ſo offended at things incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible: Pray are you the happy Man who finds nothing of that nature in the World? Is it always day with you? Do you never feel the cold and darkneſs of the approaching Night?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>No! I ſhould be then an incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Creature my ſelf. I own to my grief that there are abundance of that ſort of things. I ſay, to my grief: For I would, if I could, know every thing. But when I find a bar which ſtops me from going further, then I make a ſtand, and cannot conceive that I am any way concern'd in it. In a word as I have ſaid before, what is incomprehenſible is nothing to me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>You put me in mind of a verſe in <hi>Heſiod,</hi> wherein the old <hi>Mythologiſt</hi> ſays that <hi>Credulity, and Incredulity have equally undone Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.</hi> A thought more becoming a Chriſtian,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:51496:41"/>than a Heathen! From the firſt have ſprung Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition and Idolatry. Men have brought down their Adoration as low as their thoughts. They have worſhip'd Beaſts and Plants, as irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional as the one, and as inſenſible as the other. The ſecond has run them into other extreams. From <hi>Polytheiſm</hi> to <hi>Atheiſm;</hi> from believing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing to the believing nothing at all. It has produc'd <hi>Deiſm,</hi> not ſuch as was the <hi>Deiſm</hi> of the firſt race of the World, when Nature taught Men ſincerely to ſerve their Creator; but ſuch as looſe and profane Perſons have embrac'd, the better under that venerable Name to deſtroy Reveal'd Religion. Pardon me, if I ſay that <hi>Socinianiſm</hi> is another of its branches. Credulity has undone others, but Incredulity has ruin'd you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>You do us a double injury. <hi>Firſt,</hi> In puting us with <hi>Deiſts</hi> and <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> whom you know we are no favourers of. <hi>Secondly,</hi> By charging us with Incredulity, when in all our Books, and Prints, we publickly profeſs to believe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>That is, you aſſent to what comes within the compaſs of your Reaſon, but no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. You believe what you pleaſe, or how you pleaſe. What ſquares with your Thoughts ſhall be Faith. What does not muſt be rejected. You are then Believers at large, and ſuch as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> repreſents the <hi>Manichaeans, lib. de util. creden.</hi> who would have Faith to be nothing but Reaſon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>No, we diſtinguiſh them. The one is not the other. We are ſatisfy'd of the Truth of thoſe things, which Reaſon could never have demonſtrated. We acknowledge a <hi>Reveal'd Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi>
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:51496:41"/>and think it an infinite mercy of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, to have ſent the Lord <hi>Chriſt</hi> into the World to teach us the way to Heaven. But we are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that Revelation contains nothing but what is Poſſible, Conſiſtent with Reaſon, and eaſily underſtood. You have made <hi>Chriſtianity Myſterious:</hi> That is, the plaineſt Religion in the World is become in your hands, obſcure and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricate; and when you have nothing to ſay for your ſelves, you appeal to Faith, as to the laſt remedy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>Give me leave to ſhew you the diſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity, and weakneſs of this way of reaſoning. You ſay that you are ſatisfy'd of the Truth of thoſe things, which Reaſon could never have demonſtrated. But at the ſame time you confine this principally to the matters of Fact related in the Goſpel. Nay the Learned Author of <hi>the Reaſonableneſs of Chriſtianity,</hi> would unreaſonably have confin'd it to the bare belief of CHRIST, being the <hi>Meſſias.</hi> But is there nothing elſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides matter of Fact in the ſacred Writings? Are we not told what that <hi>Meſſias</hi> is, as well as what he has done, his Nature as well as his Actions? Does not this matter of Fact depend upon a <hi>Series,</hi> or Concatenation of Divine Verities, which the Scripture has carefully atteſted? Does not the whole <hi>Oeconomy</hi> of the Goſpel turn upon Father, Son, and Holy Spirit? Are we not ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated in their Names to our Holy Religion? And does not that <hi>Religion</hi> teach us what they are in themſelves, and what in relation to us?</p>
                  <p>But you have an eaſy and poſſible way, and that is to maim and mangle Religion. When it
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:51496:42"/>is thus murder'd and disfigur'd, then it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with Reaſon, and eaſily underſtood when it has nothing to ſay. Thus <hi>Socinianiſm</hi> by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to remove Myſteries from our Holy Religion, becomes it ſelf a <hi>Myſtery.</hi> It takes away the greateſt part of the <hi>Credenda.</hi> Let a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother <hi>Socinus</hi> ariſe and take away the <hi>Agenda</hi> too, and then the World will be ſitted with a delicate Syſtem of Religion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>Now I ſee you grow hot.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>No? but would it not amaze any Man to ſee <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> thus abus'd by Men who own themſelves to be <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and under a pretence of making Religion plain, eaſy, and rational, remove out of the way the moſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial parts of it. May not I wonder to ſee you deny your aſſent to things, becauſe you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend that they are not comprehenſible; when at the ſame time you believe things of which you can give no ſort of account, and which you muſt at laſt, as well as we, reſolve into the Authority of the Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ciation.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>Pray prove that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> very eaſily. For inſtance amongſt many things of this ſort; you believe the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the World; that is, you believe that the World and all that is in it was made of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. Now any thing to proceed of nothing, every thing to be made of nothing, is as great a contradiction <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> as one, and one, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>, but one. O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is made, is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="73" facs="tcp:51496:42"/>the moſt ſagacious Philoſopher. On this the <hi>Lycaeum</hi> built the Eternity of the World. <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian Apolog. c.</hi> 11. attributes it to <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> and <hi>Proclus</hi> to <hi>Plato,</hi> both I fear falſly. Others made matter to be eternally pre-exiſtent. Others ſaid that God was the World. I maintain, that though we can never conceive it; yet it is eaſier to imagine how Three Perſons can ſubſiſt in one Nature, than that any one thing ſhould be made of nothing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>No? I can eaſily conceive the Creation. The notion of an Almighty God producing all things, is neither arduous nor difficult. I may ſay with the Ancient, of whom <hi>Clemens Alexand.</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Str.</hi> 5. <hi>That when I contemplate this great Fabrick of the World, I think I hear the Voice of God who commands it to Exiſt.</hi> That infinite Eſſence, in whoſe mind are repoſited the Eſſences of all things, can give them their ſeveral Exiſtences when he pleaſes. None but <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpoke worthy of God, when he brings in the Almighty com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding all things out of nothing with a word of his mouth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>I muſt beg leave to ſay that this does not reach the difficulty. For if you run to the power of God, and the relation made of it by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> for it. But does it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> comprehenſible? Do you know <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>, how ſomething is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> the contradiction the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> as your Friends ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> not in the words only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> thing it ſelf. How would you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> your very principle I ſhould
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:51496:43"/>ſay, that the Revelation muſt be made conſiſtent with Reaſon; that a poſſible ſence is to be inquir'd after; that God is ſaid to create, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he orders and diſpoſes the eternally pre-exiſtent Matter? Should I criticiſe, and as you have done in other places, alter particles in the Text of <hi>Moſes,</hi> you would think that I am mad, and ſay, that when the Text is ſo plain, and the Revelation ſo expreſs, what I imagine to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, is only the weakneſs of my Reaſon, which muſt not ſtand againſt the Authority of God.</p>
                  <p>Suffer me to retort the Argument upon you. I propoſe the Myſtery of the Bleſſed Trinity, and produce the Divine Revelation for it. You cry out Contradiction, Impoſſibility, Incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſibility; I ſay all this in the caſe of Creation. You juſtly over-rule it by the Authority of the Revelation; why muſt I be deny'd the ſame pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilege, and conclude that as I admit the one, ſo you ought to admit the other?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>But then what ſignifies Reaſon, if it ought not to be judge in Religious Matters? And what Oppreſſion muſt it lie under, if it is over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rul'd by every thing which the Church will call Myſtery.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>The Church calls nothing Myſtery, but what is really ſuch: Some ſublime important Truth, which has an influence on <hi>Religion,</hi> and a perfect coherence with it: Of which we ſee ſome part, the reſt remaining abſtruſe, and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon being at a ſtand in its ſeveral inquiries about it. Thus 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. <hi>And without Controverſy great is the Myſtery of Godlineſs; God was manifeſt
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:51496:43"/>in the Fleſh.</hi> What is propos'd to us is very plain, God aſſuming our Nature, and being made Man. This is a ſtrong engagement to all the duties of Religion. And yet which way ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever you take it; it is ſtill a great Myſtery. Reaſon is infinitely puzzl'd, and has innumerable queſtions ready to offer, which it can never be ſatisfy'd in, becauſe God has reveal'd ſo much and no more. Its duty is to ſubmit and make to the veracity of God a ſacrifice of its curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity.</p>
                  <p>The ſame may be ſaid of the Reſurrection from the Dead, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.51. a <hi>Myſtery.</hi> He ſhews clearly the certainty and advantage of a glorious coming to Life again. Yet it is ſtill a <hi>Myſtery.</hi> Take away the Divine Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation; and Reaſon, humane Reaſon will charge the doctrine of the Reſurrection with contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nonſence, impoſſibility. The ſame pretended objections will lie againſt the Myſtery of the Holy <hi>Trinity;</hi> only with this difference, that you are contented in the other points to bring your Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to the obedience of Faith; but in this you will be refractary.</p>
                  <p>It is ſtrange to ſee Men's odd ways of manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Reaſon. In the ſtudy of Natural things when they can go no farther, then they enlarge upon the weakneſs of Reaſon, the miſery of our Nature, the ſhortneſs of our ſight, and the ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of our faculties. They a knowledge that God has hid abundance of objects from our eyes. But in the ſearch after Myſteries, then Reaſon is ſtrong; it ſoars as high, and can look on the Sun as ſtedfaſtly as the Eagle. Nothing ought
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:51496:44"/>to be Myſterious. Faith muſt not be our guide. It is no more the light of the Soul, but uſurpation and tyranny.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>You have a perpetual inclination to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſent us. We affirm, and we have affirm'd it a thouſand times, that we ought to be guided by Faith. But Faith muſt be rational. It is, ſays St. <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 12.1. <hi>our Reaſonable ſervice.</hi> If it is not ſuch, it is neither worthy of God who requires it, nor of Man who pays that debt to him. I ought not to believe at random, or give my aſſent to every thing, which even the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture propoſes. But I muſt examine how it is conſiſtent with the principles of that Reaſon which he has given me: Thus far I muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and no further. Reaſon firſt and laſt is to be the judge.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>Pray let us avoid thoſe perpetual <hi>Equivocations.</hi> Faith and Reaſon are always con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent. I do not ſpeak of Reaſon as it is in us, but as it is in it ſelf; with that admirable cohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Principles flowing from one another, and concentring in God who is its Author. Had we Reaſon in that ſtate, and to that degree, ſuch I believe was that of innocent <hi>ADAM,</hi> I ſhould be reconcil'd to all your noiſe of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions. But Reaſon as it is in us, is obſcure, apt to be intangl'd in the ſmalleſt thread, and uncertain where and how to fix it ſelf. But let it be conſider'd either of theſe ways, the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtency of Faith and Reaſon muſt be always un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood in ſubordination of the latter to the former. What a monſtrous attempt is this to determine Faith by Reaſon, and not Reaſon by Faith?</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:51496:44"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>What a pleaſant diſtinction is this of Reaſon conſider'd in it ſelf, or as it is in us? Of <hi>ADAM</hi>'s Reaſon and ours? As if <hi>ADAM</hi> was not ſuch another Man as I am; and Reaſon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd in it ſelf could be different from what it is in me, and all Mankind!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes indeed: Innocent <hi>ADAM</hi> juſt come out of the hands of his Maker, and taught immediately by that Infinite Spirit, who had given him his being, did Reaſon better than you or I. His perceptions were clearer: His appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions quicker: His abilities greater. Paſſion and Prejudice had not found the way to his Soul: Wine and Luſt had not inflam'd him: Ambition and the Thirſt of Gold had not deprav'd him. In a word, he was little Inferiour to the Angels themſelves; both in Purity and Knowledge.</p>
                  <p>And why may not Reaſon be conſider'd in it ſelf, in that Divine Relation which it has to the Supream Truth; calm and free in its propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; ſincere and true in its inferences, without a deſire of appearing what it is not, from what it is, when clog'd with the impreſſions of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Body, captivated by a corrupted Will, led into a thouſand ſilly errours, ever ſeeking and never finding a place to reſt in?</p>
                  <p>Theſe are the ſad effects of the firſt Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion. <hi>Man was made upright at the beginning, but they ſought out many inventions,</hi> ſays one to whom the Scripture gives the character of the moſt Knowing of Men. I tell you, that in this crazy Age of the World, and in the great decay of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> what we call Reaſon, are only the miſerable relicks of it.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:51496:45"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>You know by whom it is deny'd that <hi>ADAM</hi>'s Tranſgreſſion had any other influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence on his Poſterity, than to ſhew them an ill example. For my part I believe, that the World is the ſame as ever it was, and that if <hi>ADAM</hi> had not ſinn'd, we had ſtill been ſubject to the ſame Infirmities. Your Doctrine of Original Sin is as Myſterious as the reſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>It is ſo far from being Myſterious, that nothing diſcovers it ſelf with greater clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. All the Pride of Man cannot hide it. Our own unhappy experience contradicts our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended demonſtrations againſt it; and in this, our Heart evidently oppoſes our Mind. But we have loſt the main queſtion, let us return to it. I ſay then, that you give Reaſon too great a Scope, and that in our preſent ſtate it ought not to determine Faith, but be determin'd by it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>But ſtill we talk of Faith and Reaſon, and have not yet agreed what they are. Pray tell me what is Reaſon? But tell it me plainly. Let us have no <hi>Carteſianiſm,</hi> no Metaphyſical Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions, no Notions, no Ideas. If I cannot walk in a ſmooth and open Path, I am reſolv'd to ſtay at Home.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>I am my ſelf of your Mind. I take then Reaſon to be a <hi>Faculty of the Soul, by which we endeavour to find out the Truth, either by way of Inference, or by a plain and ſimple Perception.</hi> What have you to Except againſt this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>Nothing at all. For I think that all our Knowledge comes theſe two ways. Yet if the word, <hi>Endeavour,</hi> falls upon the laſt, as well
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:51496:45"/>as upon the firſt part of the definition, it ſeems ſomewhat incongruous. For ſimple Perceptions offer themſelves to us, and are almoſt the only things of which the Certainty is not diſputed. But yet as it is by comparing the leaſt Known, with the moſt Known Principles that we do Reaſon; and that every thing which we call a ſimple Perception, is not ſuch, I willingly agree in it. Then go on and tell me what is Faith?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Faith is the Gift of God, by which he In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightens our Mind, and inclines our Heart to aſſent to what he propoſes to us to believe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>This I do not like ſo well as the other. Though I know it comes from St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and is commonly receiv'd by the admirers of that Father. Faith is the Gift of God, as all things are in a general ſenſe. But if by it you ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe an immediate Act of his Grace by which we believe; then Faith is no more our choice, or a favour offer'd to all Men, but confin'd only to few. How can it be ſaid that God inlightens our Mind, when what you call Myſteries are as obſcure and unknown after as before we believe? And for that expreſſion of <hi>inclining our Will,</hi> it is not ſufferable, it bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ſo much upon the Doctrine of <hi>Calvin,</hi> which you know the Church of <hi>England</hi> is not fond of. It ſhews an impoſſibility of believing in them whoſe Hearts are not inclin'd, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently it makes unbelief to be no Sin.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>The Definition is I confeſs of St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin:</hi> But I maintain that it is both <hi>Chriſtian</hi> and <hi>Catholick.</hi> The Scripture has taught, and the Church embrac'd it. Joh. 6.4. <hi>No Man can
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:51496:46"/>come unto me, except the Father which has ſent me draw him.</hi> Ibid. v. 65. <hi>No Man can come unto me, except it were given unto him of my Father.</hi> Phil. 1.29. <hi>To you it is given in the behalf of Chriſt, not only to believe on him, but alſo to ſuffer for his ſake.</hi> Rom. 12.3. We are commanded to think ſoberly, <hi>according as God has dealt to every Man the meaſure of Faith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hence the Church has expreſs'd her ſelf in theſe words <hi>Can.</hi> 7. of the Council of <hi>Aurange. If any thinks that by the ſtrength of Nature he can think, or do any good thing relating to Salvation; or aſſent to the Truth reveal'd without the illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or inſpiration of the Holy Spirit,</hi> HERAETICO FALLITUR SPIRITU, <hi>HE IS DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CEIV'D BY AN HERETICAL SPIRIT, not underſtanding this place of the Apoſtle,</hi> 2 Cor. 3.5. <hi>Not that we are ſufficient of our ſelves to do any thing as of our ſelves: But our ſufficiency is of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This does not hinder Faith from being our choice, any more than it does Vertue; the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of God helping, but not altering our Nature.</p>
                  <p>The obſcurity of Myſteries, even when we believe, is no objection againſt the inlightning of the Mind. For this ſuppoſes not a clear in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight into the Nature of the thing, but only a conviction that there is ſuch a thing reveal'd. 1 Cor. 13.12. <hi>For now we ſee through a Glaſs darkly,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>in aenigmate, as in a riddle ... Now. I know in part, but then ſhall I know even as I am alſo known.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But how can you give to the inclining of the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:51496:46"/>will the name of inſufferable and bordering upon <hi>Calvinianiſm;</hi> when you cannot but know that it is the Work of God, and the Prayer of Man to him? Pſal. 119.27. <hi>Make me to underſtand the way of thy Precepts.</hi> v. 35. <hi>Make me to go in the Path of thy Commandments.</hi> v. 36. <hi>Incline my Heart to thy Teſtimonies.</hi> Prov. 16.1. <hi>The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of the Heart is from the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Church, you ſay, is not fond of <hi>Calvin</hi>'s Principles. True, but our abhorrency from <hi>Clavinianiſm</hi> muſt not drive us to <hi>Pelagianiſm.</hi> I may deteſt an opinion inconſiſtent with the goodneſs of God, without throwing my ſelf into an exceſs injurious to the Grace of CHRIST. The Definition then is good and ſafe, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I am willing, if poſſible, to remove all your prejudices, I will put it in fewer words. <hi>Faith,</hi> then, <hi>is a Firm aſſent to what God has re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd to us.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>I cannot quarrel with this. It is well that once at leaſt you will be plain.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>It is well that there is ſomething which you will not deny. This Definition, though not ſo exact as it ought to be, is enough to ſhew you the inſufficiency of Reaſon. For if Reaſon can embrace all that is neceſſary for a Man to know, there can be no neceſſity of Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. This of it ſelf ſuppoſes and is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing proof of our ignorance. For if there are objects which <hi>Reaſon</hi> cannot reach, but muſt owe their diſcovery to a higher and more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Principle; then Reaſon is palpably weak and imperfect. There cannot be a more ſenſible Argument of its Deficiency.</p>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:51496:47"/>
                  <p>But there is another inconvenience as diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nible as this. Reaſon not only cannot reach the object which Revelation preſents; but alſo the object once preſented, it cannot be converſant about it, nor examine the ſeveral parts or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects of it. It cannot come to a view near e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to employ its Faculties in it. The ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of which is very plain, and it is this: That as Reaſon with all its ſagacity and pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tration could never find out ſuch an object, and knows only that there is ſuch a thing becauſe God preſents it, and muſt rely for the truth of it upon God's veracity; ſo the nature of the object propos'd muſt ſtill remain obſcure, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is as great an impoſſibility in finding out the nature of the object, as the object it ſelf.</p>
                  <p>In natural things Reaſon meets with an object fit for its inquiry, and not only finds out the object, but even penetrates what can be known of it, becauſe both are commenſurate: Or, to avoid hard words, which neither you, nor I love, becauſe there is a fair proportion between the object, and the powers and faculties of Reaſon. But in things <hi>ſupernatural,</hi> which word is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to decide the difference, if you would but conſider of it, there is ſo infinite a diſtance between the object propos'd, and the weak per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions of Reaſon, that if we are juſt to our ſelves, and have any reſpect for the order which the All-wiſe God has eſtabliſh'd, we cannot ſo much as pretend to an inquiry into the Nature of the thing offer'd.</p>
                  <p>This highly vindicates the wiſe and ſober An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:51496:47"/>of abundance of Learned Men amongſt us, who in the diſputes about the Bleſſed <hi>Trinity</hi> and <hi>Incarnation</hi> have told you, that theſe are Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries above our Reaſon: That we ought to rely upon the Divine Revelation, and not pretend to give an account of things Incomprehenſible. This you have thought to be an evaſion of all your pretended contradictions; you have derided it; and call'd it <hi>a Trinity of the Mob of ignorant and lazy Doctors.</hi> Whereas if you weigh the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples laid before you, it will appear very firm and ſolid. For to ſtate contradictions in an object Reveal'd, when that object is above all our Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions; when all that we know is that it is, and that too, becauſe it is Reveal'd; but are altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ignorant what it is. Reaſon then ſoars a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove its nature, and what you call contradictions are only the ſtumblings of Reaſon, which ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to climb up an inacceſſible rock, is ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully flung on its back and overthrown.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>But then you make Faith the obſcureſt thing in the World, and what advantage is it to us, if our darkneſs is remov'd by a greater, even a darkneſs that may be felt? If what you ſay is true, I know little by the help of Reaſon, and much leſs by that of Revelation.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>I make Faith what God has made it. The things which he propoſes exiſt and are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain. He is pleas'd to caſt a veil over them, and we ought not to preſume to take it off. It is he that has made us and not we our ſelves; and in vain we ſtrive to ſtart out of the limits to which he has confin'd us. Nor is the homage and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of our underſtandings conſiſtent with clear
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:51496:48"/>Perceptions of things. It would no more be Faith but Knowledge. We ſhould not be <hi>in via,</hi> as the Fathers ſpeak, in the way which leads to Heaven, which is a ſtate of obſcurity, labour, humility, and the fear of God: But <hi>in Patria,</hi> in Heaven it ſelf, a place of intuition, tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility, glory, and perfect love.</p>
                  <p>But let me tell you that Faith has that mighty advantage, that if it is not the cleareſt evidence, it is at leaſt the greateſt certainty in the World. All our aſſurance in other things is humane. The very Principles of <hi>Geometry</hi> are no more. But Faith has a Divine Foundation, and that is, the Authority of God. St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> was ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of the truth of this, that <hi>Homil</hi> 21. <hi>in Epiſt. ad Heb.</hi> he did not doubt to affirm that <hi>he had no Faith who believ'd not more firmly the things reveal'd, than thoſe which are daily the object of ſenſe.</hi> You know the Famous ſaying of St. <hi>Ambroſe de ſacram.</hi> l. 1. cap. 5. <hi>Tolle argumenta ubi Fides quaeritur. Away with all your Reaſons, where Faith is the queſtion.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>If you get amongſt the Fathers, we ſhall have a Sea of Authorities which you know we have no very great eſteem for. I wiſh you would lay them all aſide. But if you will not, what think you of <hi>Lactantius,</hi> who <hi>Inſtit. l.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. ſpeaks thus. <hi>Oportet in ea re maxime,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Every Man is oblig'd, particularly in that wherein his own being is concern'd, to truſt to himſelf; and it is much better to endeavour with the beſt judgment and ſenſe that we can, to find out the truth, than to ſuffer our ſelves to be deceiv'd by other People's errors; as if we were wholly Strangers to Reaſon: God ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:51496:48"/>given all Men ſuch a ſhare of Wiſdom, as to be able to ſearch into thoſe things which are unknown to us, and to examine thoſe that are not.</hi> The ſame Principle <hi>Minutius Foelix</hi> makes uſe of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Caecilius.</hi> And this is the very Argument of <hi>Theodoret,</hi> in his firſt Diſcourſe <hi>de curand graec. affect.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It may be ſaid of <hi>Lactantius</hi> his aſſertion, that nothing can be truer and better. It does juſtice to God, who is the Author and Giver of every good and perfect gift; and to Man, by owning his great and diſtinguiſhing Privilege. You have ſpoke of Faith very well and accurately. But for all that do you know what it is to blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme Reaſon. It is to wound Mankind in the moſt ſenſible part, and to put us out of a capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of ever acting like Men. Reaſon is a light which comes down from the Father of lights. As the natural light diſcovers it ſelf and all other objects; ſo Reaſon the light of the Soul diſcovers its native excellency, and is the tryal of all other things. Its eagerneſs in the purſuit of Truth, is a proof that it is made for it, and capable of it. It looks much like <hi>Prieſt-craft,</hi> to deſire me to ſhut my Eyes, and truſt my ſelf to another guide, whilſt I can ſee my way as perfectly as any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <p>I had once a great reſpect for St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> but I have loſt it, ſince I read a paſſage of his, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he ſtrangely abuſes humane nature. It is <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 15. de <hi>ſerm. dom. in monte. Hominis anima rationalis lumine veritatis vel tenuiter pro ſui capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citate illuſtratur, ut verum aliquid in ratiacinando ſentiat. The rational Soul of Man receives as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:51496:49"/>to its capacity, ſmall illuſtrations and glances of light, that by Reaſoning it may feel ſomething of Truth.</hi> Thus the Doctors of the Church run down Reaſon, and perceive not that they run down Mankind at the ſame time.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>You are in the right to lay the Fathers aſide, for they are all againſt you. I ſhould be glad to be rid of a witneſs, who I am ſure will ſwear home againſt me. The Author of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity not Myſterious</hi> has invalidated their evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to ſome purpoſe. He will not allow above five or ſix to have been Men of ſence; and to ſhew how contemptible they are, he flatters himſelf that ſome ages hence he will be look'd on as a Father. I hope he is no Prophet, and does not ſee ſo much extravagance in the ſucceeding times.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lactantius</hi> every way an admirable Author, argues againſt Idolatry. He ſays very well that no Religion is to be taken upon truſt, and that in ſo great a concern every one ought to judge for himſelf. Idolatry is ſo unreaſonable a thing, that whoſoever admits it, muſt be a ſtranger to Reaſon; God having given every Man ſuch a meaſure of Wiſdom as to reject that which is ſo openly bad, and look for ſomewhat better. But he never pretended that amongſt Chriſtians, who ſo unanimouſly ſubmit to the Revelation, which God has made of himſelf in the Holy Scriptures; Man was to diſpute againſt God, and Reaſon to ſtruggle with Faith. Read the firſt Chapter of the firſt, and the greateſt part of the third Book, and you will ſee that from the contradictions of Philoſophers, he proves
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:51496:49"/>Reaſon to be inſufficient to find out the truth, and that it is only to be met with in that Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, where it is divinely Reveal'd.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Minutius Foelix</hi> argues after the ſame manner. <hi>Caecilius</hi> pleaded a Tradition of Idolatry, in which he thought himſelf ſecure. <hi>Minutius</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, that he ought to appeal to his own Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which will evidently ſhew him the folly and impiety of <hi>Polytheiſm.</hi> And all that <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doret</hi> inſiſts on is, that the ſimplicity of our Holy Faith wants not ſolid and rational arguments, by which it is confirm'd. Such I take to be the Authority of the Revelation, which in ſtrength and clearneſs is ſuperiour to any Argument whatſoever.</p>
                  <p>But laying all this aſide: When you have done all you can, and writ never ſo fine a Panegyrick on Reaſon, the ſtrength of it cannot be better judg'd of, than by its uſe. You will be aſham'd of ever pleading for Reaſon, when you conſider how the great Maſters of it have been diſtracted! And you will ſay with <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Matt. 6.23. <hi>If therefore the Light that is in thee be darkneſs, how great is that darkneſs?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The firſt Men of the World, though ſo near their beginning, and the impreſſions of Reaſon, ſo much the ſtronger becauſe neareſt to their ſpring, yet generally run into <hi>Idolatry</hi> and <hi>Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.</hi> You know how few they were who call'd upon the Name of the Lord. The Church was confin'd to the Family of <hi>Noah.</hi> The fury of the Flood was an eminent inſtance of a Reaſon, which had ſo far wandred from its Principles that it was paſt recalling, and was fit for nothing but deſtruction.</p>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:51496:50"/>
                  <p>When the World after that was ſo far re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſh'd, as to afford great <hi>Monarchies</hi> and nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Nations; you ſee Reaſon as inſufficient as before, and Men as obſtinately bent to depart from their Creator. I will not run through their ſeveral <hi>Idolatries.</hi> The <hi>Aegyptians</hi> ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for their Learning, who thought themſelves, and were look'd upon by others as highly Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Men, did debaſe Reaſon to that degree, as to make Gods of their very Roots and Plants. <hi>A happy People,</hi> ſays pleaſantly <hi>Juvenal, who ſee their Deities grow in their Gardens!</hi> But you will ſay they were unthinking People who had not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd the matter, or inquir'd into the Nature of Reaſon. But what muſt you think of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſſers of Learning and Reputation, I mean the <hi>Greeks?</hi> Men who valu'd themſelves upon being inquiſitive, treated all the parts of Philoſophy, and fill'd the World with Sects and Syſtems.</p>
                  <p>Good God! The Dogmaticks thought Reaſon ſo clear as to be certain of every thing, and to doubt of nothing: An extravagance of which they had a confutation in themſelves. Theſe <hi>Socrates,</hi> the wiſe <hi>Socrates</hi> takes up, and is ſo far from taking Reaſon to be clear, that he profeſſes that if any thing was certain, it was this, <hi>That he knew nothing to be certain.</hi> This Aſſertion <hi>Arce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilas</hi> and <hi>Pyrrho</hi> cannot be reconcil'd with; carry the doubt yet further, and find no certainty in that very Propoſition, but make Heſitation, and Fluctuation the Principles of their Doctrine.</p>
                  <p>They are not more lucky in their ſearch about Happineſs, Providence, the Being of God, and the Original of the World. There is a ſtrange
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:51496:50"/>confuſion in their Opinions, and an incredible weakneſs in their Arguments. They have veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd the ſaying of <hi>Solomon,</hi> Eccleſ. 3.11. <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum trad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>t diſputationi eorum. God has made the World the ſubject of their diſputes.</hi> Or as our Tranſlation reads it. <hi>He has ſet the World in their Heart, ſo that no Man can find out the Work that God made from the beginning to the end.</hi> And Eccleſ. 8.17. <hi>Though a Man labour to ſeek it out, yet he ſhall not find it; yea further, though a Wiſe Man think to know it, yet he ſhall not be able to find it.</hi> This is the Reaſon which you cry up ſo much, and theſe are your Rational Men.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>All this is a Satyr upon Reaſon and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe. Yet it cannot detract from its dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. And it is a conſequence ill drawn, That be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſome Men have Reaſon'd ill, therefore we cannot Reaſon well. Several People have had but one Eye, therefore we have not two. The <hi>Aegyptians</hi> and <hi>Greeks</hi> have been delirious, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt be ſo too. They did conclude at random in thoſe days, becauſe they wanted all the means of Erudition, which we have, and therefore we muſt talk at the ſame rate, though a long experience, innumerable Books, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curate Methods in all Arts and Sciences have wonderfully reſin'd our Notions. With you the dawning of the Day gives more light than the full Noon; and the Morning is wiſer than the Evening of our Lives. Pray let us lay aſide theſe common places, and come to a cloſer way of reaſoning.</p>
                  <p>Is there ſuch a thing as Reaſon, or is there not? If there is not, then we are like the Beaſts that
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:51496:51"/>periſh, uncapable of either Reward or Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, becauſe uncapable of Good and Evil. But if there is, then it muſt be given us for ſome end, and it muſt be fitted for the attainment of that for which it is given. You have granted in your Definition of Reaſon, that <hi>it is a Faculty of the Soul by which we endeavour to find out the Truth.</hi> Is Truth then attainable, or is it not? If it is not, then your Definition is worth nothing. If it is, then Reaſon is not only the inſtrument by which we find it, but alſo the judge of that Truth which we find. Not that I pretend that Truth is not greater than our Reaſon, and that Reaſon penetrates the whole extent of the Truth which it contemplates: But I maintain that as the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject falls under the ſcrutiny of Reaſon, it muſt judge of it, and what it affirms or denies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning it is true. I know that Men have not the ſame ſtrength of Apprehenſion. That which ſeems a demonſtration to me, will be juſtly call'd an impertinence by another. But I ſay that it is the touchſtone of all that is propos'd to us; and that nothing can be laid before us as Truth, in which we are concern'd, but Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon muſt inquire into and judge of it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>But what is all this, but what has been ſaid a thouſand times, and what you have offer'd to me already? Does this reſolve at all the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty propos'd. It were eaſy to me to ſhew you that the Reaſon of this age is not better than that of the <hi>Greeks</hi> and the <hi>Romans:</hi> That 'tis not to Books or Experiments, but to Religion, that you owe the improvement of your Reaſon, and that the beſt <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ever made the beſt
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:51496:51"/>Philoſophers. But granting all that you can pretend from that which you call cloſe Reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what is it to the purpoſe? Admitting that you conclude right in all thoſe things which are within the reach of Reaſon, which is not only diſputable, but even falſe; is it not altogether Deficient in what is above it? Fooliſh and raſh aſſertion, that becauſe Reaſon knows ſome things, therefore it muſt know all things: And that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it can grapple with natural, therefore it may with ſuper-natural Objects.</p>
                  <p>Theſe three things Men are guided by, <hi>SENSE, REASON, FAITH.</hi> We believe firſt our Senſes. We ſee, hear, ſmell, taſte, touch; from theſe we receive the firſt impreſſions. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are fallible, impoſing, and like to make us draw falſe conſequences, Reaſon comes to help us. It rectifies the miſtakes of ſenſe. The larger operations of the Soul embrace Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of a greater extent, and with an incredible eagerneſs will ſearch what they are, as well as what they appear. This is the ground of <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophical</hi> inquiries. But Man is not contented with this. For beſides that the way is painful, tedious, and yielding very often neither profit nor pleaſure, he can fix no where. He finds in himſelf a deſire of happineſs, which no created being can procure. Suppoſing that he can mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the Heavens, underſtand luminous Bodies, be acquainted with the laws of Motion and Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; this is ſtill far from anſwering the vaſt capacity of a Soul, which diſtaſted with infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior objects, aſpires at the Knowledge of God's Nature, of his own Immortality, and of a future State after this Life.</p>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:51496:52"/>
                  <p>There is ſomewhat which he is ſenſible is want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the perfection of his own Being. He ſees at a mighty diſtance great and venerable objects, but cannot draw near to them, being kept back by his inacceſſible light of one ſide, and the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity and weakneſs of his Reaſon of the other. The merciful God will not diſcover himſelf plainly to him. If he did, he could not bear the Splendor; <hi>For no Man ſhall ſee God, and live.</hi> But he has ordain'd Faith as a <hi>Medium</hi> between the darkneſs of this Life, and the Glory of the next. He has commanded Man to believe, fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereby all the uncertainties, and rectifying all the miſtakes of Reaſon. And has given him the greateſt encouragement that can be, by aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring him that he ſhall know hereafter, what he now believes.</p>
                  <p>Suppoſing that one ſhould argue for Senſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Reaſon, as you do for Reaſon againſt Faith, you would ſay to him, that Senſe in a Matter, which depends from Senſe, is the beſt judge; but that in a Matter about which Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon alone is converſant, it has nothing to do, becauſe the object is much above its reach. Should Senſe reply, God has fitted me for ſome end, and that end is the apprehending of Truth, and conſequently attainable, or elſe it is no end; and by this I am fitted to judge of ſuch, and ſuch objects; you would ſay to him, Senſe is one thing, and Reaſon is another. Senſe is to be ſo far from pretending to be the judge of Reaſon, that is has nothing to do with it. Pray be juſt and ſay the ſame of Reaſon. It will ſtrive to inquire into the buſineſs of Faith. Faith will
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:51496:52"/>own that concerning things within the compaſs of Reaſon, there can be no fitter judge. Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon will tell Faith, that it contradicts it ſelf, that it propoſes impoſſibilities, that it is every way incomprehenſible. Faith will laugh at this, and ask how Reaſon can talk of contradictions, and impoſſibilities, and incomprehenſibilities, where it has nothing to do, and has no ſort of aptitude to ſee whether it is ſo or no. I am ſure this is their Sence who ever pretended to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand thoſe matters. St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in his Book, <hi>de morib. Eccl. Cathol.</hi> In the third Book <hi>contra Acad.</hi> c. 19 .....</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>I have declar'd my ſelf already againſt citations of the Fathers. Favour me ſo far as to bring in no more. 'Tis not what they ſay, but what you ſay, which I am willing to hear. What St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> tells <hi>Adimantus, Voluſianus, Honoratus,</hi> is nothing to me. He was a Man of Sence, but I build no part of my Faith upon his or the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſayings. I like your way of ſpeaking very well: Pray go on.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>What you require of me is highly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt. For though I build my Faith no more than your ſelf upon the Fathers, but only upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd word of God; yet I think their Authority to be great and conſiderable. As our Holy Faith is the ſame now as in the beginning of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> becauſe a part of its Character is to have been <hi>once</hi> deliver'd; ſo I conceive that it is now beſt defended by the ſame methods which the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Doctors us'd at firſt. When our Myſteries were propos'd to the Heathens, they were as quick as you can be at objecting contradictions.
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:51496:53"/>They magnify'd Reaſon as much as any of you have done ſince. The Fathers did ſtrenuouſly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply themſelves to ſhew its weakneſs and inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency, and by aſſerting the neceſſity of Faith over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rul'd all their objections. When you have done all that you can, you muſt at laſt come to this; only with a far greater diſadvantage of your ſide, becauſe the Heathens rejected that very principle which you admit, and that is the Divine Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. You cannot oppoſe the Authority of the Fathers, without doing the Chriſtian Church a vaſt injury, and robbing it of one of its greateſt Ornaments. This very thing muſt be a preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice againſt you, that you have renew'd the old objections of the Heathens againſt this Sacred Doctrine, and deſpis'd thoſe very ways which were us'd by the Fathers in the confutation of their errors.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>You perpetually cry up the Fathers, and yet would not be bound in this very point to make good their Reaſonings. Are there not three Faculties of the Soul, and yet but one Soul; the Root, Bark, and Branches of a Tree, and yet the ſame Tree; <hi>Peter, James,</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> three Men, and yet the ſame humane Nature; are not theſe and twenty more ſuch inſtances delicate proofs of a <hi>Trinity</hi> in <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>They are no proofs, nor ever were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be ſuch. What can be made of them is, that they are Illuſtrations, faint Adumbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or Reſemblances of the inexplicable <hi>Myſtery.</hi> The Fathers requir'd believing, and not reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. They affirm'd Reaſon incapable of judging of <hi>Myſteries,</hi> and reſolv'd all into Faith, <hi>that
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:51496:53"/>firm aſſent to what God has Reveal'd.</hi> You may ſee this Elegantly treated by <hi>Arnobius,</hi> who calls Reaſon <hi>blind, uncertain, weak, and owing to the Mercy of God, that himſelf has ſpoken to inform it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lactantius</hi> is poſitive <hi>lib.</hi> 3. c. 1. that <hi>the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and worſhip of God cannot be attain'd by Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or Senſe; and therefore that laying aſide all theſe Maſters of an earthly Philoſophy, who have ſo contradicted one another, and have left nothing cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; we ſhould look up to God, who</hi> Tradidit Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum verae Religionis, ut revelatae divinitùs veritatis cognitionem conſequamur, <hi>Has given us the Sacred Inſtitution of the true Religion, that we may attain the Knowledge of that Truth which is Divinely Reveal'd.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And in the ſame place; <hi>Divina tradita ſunt breviter &amp; nude. Nec decebat aliter, ut cum Deus ad hominem loqueretur argumentis aſſereret ſuas voces, tanquam fides ei non haberetur; ſed ut oportuit eſt locutus quaſi rerum omnium ſupremus Judex; cujus non eſt argumentari ſed pronunciare verum. Divine things are deliver'd in a ſhort and plain manner. Nor was it fit that it ſhould be otherwiſe. As if God was not to be believ'd, except he gives Reaſons for what he ſays. He has ſpoke as the ſupreme Judge of all things, whoſe part is not to diſpute, but ſimply to pronounce what is true.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tertullian</hi> de anim. <hi>Cui enim veritas comperta ſine Deo? Cui Deus cognitus ſine Chriſto? Cui Chriſtus exploratus ſine Spiritu Sancto? Cui Spiritus accommodatus ſine Fidei Sacramento? Who has been able to attain the Truth without God? Who has known God without Chriſt? Who has known Chriſt without the Holy Spirit? Who has known the Holy Spirit but by the ſacred way of Faith?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:51496:54"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great <hi>Hom.</hi> 26. in <hi>Evang.</hi> aſſures that <hi>Fides non habet meritum cui Humana Ratio praebet experimentum. That Faith is of no value which is grounded upon the inquiries of humane Reaſon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> has treated this very argument in abundance of places with the utmoſt accuracy. The <hi>Greek</hi> are perfectly agreed in this with the <hi>Latin</hi> Fathers. It is the Divinity of <hi>Origen,</hi> of <hi>Theodoret,</hi> of St. <hi>Chryſoſtom.</hi> I will go further with you, and ſay that this is the ſence of the generality of Divines; which has made that great Schoolman <hi>Aquinas</hi> lay this as a Principle in that part of his Works, which is much the beſt of all his Writings, and that 2 <hi>a.</hi> 2 <hi>da. qu.</hi> 2. <hi>art.</hi> 4. <hi>Ratio Humana in rebus Humanis eſt multum defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciens, cujus ſignum eſt, quia Philoſophi de rebus Humanis naturali inveſtigatione perſcrutantes, in multis erraverunt, &amp; ſibi ipſis contraria ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t ergo eſſet indubitata &amp; certa cognitio apud homines de Deo, oportuit quod Divina eis per modum Fidei traderentur, quaſi à Deo dicta qui mentiri non poteſt. Humane Reaſon is much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, even in Humane things, of which this is a proof, that the Philoſophers in that ſearch about them which they made by natural inquiries, have mightily err'd, and contradicted themſelves. And therefore to the end that Men's Knowledge concerning God might be certain and undoubted, it was neceſſary that Divine Matters ſhould be deliver'd to them by way of Faith as ſpoken by God, who cannot lye.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>Then we are no more Men, but Stocks and Stones. Our obedience to God is no more choice, but neceſſity. If Reaſon has nothing to do in matters of Faith, Men ceaſe to be reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able as ſoon as they Commence Chriſtians. We
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:51496:54"/>are all oblig'd to you for diveſting us of that by which we are like God. At this rate any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagance will be call'd a <hi>Myſtery;</hi> any little Prieſt will obtrude and defend it; and under the ſpecious name of Faith overcome the cleareſt demonſtrations of Reaſon. Once more this is <hi>Prieſt-Craft</hi> with a vengeance. Pray tell me what I muſt do with my Reaſon hereafter, and into what ſort of Creature it ſhall tranſmigrate, ſince a Chriſtian is no more capable of it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>This is all heat and madneſs. I am for Reaſon as much as your ſelf. But I would have it kept within its due bounds. It is of great uſe in Religion, and I am not out of hopes to make you ſenſible of it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>When the Sea gives over ebbing and flowing, and not before. You have prov'd that in matters of Faith Reaſon is to be ſilent; and now you tell me that it is of great uſe. How can this be reconcil'd?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>We have ſpoken too long to enter now on a new diſcourſe. Let us put it off till I have the happineſs to ſee you. In the mean time let me beg a double favour of you. <hi>Firſt,</hi> to conſider impartially what has been ſaid between us. <hi>Secondly,</hi> that in caſe you will not be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, the difference of our Sentiments ſhould not in the leaſt alter our Friendſhip.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſhould be too great a ſufferer my ſelf in denying any part of this. I was ready to ask it, but you prevented me. When ſhall we meet again?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>To Morrow if you will in My Lord Biſhop's fine Garden. There is no Body now there. We ſhall not only be free, but alſo
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:51496:55"/>enjoy for ſome hours the prettieſt Solitude I know about the Town.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>Done.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="dialogue">
               <head>The Fourth DIALOGUE.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>I hope I have not tir'd your Patience. How long have I made you ſtay here?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>A very little time, and that without any trouble; for this is really a very curious Place. Nature and Art have combin'd to make it fine. How large and firm are thoſe Walks? What a plenty of excellent Fruit adorns theſe Walls? How proud is this <hi>Parterre</hi> of an infinite variety of Native and Foreign Flowers? But let us haſten to the end, where a ſmall River calmly and ſilently runs; and ſtately Trees on both ſides will ſcarce ſuffer the Sun to view the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>In ſuch places as this was Philoſophy born. There ſpeculative Men ſecure from the noiſe and vices of Towns, gave themſelves to Contemplation. Their manners were innocent, and their way of living plain and unaffected. They ador'd the Author of all theſe things, and ſpent their time in ſerious and profitable inquiries.</p>
                  <p>But theſe Men of thoughts grew fond of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting their ſecrets, and brought Philoſophy
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:51496:55"/>into Towns. There it became proud, vain, and full of Talk. It muſt come back again, or elſe it will never be what it was in that Bleſſed Age. But let us draw to that ſmall Building at the end of this Walk?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>We are going to it. It is a place con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated to Solitude. There is written without in large Characters, NO PASSIONS CAN COME IN HERE. And within, NEVER LESS ALONE THAN WHEN ALONE. There we ſhall ſit down, and you will diſcharge your Promiſe of giving Reaſon ſatisfaction for your violent Invectives againſt it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>I never injur'd Reaſon. It would be an unſucceſsful attempt. All that I have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd to do, is to keep it within its due bounds. In our Diſputes as well as in all other things we are apt to run into extreams. Our Thoughts of Reaſon are either too great or too mean. We give it too much or too little. And this comes from want of uſing our ſelves <hi>to think ſoberly.</hi> Thus ſome believe themſelves to be all Eyes, and obſtinately run on with Notions of which they never had patience enough to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider every part, and which when examin'd, are not what they appear'd to be at firſt. I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd that moſt of us are more taken with proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility than Truth. What is fine, ſmooth, and eaſy ſteals away our aſſent, which a further and cloſer inquiry would oblige us to deny.</p>
                  <p>Your Books are all of that ſort. You have eſpous'd a Principle that Reaſon ought to be the Judge in Religious matters. This carries along with it a great deal of Probability, and inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:51496:56"/>it ſelf the more eaſily, becauſe it flatters our Pride. But when this comes to be throughly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amin'd the obiections againſt it are ſo many, that all that can be ſaid of it is this, that it is only an Opinion which indeed appears probable, but is certainly falſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>Pray ſit down, and acquit your ſelf. Shew the conſiſtency of Reaſon with Faith and its great uſe in Religion. Or elſe I muſt accuſe you of Non-performance.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>We cannot treat this with any Candor except you acknowledge, <hi>Firſt,</hi> that as Reaſon has its Beauties and Excellencies, it has alſo its Deformities and Weakneſſes. It is a light which God has given us to know him and our ſelves. But that light ſuffers frequent <hi>Eclipſes.</hi> It ſhines dim, and is often put out. We are not wiſe all the hours of the day. Sometimes our thoughts riſe as the Sea when it overflows the neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Shoars; and ſometimes again they ſink into a ſmall and contemptible Channel. We own and diſown, admit and reject, are pleas'd this minute with a concluſion, and the next lay it aſide; look upon thoſe things as Errors which we formerly embrac'd as Truths, and take thoſe for Truths which we once rejected as Errors.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Secondly,</speaker>
                  <p>You muſt grant me that Reaſon is not the ſame in all Men; I mean as to its vigor and efficacy. In ſome a happy Nature with the addition of a careful Education, Reading, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, and Experience, makes it quick and active. It is admirable to ſee how ſome Men will like lightning run through a maſs of propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, and underſtand a thing as ſoon as it is
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:51496:56"/>offer'd. But in others it is heavy and dull, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd by the matter in which it is inclos'd, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſunk; and as the <hi>Phyſicians</hi> ſay of Blood, incapable of circulating through the abundance of viſcous humours, by which it is detain'd. The far greater part of Mankind is of this ſort. Of the common Saylors, Souldiers, Labourers, Women, it may be ſaid that the Body is truly the gaol of the Soul, from which it ſeldom breaks out, to exert any acts anſwerable to the dignity of its nature.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I beg alſo that you would not deny, that though there is ſo viſible a difference in the exerciſe of Reaſon, and ſome Men do almoſt as far exceed others, as theſe exceed irrational Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; yet there is ſome univerſal Principle fitted to every one's capacity, and in which all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind agree. Such is the ſearch after Happineſs. The groſſeſt and moſt illiterate of the Sons of <hi>ADAM</hi> are as much convinc'd of this as your ſelf, whoſe erudition is certainly great. This is not learned from Books, or taken up upon the credit of Authors, but is an invincible inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which every one finds in his own Heart.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>I grant all this but your compliment to me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>All this granted, I proceed, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to be poſitive that Reaſon can never ſhew to Man the way to Happineſs. For though it concludes very well from the Works of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that there is a God, who is the Author and giver of that happineſs, and that the ſervice of God is the way to obtain it; yet what we ought to believe of that God, how he is willing to be
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:51496:57"/>ſerv'd, and which way we can appeaſe his anger and ſecure his favour to us, is altogether above the reach of Reaſon. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.13. <hi>His ways are paſt finding out.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Doctrine of a Covenant of Grace, of a Redeemer in whom we are pardon'd and accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and who by the Sacrifice of himſelf ſhould reconcile us to God, are Myſterious depths to which Reaſon, the moſt clear ſighted Reaſon has not the leaſt acceſs.</p>
                  <p>It was neceſſary then that Authority ſhould ſupply that want, and God reveal what it was impoſſible Man ſhould acquaint himſelf with. Revelation is that which informs our underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, cures our ignorance, rectifies our miſtakes, and by a ſhort and infallible way leads us to hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs. This the Philoſophers aim'd at by the ſtrength of Natural Reaſon, but very unſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsfully. You know what <hi>Socrates</hi> and <hi>Plato,</hi> what the School of <hi>Epicurus,</hi> what <hi>Zeno</hi> and the <hi>Porticus</hi> ſaid to it. Their Syſtems were vain, fooliſh, flat, and unpracticable. This impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant diſcovery was to be the work of him who <hi>had the words of Eternal Life.</hi> And the wiſeſt and beſt Definition that ever was given of it, is <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.3. <hi>And this is Life Eternal, that they might know thee the only true God, and Jeſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I call this a ſhort and an infallible way. It is infallible, becauſe propos'd by him who can neither deceive, nor be deceiv'd. It is ſhort, becauſe it cuts off all the <hi>Ambages</hi> and uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which Reaſon is intangl'd in, and reſts upon a rock, and that is, the Authority of God.
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:51496:57"/>You make Faith ſo difficult a thing, and exclaim loud when we endeavour to bring you over to it. But for my part when I take a view of thoſe Principles which Mankind rely upon, I find it much eaſier to believe than to reaſon. Can I be ſafer than when God himſelf is my Guide? Shall I find more truth any where than in what God propoſes? Or are the Mazes or Labyrinths of humane Argumentations eaſier to run through, than the Aſſeverations of Scriptures. This has made St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> to ſay, <hi>de Trin.</hi> l. 14. c. 1. <hi>that many of the Faithful have Faith in a very high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, though they have little or no Learning.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>That is, it is eaſier to ſwallow any thing, than to inquire whether it is true or no?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>No: For if you Conſider this Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Authority of the Divine Revelation, you will find that it prevents all ſorts of miſtakes, and makes us give over reaſoning and diſputing, not becauſe we deſign to avoid the labour and trouble of it; but becauſe we are ſatisfy'd that here lies the Truth, and that it is impoſſible to find it any where elſe. That <hi>whatſoever God is pleas'd to reveal is true,</hi> is a propoſition to which all Mortals in any capacity whatever give a moſt ready aſſent. There is none of us but what has in ſome meaſure or other Notions of God, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to that Divine Being. In ſome they are more ripe and refin'd than in others, in <hi>Chriſtians</hi> moſt of all. But all agree that as he is Wiſe and Holy, ſo he is True; and that what he delivers to us has an indelible Character of Truth.</p>
                  <p>This has not only been taught by us, but by
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:51496:58"/>the Heathens themſelves. <hi>Homer</hi> and <hi>Heſiod</hi> have acknowledg'd it. <hi>Euripides</hi> owns in <hi>Helen,</hi> v. 1164. <hi>&amp; ſeq.</hi> that <hi>he has found nothing certain amongſt Men but this that the words of the Gods are true.</hi> And I think it is <hi>Porphyrius,</hi> a Man of mighty prejudice againſt <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring the ways of the <hi>Greeks,</hi> and of the <hi>Jews</hi> towards the attainment of the Truth, ſays that the latter who ſought after it by Faith, that is, by the means of a Divine Revelation, were much more in the right than the former, who made uſe only of Reaſon to attain it. This once admitted, which indeed cannot be deny'd, I hope to let you ſee that I am not unjuſt to Reaſon. You will give me leave to conſider it, before, in, and after the admitting of the Revelation.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>Conſider it which way you will.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>Faith then pre-ſuppoſes Reaſon. They muſt be Rational Creatures whom it is infus'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and without the one we are not capable of the other. Though the Almighty has an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute power over us, yet he is pleas'd not to force our aſſent, but propoſes the Faith and perſwades us to it. <hi>It comes by hearing,</hi> ſays St. <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 10.17. that is, it is not impos'd tyrannically without reaſons or arguments to inforce its ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity and uſefulneſs, but with all the proper methods to engage our aſſent. We believe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we have all the Reaſon in the World ſo to do. And Faith becomes our choice upon the nobleſt and ſtrongeſt Motives that can be. I do Reaſon all the juſtice and honour which it can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect or deſerve, by ſaying that our moſt Holy Religion is built on this moſt rational Principle,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:51496:58"/>than which Man has none ſtronger, none more evident. <hi>Whatſoever God reveals is true, and therefore the Myſteries of Chriſtianity are true, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God has reveal'd them.</hi> There is no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception againſt the firſt of theſe Propoſitions. In abundance of other things Reaſon is in the dark, but it meets with no ſort of obſcurity in this. The ſecond then is its work and exerciſe, to which it ought to be apply'd. Reaſon muſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy it ſelf whether God has reveal'd what Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion offers? It is highly juſt that it ſhould be ſo; or elſe every thing will be call'd Revelation, and every folly conſecrated by pretending to have God for its Author. <hi>Men will ſee vanity and divine lyes, ſaying, thus ſays the Lord, when the Lord has not ſpoken,</hi> Ezek. 22.28.</p>
                  <p>Thus St. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorts the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 5.21. to <hi>prove all things and hold faſt that which is good.</hi> Compare all the Sects which have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to inſtruct Men in relation to a better Life. Try even thoſe Syſtems which boaſt an infallible Judge. Let nothing that aſſumes the Name of Truth eſcape a ſevere inquiry. But when all is done, <hi>hold faſt that which is good;</hi> to wit, that which we are perſwaded cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive us, even the Revelation of God. You ſee then a large Province for Reaſon to act in. And at the ſame time how eaſy is that task which brings us at laſt to the Author of our being to receive the Truth at his hands.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>All this is well. But ſtill vaſt difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties preſent themſelves. <hi>Firſt,</hi> Where is this Revelation which you ſuppoſe? I know you will anſwer immediately, that it is to be found in the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:51496:59"/>Sacred Writings. But then you make it to be the Province of Reaſon, to ſatisfy it ſelf in the Truth of the Revelation. If by this you mean the certainty of the Divine Records, you plunge your ſelf in endleſs, and I will ſay, unſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful queſtions about their Inſpiration. You will be forc'd to ſhew which of them are inſpir'd, and which are not? You will find them who have pleaded for the Goſpels of <hi>Baſilides, Apelles,</hi> and <hi>Tatianus.</hi> For that according to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> St. <hi>Paul,</hi> St. <hi>Thomas,</hi> &amp;c. For the Acts of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, by St. <hi>Andrew,</hi> St. <hi>Philip,</hi> &amp;c. For o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Epiſtles of St. <hi>Paul</hi> than thoſe which we have, and ſeveral Writings related by St <hi>Hierom de Scriptor. Eccl.</hi> in <hi>Luc.</hi> and cenſur'd by <hi>Gelaſius,</hi> you will meet with <hi>Prochorus,</hi> and <hi>Abdias</hi> the <hi>Babylonian,</hi> and a world of ſpurious Writers pretending the Divine Revelation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> If you paſs from the certainty of the Records, to the particular places by which you affirm that God has reveal'd your Doctrine, their ſence will be ſtill diſputed. It will be ſaid that God indeed has reveal'd them, but not in the ſence which you underſtand them in. And it will be the ſame as if you had no Revelation at all.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Suppoſing that Reaſon can effect all this, whoſe Reaſon muſt it be? Is it that, as you were pleas'd to ſpeak, of the common Saylor, the Souldier, the labouring Man? Indeed the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple will ſtand unmoveable, <hi>what God has re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd is true.</hi> But your Aſſertion that <hi>he has re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd the Myſteries</hi> of <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> will be diſputed, partly from the uncertainty whether
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:51496:59"/>the Records are truly Divine, partly from the doubt of the ſence of the particular places which you alledge. So that Reaſon in moſt Men will have nothing to do, becauſe they are not capable of learned inquiries; and the few that are will wrangle with you to the end of the World.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>The firſt of your objections cannot be propos'd by a <hi>Socinian.</hi> It is of ſome force in the Mouth of a <hi>Heathen,</hi> or of a <hi>Deiſt.</hi> Were I to argue againſt either of them, I ought not to take it ill, if they oblig'd me to prove the certainty and inſpiration of the Divine Records. Nor is this ſo difficult as you imagine. Criticks have made that a Controverſy which is none in it ſelf, and never was ſo before. So great and venerable are the Arguments by which the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity of the Sacred Writings is prov'd, that nothing has yet been ſaid of any moment againſt it. It is to no purpoſe to inſiſt on this with you, who own <hi>the Scripture to be a compleat and infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible rule of Faith.</hi> Nor is it more neceſſary to make it appear that the Books in diſpute in the Primitive Ages of the Church were ſpurious. For beſides that we have nothing left of them but their Names, and that too with ſome diverſity; and that they obtain'd very little, becauſe the cheat was preſently found out; it would not be fair in you to put one to the trouble of diſproving Books which you diſprove your ſelf. You ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit with all the reſt of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> the <hi>Canon</hi> of the old and new Teſtament, <hi>Pag.</hi> 6. of the Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Edwards. Whereas</hi> Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> ſays the Author, <hi>would intimate that we reject divers Books of Scripture; on the contrary we receive into our
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:51496:60"/>Canon all the Books of Scripture that are receiv'd or own'd by the Church of</hi> England; <hi>and we reject the Books rejected by the Church of</hi> England. So then all this difficulty is over.</p>
                  <p>Your ſecond objection is as eaſily reſolv'd. When ever any thing is propos'd as Faith, the buſineſs of Reaſon is to ſee whether it is to be found in thoſe Writings wherein we all confeſs that God has reveal'd what we ought to believe? Thus the <hi>Beraeans, Act</hi> 17.11. at the preaching of Paul <hi>Search'd the Scriptures daily, whether the things which he ſaid to them were ſo?</hi> They ſound his allegations true, and therefore <hi>many of them believ'd.</hi> Nor will this, as you inſinuate, reſolve it ſelf into a diſpute about the ſence of the places alledg'd. For, as we have ſaid before, thoſe places are ſo plain, ſo uncapable of any other ſence than what they offer; The deductions from them are ſo Natural and eaſy, that all diſputing is wholly exciuded. For inſtance the Debate between you and me is about the Holy <hi>Trinity.</hi> You deny and I affirm it. We both agree upon a <hi>Medium</hi> to find whether it is ſo or no? And that is the Authority of the Sacred Writings. If in them there is a clear Revelation that God is one, and if I produce thoſe Texts which plainly and naturally attributes thoſe qualifications to Father, Son, and Holy Spirit, which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municable to no created Being, and cannot be diverted any other way without changing the ſence of the propoſition, you muſt as the Noble and Candid Spirits of <hi>Beraea</hi> certainly yield.</p>
                  <p>Againſt your third objection I ſay that the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned part of the World is as capable of this
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:51496:60"/>as the learned; Nay much more. For beſides the plainneſs of the Revelation their perceptions in what they underſtand are more direct, and not clogg'd with ſubtilties as ours are. They have, I am afraid a more ſincere reſpect for the Divine Revelation than we. Take an honeſt Country-Man, and ask him who is he that is <hi>bleſſed over all for ever?</hi> He will anſwer immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately, <hi>GOD.</hi> Shew him in the Scripture that this is ſaid of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> He will immediately con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is <hi>GOD.</hi> Object to him that if Chriſt is God, and the Father God, then there are two <hi>Gods.</hi> He will immediately reply, No, They are but <hi>one,</hi> For God is but <hi>ONE.</hi> You may puzle him with your Ratiocinations. He may be at a ſtand and hear you cry till you are hoarſe, that two cannot be one, and that he does his Reaſon an injury. He will tell you that it is ſo indeed when he takes an account of his ſheep and horſes, but in what concerns his Religion, his <hi>Bible</hi> in his Reaſon; It ſays ſo, and he believes it.</p>
                  <p>The Learned will not wrangle to the end of the World, except by the Learned you mean only the <hi>Socinians.</hi> I am ſure and you cannot but be ſo too, that for many Ages, and now in this very Age the Learned of all Societies agree in this. And though the <hi>Socinians</hi> are infinitely fond of their objections againſt our <hi>Myſteries,</hi> yet I deſpair not to ſee them come over to the Faith. They are Rational, and at one time or other will be equitable Men.</p>
                  <p>But now let us ſee the Province of Reaſon, when it is ſatisfy'd that ſuch, or ſuch a truth is reveal'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:51496:61"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>I know what you are going to ſay, and it is this. That Reaſon having once ſatisfy'd it ſelf of the certainty of the Revelation, it has no more to do; but its duty is to ſubmit to what God has reveal'd. Let a propoſition contain never ſuch a groſs or palpable contradiction it muſt be ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd contentedly. But in good truth, can this be done? If this is Faith and believing who can believe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>God can reveal neither contradiction nor error. There is a great difference between underſtanding the truth of a propoſition, and the Nature of the thing propos'd. <hi>God was mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in the Fleſh, and the Word was made Fleſh,</hi> are propoſitions ſo vaſtly plain, that no other ſence can be made of them but this. <hi>God has appear'd in our Nature.</hi> There is no error, no contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in this. In a word we underſtand it. But the Nature of the thing propos'd is ſo unknown to us, and ſo much above us, that it is raſh and bold for us to inquire into it, or imagine error, or contradiction in it. I ſay then, that the Truth once propos'd we ought to acquieſce in it: That Reaſon is to be ſilent, and give no way to further inquiries.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>But can Reaſon be ſilent, when you im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe on me the belief of that of which I have no kind of Notion?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>If by Notion you mean an inſight into the thing Reveal'd, you are unjuſt. We have diſcours'd already that the Nature of Faith is to be obſcure, or elſe it is no Faith. This can be no difficulty at all. It is enough for us that we underſtand that God has propos'd ſuch a thing,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:51496:61"/>though we underſtand not at all the thing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd. I cannot apprehend how God aſſumes our Nature and is manifeſt in the Fleſh; But I apprehend that God tells it me in clear and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs terms, and therefore I believe, and think not my poor ignorant Brain a competent Judge of God's Veracity.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>But pray hold a little. Will you be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy'd of the deficiency of your method, if I ſhew you that after you have attain'd the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of the Revelation, you muſt believe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, which are inconſiſtent with and deſtroy one another? You believe God to be one, and yet Father, Son, and Holy Spirit to be every one God. Does not the firſt propoſition deſtroy the ſecond, and the ſecond the firſt? How can he be one and three, three and one?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>This is ſtill begging of the queſtion. God can propoſe nothing Contradictory or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent. I confeſs I cannot underſtand how this is, but it is reveal'd, therefore certainly true, and on that account I believe it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>You believe that Chriſt is God and Man; Infinite and Finite; Immortal and Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal; The Supreme, moſt High God, and yet ſuffering and Dying. He is God and he is ſent; He is God and yet prays to God. He is God over all, and yet ſubject to him who put all things under him. If this is not inconſiſtent, I do not know what inconſiſtency is.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>If <hi>Plato, Ariſtotle,</hi> or any of the Sons of Men ſhould tell me this, I would ſpeak as you do. But God is true, and he ſays all this. I adore the Divine Oeconomy, though I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:51496:62"/>it not. To be God and Man is no Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction. The Scripture repreſents Chriſt as <hi>God bleſſed over all for ever.</hi> It repreſents him alſo as a Man. Nothing can be more expreſs than the declarations of his <hi>Divinity:</hi> Nothing more clear than thoſe of his Humanity. Which part of the Revelation ſhall Reaſon overthrow? Convinc'd by the proofs of his Humanity you will ſay that he is no God. Another convinc'd by the proofs of his Divinity will deny that he is a Man. Thus Reaſon more inconſiſtent with it ſelf than you fanſie Revelation to be, will reject every part and deſtroy the whole.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>No. Reaſon will reconcile all, and by an eaſy explication will make him an inferior, or a deputed God and alſo the greateſt of Men.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>A <hi>Socinian</hi> Explication! But the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery is that our Texts are not capable of any. <hi>God Bleſſed over all for ever; The word was with God, The word was God,</hi> and twenty more ſuch places admit of no explication. <hi>A Man of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows and acquainted with grief, in the Form of a Servant, humbling himſelf to the Death of the Croſs, becoming Sin for us, and dying for Sinners,</hi> contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts all your explications. Away with this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy which really debaſes Reaſon! Take the Revelation as a Rational Man; as it lies in all its parts; as it comes from God, who in the fullneſs of time has ſent his Eternal Son to aſſume our Nature and become a Sacrifice for us.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>But you can never perſwade me that Reaſon has not as much right to examine the truth of the thing propos'd, as the propoſition it ſelf; and to reject it, if it is not agreeable to its Principles.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:51496:62"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>But you can never prove that Reaſon is capable of examining that which is above Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and ſuch are things reveal'd. Their truth indeed depend from the conformity which they have with the Supreme Reaſon, which is God. But in reſpect to us their Truth conſiſts not in their agreeableneſs to yours, or my Reaſon: But wholly in the Authority of the Revelation. They are true, becauſe they are reveal'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>But is not my Reaſon a part of that Supreme Reaſon? Truth is but one either in the Creator, or in the Creature. Revelation cannot make that true which appears to me unreaſonable.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>You will never be weary of urging the ſame things over and over again. Whatſoever God reveals is true. But you ſay, it does not ſquare with my apprehenſions. Nay, it contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts them. Therefore it is not true. What a ſtrange way of Reaſoning is this. Truth in God is truth in Man. Granted. But is it in the ſame extent or degree? Do we know as much as God? A ſpark will pretend to be as Luminous as the Body of the Sun. I ſee as through a glaſs dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and I will judge of him who inhabits a ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of light which no Mortal can come near unto, Job 10.4. <hi>He muſt have Eyes of Fleſh, and ſee as a Man ſees,</hi> or elſe I will not believe what he ſays. This is monſtrous and not worth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting upon. Let us therefore proceed.</p>
                  <p>Reaſon then being ſatisfy'd in the truth of the Revelation cannot act like it ſelf, except it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives with the humbleſt and firmeſt ſubmiſſion what God has reveal'd; and as, St. <hi>Paul</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes it 2 Cor. 10.5. <hi>caſts down imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi>
                     <pb n="114" facs="tcp:51496:63"/>
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>REASONINGS, and every high thing that exalts it ſelf againſt the Knowledge of God. And brings into captivity every thought to the obedience of Chriſt.</hi> It is a great part of a Chriſtian's duty to correct the extravagances of Reaſon. For it is ſtubborn, reſtleſs and impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent of Government. It muſt be caſt down and chain'd up, as one which, if let alone, will be outrageouſly mad. It will never want pretences to riſe againſt its Soveraign, and in them it will obſtinately perſiſt.</p>
                  <p>This is the ground of thoſe frequent exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in Scripture to miſtruſt Men's inquiries, and give glory to the veracity of God. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.4. <hi>Let God be true but every Man a lyar.</hi> Rom. 4.20. <hi>Abraham</hi> is commended for not following the inſinuations of Reaſon, but giving himſelf wholly to the conduct of Faith. <hi>He ſtagger'd not at the promiſe of God through unbelief, but was ſtrong in Faith giving Glory to God.</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> would have us, Rom. 11.20. <hi>to ſtand by Faith,</hi> the Principles of Reaſon being too weak, but this ſtanding unmoveable. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.26. He tells us plainly and forcibly that Faith requires the obedience of our minds. <hi>According to the revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Myſtery which was kept ſecret ſince the World began, but now is made manifeſt, and by the Scriptures of the Prophets according to the command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Everlaſting God made known to all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for the obedience of Faith.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>But I muſt interrupt you, and tell you plainly and forcibly, that what colour ſoever the places which you have cited to prove Faith above Reaſon, this has none at all. You have
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:51496:63"/>found Myſtery, and Obedience of Faith toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and it has deceiv'd you. Read <hi>page</hi> 7. of that Print of ours call'd <hi>an impartial account of the word Myſtery.</hi> The Author tells you that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is revealed is no more a <hi>Myſtery.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>I wiſh it were not out of our way to give you ſome remarks on this ſame Print of yours. A perpetual Equivocation runs through the whole Work; and a willful miſunderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the words <hi>Knowing, Delivering, Revealing, Making Manifeſt,</hi> which imply indeed a diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but not at all an explication of the Truth reveal'd. Never did I ſee a greater unſincerity in any Writing. This very particular Text he has confin'd to the Vocation of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> which extends to all Chriſtian Myſteries, which are indeed Reveal'd as to their exiſtence, the <hi>quod ſint,</hi> as Divines ſpeak, but not the <hi>quid ſint,</hi> what they are in themſelves. He has not given one ſingle inſtance of a Myſtery made known, but after the Revelation is ſtill a Myſtery. The Creation, Reſurrection, Incarnation, <hi>Trinity,</hi> though clearly reveal'd, are ſtill Myſteries. The very Attributes of God, though not only made manifeſt in the Scriptures, but alſo in a great meaſure obvious to Reaſon, as Eternity, Immen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are ſtill Myſterious and Incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible. Let me beg of you then not to interrupt me with objections of that nature, which really make againſt you. But ſuffer me to go on in ſhewing you how God in his word has eſtabliſh'd the dominion of Faith over Reaſon, and the ſubmiſſion and obedience of Reaſon to Faith.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:51496:64"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>I will not, on condition that you cite no Texts capable of being conteſted.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>I have not yet, and will not for the future. What can be plainer than 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7. <hi>We walk by Faith, not by ſight?</hi> We truſt not to our little Reaſonings, which we are ſo weak as to call <hi>ſight</hi> and demonſtration, but rely upon a higher, nobler, and more infallible Principle, Faith in God. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.4, 5. St. <hi>Paul</hi> declares that his preaching has not been drawn from Mens Arguments, or adorn'd with a vain oſtentation of Eloquence; <hi>But in demonſtration of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and power of God;</hi> that is by the Writings of the Prophets inſpir'd by the Holy Spirit, by the voice of the Spirit it ſelf, by the Miracles of <hi>CHRIST</hi> and his Apoſtles, as <hi>Origen</hi> expreſſes it, <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>contr. Celſ. That your Faith ſhould not ſtand in the Wiſdom of Men, but of God.</hi> That your Faith ſhould not reſt upon Men's Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments but the Authority of God. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.23. He would have the <hi>Coloſſians</hi> to cruſh and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the ſuggeſtions of Reaſon and ſence and <hi>continue in the Faith ſettled and grounded, and not be mov'd away from the hope of the Goſpel.</hi> The ſame is urg'd 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.7, 8. and indeed in very many other places which it would be too tedious to cite. But what has the Saviour of the World ſaid himſelf in the caſe? Joh. 20.29. <hi>Bleſſed are they that have not ſeen, and yet have believ'd.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>Here I muſt interrupt you. This re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to the particular Fact of the Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt: It does not infer at all the belief of a doctrine contrary to my Reaſon. You offer no violence to the mind, when upon a ſolid Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:51496:64"/>I am perſwaded that ſuch a thing or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is or has been. I never was at <hi>Rome;</hi> But I believe as firmly as the <hi>Romans</hi> themſelves that there is ſuch a place. I never was bleſs'd with the ſight of my Saviour, or acquainted with the Glory of his Reſurrection; yet I believe as firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as any one that he was in the World, and roſe from the dead. But what is all this to your Doctrines?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>Be not ſo injurious to a Noble Paſſage, which though occaſion'd by a particular matter of Fact, the Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt, yet is a General maxim and of a vaſt influence on Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. It holds not only as to the Reſurrection, but alſo as to all Reveal'd Truths. Bleſſed are thoſe who believe what they have not ſeen with the Eyes of the Body: and they alſo are Bleſſed who believe what they cannot ſee with the Eyes of the Mind! Happy in both, that they come to God with an abſolute reſignation of their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Seeing muſt not be reſtrain'd to ſenſe, but extended to whatſoever God propoſes. Doctrines as well as Matters of Fact rely upon the Divine Authority.</p>
                  <p>But let us ſee how <hi>CHRIST,</hi> the Light of the World, has done in the delivery of his Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Doctrine. Has he courted our Minds to an aſſent by explaining the Nature of the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries which he offers? Or after the manner of the then Philoſophers, by diſputing and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to remove the prejudices of Reaſon? Not at all, but firſt he eſtabliſhes his own Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and then commands our belief. This grand point once ſettled, He tells us, Mark 16.16.
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:51496:65"/>
                     <hi>He that believes ſhall be ſav'd, he that believes not ſhall be damn'd.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Once more <hi>CHRIST</hi> gives the <hi>Jews</hi> no liberty of examining his doctrine, or, as you Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen of the <hi>Socinian</hi> perſwaſion are us'd to do, to admit or reject it, as you think it agreeable, or diſagreeable to your Reaſon. He proves what he is by two undeniable Principles. The <hi>Firſt,</hi> is the Prophecies accompliſh'd in him. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.43. <hi>To him give all the Prophets witneſs.</hi> The <hi>Second</hi> is the Miracles which he does. <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.37, 38. <hi>If I do not the works of my Father, believe me not; but if I do, though you believe not me, believe the works, that you may know and believe that the Father is in me, and I in him. And before</hi> v. 25. <hi>the works that I do in my Father's name, they bear witneſs of me. He had reveal'd to them</hi> a great Myſtery, <hi>viz.</hi> his Unity with the Father, an Unity of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Eſſence. v. 30. <hi>I and my Father are one.</hi> The Reaſon of the <hi>Jews</hi> ſtumbles at this, and even to that degree, that they take up ſtones to ſtone him. He uſes no other Arguments; but will have them to obey and ſubmit; and this upon the account of the greateſt and moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing demonſtration that can be, even the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous works of God. To deal ſincerely, can any thing be objected againſt this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes truly. You know that we deny this to be an Unity of Nature, and appeal to <hi>v.</hi> 36. But not to inſiſt on this, which we have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten objected, and you pretend to have as often anſwer'd, and not ſtart from the main queſtion; I ſay that he proves nothing, who proves too much. You ſtrain the point too high. You not
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:51496:65"/>only debaſe, but totally extinguiſh Reaſon. You leave it bare, naked, deſtitute, and like the Idols, Pſam. 115.5. <hi>Which have Eyes and ſee not, Mouths and ſpeak not.</hi> Have a care of <hi>v.</hi> 8. <hi>They that make them are like unto them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Is it to be imagin'd that we can renounce Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon? The will indeed is free and may embrace and reject. But the Mind is not capable of choice. It muſt neceſſarily aſſent or diſſent. It can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be brought to believe a contradiction. For my part, I openly declare, that againſt what part ſoever of my ſelf I practiſe ſelf denial, it ſhall never be againſt my Reaſon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>How often have we ſaid, and how of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten muſt we ſay it again, That nothing in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is contrary to the Principles of true Reaſon? That what you call Contradictions are not real, becauſe God can reveal no contradiction: and that Reaſon over-rules all its reluctancies by that moſt Rational Principle, that we owe our aſſent to what God has reveal'd. This is not then to renounce your Reaſon, but only its irregulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and exceſſes; to diveſt it of its pride and folly; and bring it to all the purity and ſtrength of which it is capable on this ſide the grave.</p>
                  <p>But how can one hear without horror, that you will not practiſe ſelf denial againſt your Reaſon, that is, you are reſolv'd not to be a <hi>Chriſtian?</hi> For he that is ſo, muſt, as we have ſaid already, <hi>bring into captivity every thought to the obedience of Chriſt.</hi> There is a pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Spirit to which <hi>CHRIST</hi> has annex'd a bleſſing. The living contentedly under the hard circumſtances of want, and a willingneſs to
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:51496:66"/>part with our riches to become poor for <hi>CHRIST</hi>'s ſake is but one part of it. The other conſiſts in robbing the mind of <hi>oppoſitions of ſcience falſly ſo call'd,</hi> which puffs us up, and through the vain additions of Philoſophy gives us a high opinion of our ſelves. The various notions which we have of things, are the riches of our mind, which we muſt be ready to part with, when ever <hi>CHRIST</hi> commands it. Learning without Piety looks upon this as an injury to Reaſon; unwilling to ſtoop, and be overcome; But Piety with Learning puts the Servant of God in that humble frame of ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to what he reveals.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>This is perfect <hi>Enthuſiaſm</hi> and <hi>Fanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſm</hi> all over. This the Prieſt perſwades the people to, that he may command their Faith. That point gain'd, he will quickly diſpoſe of the reſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>If this is <hi>Enthuſiaſm</hi> and <hi>Fanaticiſm,</hi> then all the World, but the <hi>Socinians,</hi> have been <hi>Enthuſiaſts</hi> and <hi>Fanaticks.</hi> The firſt Men of the World liv'd altogether by Faith. The Apoſtle gives the ſame Character to the <hi>Patriarchs,</hi> and <hi>Prophets.</hi> Whatſoever they did was the Work of Faith. Reaſon then was in ſubjection to it. But when Man ſubſtracted himſelf from the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God, and ſuffer'd himſelf to be guided by his own notions, then Reaſon grew proud, ſhook off the eaſy yoak, and gave birth to the opinions of Philoſophers, whom <hi>Tertullian</hi> calls elegantly <hi>Haereticorum Patriarchas, the Patriarchs of Hereticks.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Some of the wiſe Heathens themſelves were
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:51496:66"/>not inſenſible how many errors this pretence of Reaſon threw them into. <hi>Tully lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de nat. Deor.</hi> makes <hi>Cotta</hi> to ſpeak ſmartly to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe againſt <hi>Balbus</hi> the <hi>Stoick.</hi> I omit <hi>Socrates</hi> and <hi>Plato. Philoſtratus de vit. Apollon.</hi> lib. 5. c. 14. aſſerts that <hi>Philoſophy is good to lead us into the Knowledge of Natural, but not at all of Divine Truths.</hi> And <hi>Jamblichus</hi> is poſitive that <hi>Man by the ſtrength of Reaſon cannot underſtand Sacred and Religious matters.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To increaſe the number of thoſe <hi>Enthuſiaſts</hi> I dare to ſay that this has been the Unanimous ſence of the Fathers. Hence that ſaying of St. <hi>Auſtin Epiſt.</hi> 3. ſo highly Reverenc'd by the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Ages. <hi>Tota Ratio facti eſt potentia fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cientis.</hi> All the Reaſon which we can give of any thing that is done, is his power who does it. And the great Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Milan</hi> in Epiſt. ad Rom. <hi>Magni meriti eſt apud Deum, qui contra ſcientiam ſuam Deo credidit, non dubitans poſſe illum, utpote Deum, quod ſecundum mundi rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem fieri non poſſit. He is very dear to God, who believes God againſt all the Principles of his Reaſon, not doubting but that he can, as God, do that which cannot be done according to the Courſe and Reaſon of the World.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>You ſtare at this as very ſtrange and unaccoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table. But yet this is the Language of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Church. Thus ſpoke theſe Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Biſhops, and if we have any Zeal for Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Truths and Primitive Manners, we ought to ſpeak ſo too. Nay, this Notion is ſo Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal, that of all them who ever profeſs'd a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd Religion, none but the <hi>Socinians</hi> have op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſ'd
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:51496:67"/>it. The very Jews themſelves were not without it. The Author of the ancient Book <hi>Coſri par.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 27. ſays that <hi>Abraham</hi> came firſt to the knowledge of God by Reaſon; but that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter God had Reveal'd himſelf to him, he gave o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all his Arguments to ſtick to the Revelation. And that the old <hi>Rabbins</hi> underſtood the 12. of <hi>Geneſis v.</hi> 1. <hi>Get thee out of thy Country,</hi> and Gen. 15.5. <hi>And he brought him forth abroad,</hi> in an Allegorical ſence; as if God by theſe Words had commanded him to go from himſelf, his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane way of apprehenſions, his weak ratiocina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and leave himſelf wholly to his conduct. I confeſs, the Allegory is more pious than ſolid: It has a tincture of <hi>Rabbiniſm</hi> all over. But ſtill it is home to the point which I was to prove; that the <hi>Jews</hi> in this had the ſame notion with the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> that when Reaſon is ſatisfy'd that the Almighty ſpeaks, it ought to ſubmit, and ſtifle all its pretended contradictions.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>If the Ancient <hi>Jews</hi> were ſo much for believing, how come the Modern to be ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credulous? They are as mighty ſticklers as we for the Unity of the Great God. They deny <hi>CHRIST</hi> to be God. Yet to them were committed the Oracles of God. How comes it then that they are not affected with that Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a <hi>Trinity</hi> which you pretend to be ſo plain and expreſs?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>It will carry us too far out of our ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to lay down the Cauſes of their Incredulity. But yet it muſt be ſaid that in their diſputes with us, they have been more ſincere than you, as to the main point on which this Controverſy turns.
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:51496:67"/>For they have not pretended to Reaſon about this, or build their denial upon imaginary Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, the weak efforts of a Reaſon at a ſtand; but they have rejected all the new Diſpenſation, and diſown'd <hi>CHRIST</hi> to be the <hi>MESSIAS.</hi> In a word they have diſputed the Revelation: A Topick which you cannot pretend to, becauſe you admit the Sacred Writings of the New Teſtament. I ſhall ſay no more to this, but diſpatch the third conſideration, and ſee the uſe of Reaſon after Faith is admitted, and put your patience to a new trial?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>You command my attention.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſay then that Reaſon thus reſign'd ceaſes not to act. The noble Faculty has ſtill a large Field to exerciſe it ſelf in. For though it ſuppoſes the <hi>Axiomata,</hi> the firſt Principles of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> the Divine Myſteries to be ſo cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, as not to be capable of the leaſt doubt, but to be admitted with the moſt humble adoration, and ſincere and firm aſſent that can be; yet there are ſome Univerſal, and ſome Particular dependent, inferior Truths which it has the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to conſider. There are things which we know by Faith alone, others by Reaſon alone, and others by Faith and Reaſon together.</p>
                  <p>Of the firſt ſort are the Myſteries of the Holy <hi>Trinity,</hi> Incarnation, Reſurrection, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It is of theſe that St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> de <hi>vocat. Gent.</hi> ſays ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently, <hi>Magna eſt fortitudo conſenſionis cui ad ſequendum veritatem Auctoritas ſufficit etiam latente ratione. That aſſent has a great force, which, though we cannot ſee the Reaſon of things, yet makes us to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the Truth on the bare account of Authority.</hi> A
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:51496:68"/>doctrine ſo known, ſo reverenc'd in the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church, that St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> is ſo far from pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending that we can diſpute about them, that when the Philoſophers would argue againſt them who had embrac'd <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> he makes them anſwer thus <hi>Serm.</hi> 189. <hi>de temp. Accepto Baptiſmo, hoc dicimus, Fidelis factus ſum, Credo quod Neſcio. Having receiv'd Baptiſm we ſay this, I am become a Chriſtian, I believe what I cannot underſtand.</hi> In this Reaſon has nothing to do, I am altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther determin'd by Faith. It is from thence that the School-men have laid this as a Principle in their barbarous way of ſpeaking, that <hi>Habitus Fidei non eſt diſcurſious, ſed animus unico actu fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in objectum materiale propter formale.</hi> Which in plain <hi>Engliſh</hi> is this, that <hi>Faith depends not from Reaſon and Diſcourſe, but that the Soul of Man by the ſame act embraces the truth propos'd, a ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary ſort of an object, upon the account of the firſt, which is God revealing it to us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Of the ſecond ſort is whatſoever is not of Faith, but only ſerves to illuſtrate and confirm, to defend and propagate it. All our Arguments are the product of Reaſon. There is a Divine <hi>Oeconomy</hi> and Coherence in the Sacred Writings which it perceives, and from which it draws in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences: An <hi>Analogy</hi> of Faith which by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord and relation of the ſeveral parts make up the whole body of Divinity. It is a judicious obſervation of St. <hi>Auſtin, de Trin. lib.</hi> 14. <hi>c.</hi> 1. that as there are things which can never be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood except they are believ'd, ſo there are things which can never be believ'd except they are underſtood.</p>
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:51496:68"/>
                  <p>And ſuch are <hi>Prophecies,</hi> of which it is ſaid 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. <hi>We have alſo a more ſure word of Prophecy, whereunto you do well that you take heed as unto a light that ſhines in a dark place, until the day dawn, and the day Star ariſe in your Hearts.</hi> A Prophecy cannot be believ'd, except Reaſon has made way to Faith, by being convinc'd of its accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Thus CHRIST argu'd <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.44. <hi>Theſe are the words which I ſpoke to you whilſt I was with you, that all things muſt be fulfill'd which were written in the Law of</hi> Moſes, <hi>and in the</hi> Prophets, <hi>and in the</hi> Pſalms <hi>concerning me.</hi> For though Prophecy has the Sanction of the Divine Authority, and is to be aſſented unto, even as to its future accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, becauſe none of the Words of God can fall to the ground; yet when you tell me that it is accompliſh'd, it is altogether the work of my Reaſon, to examine whether it is ſo, or no?</p>
                  <p>God by his Prophets, and indeed by the two firſt Diſpenſations, that of Nature, and that of the Law, has promis'd that a MESSIAS ſhould come for the Redemption of Mankind. The Prophecies concerning him are many, and expreſs. Some deſcribe his Nature, others his Perſon: Some his miraculous Works, others his Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Doctrine: Some the time and place of his coming, others his Life, Death, Reſurrection, Aſcenſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> All this is true, and Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently commands our belief, becauſe God has ſpoke it. But whether this or that Perſon is the MESSIAS, muſt depend from an examination in whom all theſe things are fullfill'd: Whether in this, or that Man. And this is certainly the Work of Reaſon.</p>
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:51496:69"/>
                  <p>The ſame muſt be ſaid of Miracles. There is not a more forcible Argument that the Author of Nature has Reveal'd a Doctrine, than when he alters or ſuſpends its ordinary courſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm it. But ſtill I have a Liberty to try whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Spirits are of God? Whether it is a real Miracle, and not an Illuſion? Whether the Matter of Fact is true? Thus <hi>Act.</hi> 13.12. <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius Paulus,</hi> who before is call'd a Prudent Man, ſeeing <hi>Elymas</hi> by the bare ſpeaking of St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſtruck with blindneſs, <hi>believ'd, being aſtoniſh'd at the Doctrine of the Lord.</hi> The Miracle was cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the ground of his Faith. But he had not deſerv'd the name of a Prudent Man, if he had not ſatisfy'd himſelf of the Truth of the Miracle.</p>
                  <p>And in this <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> appears Venerable to me beyond any thing that Men ever call'd Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that it is ſo far from reſtraining Reaſon where it ought to act, that it gives it the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſcope imaginable. I am <hi>aſtoniſh'd at,</hi> or much better as the <hi>Latin</hi> Interpreter reads it, I <hi>admire</hi> that Doctrine of the Lord, which, though re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd into the Authority of him that reveals it, yet is embrac'd upon the moſt Rational Motives that can be.</p>
                  <p>I am ſure you will be pleas'd, when I tell you that <hi>Criticizing</hi> is alſo the Work of Reaſon. I mean by <hi>Criticizing</hi> that acute judgment by which we reject what is ſpurious, and take up what is genuine and certain, holding to the Purity and Sincerity of Ancient Copies, eſtabliſhing true Readings, and making Tranſlations as exact and as agreeable as can be to the Original. All that which facilitates the underſtanding of the difficult
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:51496:69"/>places of Scripture, muſt be put in the number. This has made Interpreters, Commentators, Annotators, and a world of Polemick Writers who have deſerv'd well of Religion in general, and have been in particular the Glory of the <hi>Reformation.</hi> The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is oblig'd to us for that ſort of Learning, and indeed for all manner of Knowledge; there being no part of it but what has been reviv'd by Proteſtants, and moſt of all by <hi>Engliſh</hi> Writers. Though of theſe laſt, the Learned World has juſt cauſe to complain, that ſo many incomparable Books have been confin'd to their own natural Language. I confeſs alſo, and that to my grief, that our great love and ſtudy of the Eaſtern Languages ſeems to forſake us, and go over to our Adverſaries.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>I am ſorry for it too. But now you commend <hi>Criticks,</hi> what do you think of Us as to that particular.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>I wiſh you would not oblige me to run out of my Subject. But ſince you will have me give you my ſence of this, I beg of you to forgive me, if I ſay that you are the moſt lamentable Criticks in the World. Your out-landiſh Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, I mean them who are openly <hi>Socinians,</hi> except ſome tolerable good Latin, interlarded now and then with a Greek Phraſe, are not worth reading. Thoſe that keep behind the Curtain are much better. But when they come to the points in diſpute, they are as weak and as inſufferable as the other. Your <hi>Engliſh</hi> Writers are Men of much more digeſted thoughts, and a purer way of expreſſion. As long as they keep within their pretended difficulties, they are like
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:51496:70"/>to impoſe. But when they are brought to the Teſt, that is, to the Sacred Writings, their <hi>Criticiſms</hi> are ſo mean, ſo ſtrange, ſo unſincere; their evaſions are ſo many, ſo viſible, ſo unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, what they have to ſay is ſo unſatisfactory, and ſo foreign to the thing, that of all Men I would not have you ſet up for Criticks. But to return.</p>
                  <p>There are things which we know both by Faith and Reaſon. Such is the exiſtence of God. Rom. 1.19, 20. <hi>That which may be known of God is manifeſt to them: For God has ſhew'd it to them. For the inviſible things of him from the Creation of the World, are clearly ſeen, being underſtood by the things that are made, even his Eternal Power and Godhead.</hi> That Reaſon muſt ſtrangely act againſt it ſelf which denies the Being of God. But though this is ſo plain as to come within every Man's capacity, yet the <hi>Exiſtence</hi> of God is alſo the object of our Faith. We may ſay the ſame of his Unity, Immenſity, Omnipreſence, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Power, and his other Divine Attributes, particularly that Providence by which he governs us and the World, Heb. 11.6. <hi>He that comes to God muſt believe that he is, and that he is a reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of them that diligently ſeek him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I am alſo apt to think, that though Faith teaches us that <hi>in Adam all die;</hi> that <hi>we have all ſinned and come ſhort of the Glory of God,</hi> and that our Converſion to God is a new Creation, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Created in Jeſus Chriſt unto good Works,</hi> yet Reaſon in a great meaſure may be acquainted with the corruption of our Nature. We cannot come out of the hands of God, with that dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:51496:70"/>of Mind, that World of evil Inclinations, and that tendency to Sin which we have. There is that in Man which of one ſide convinces him of his Greatneſs and Excellency; and of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, of his Baſeneſs and Miſery. We have an incredible deſire of Happineſs, and yet purſue thoſe things which end in our ruine. So great a Contradiction cannot come from the All-wiſe and Merciful Creatour. Anſwer me not that we Sin by Imitation. It is a poor and ſilly Notion, which leaves the Difficulty whole and unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd.</p>
                  <p>Reaſon alſo as well as Faith acquaints us with the Immortality of the Soul, and the certainty of a State of Rewards and Puniſhments after this Life. In this the generality of the Wiſe Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens agreed. <hi>Cum de animorum aeternitate diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerimus,</hi> ſays <hi>Seneca,</hi> Epiſt. 117. <hi>non leve momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum apud nos habet conſenſus hominum aut timen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium inferos, aut colentium. When we diſpute of the Eternity of the Soul, the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal conſent of Men who either fear or adore the Powers below, is of no ſmall importance. I make uſe of that publick Perſwaſion.</hi> And <hi>Macrobius</hi> de Som. Scip. l. 1. c. 14. <hi>Obtinuit non minus de incorporalitate animae quam de immortalitate ſententiae.</hi> The opinion of the Souls Immateriality has been as generally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd as that of its Immortality.</p>
                  <p>But not to multiply any more inſtances, let us conclude with the Divinity of the Sacred Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings: They are receiv'd by us not only with the homage of an humble Faith, but alſo by ſtrong convictions of Reaſon. I take it to be granted by all Chriſtian Societies that the Holy
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:51496:71"/>Scriptures are divinely inſpir'd. This is a point of their Faith, and indeed the foundation of all the reſt. The <hi>Socinians</hi> themſelves who have deny'd ſo many things, never controverted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, agree with them in this. But yet I am perſwaded that Reaſon does not want ſeveral noble and ſubſtantial Arguments to prove it.</p>
                  <p>That which <hi>Origen</hi> contr. Celſ. <hi>Theodoret</hi> Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſat. in Pſ. St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and the generality of the Fathers have us'd, ſeems to me Irrefragable. And that is, the vaſt number of <hi>Prophecies</hi> which we find to have receiv'd their accompliſhment. For all Mankind aſſert Prophecy to be the Gift and Work of God, and only in his Power. Iſa. 41.23. <hi>Shew the things that are to come hereafter, that we may know that you are Gods.</hi> And <hi>Pacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius</hi> in Gell. lib. 14. c. 1. <hi>Nam ſi qui, quae even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura ſunt provideant, aequiparent Jovi.</hi> An Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument truly call'd by the Ancients <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and by the Apoſtle 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.4. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>the demonſtration of the Spirit,</hi> to diſtinguiſh it from the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>the demonſtration of Power,</hi> which conſiſts in miraculous operations. And therefore that Record is truly divine in which God has left ſuch ſplendid and laſting monuments of his Holy Spirit.</p>
                  <p>But if a Book may truly be call'd Divine which tranſcends all Books whatſoever, that Collection which we have of the Sacred Writings juſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves that name. For beſides that it can be made to appear that all the Theology, all the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, all the Rites, all the Laws, all the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and Cuſtoms, all the Heroes of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, are deriv'd from thence; and that this
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:51496:71"/>Truth is not unperceiveable, though oppreſs'd and eclips'd with the interpoſition of innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Fables and Lyes; pray what Book can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare with this for Antiquity, for certainty in the diſcovery of the Creation of the World, the formation of all things, the Hiſtory of the firſt Ages; but above all for that vaſt number of Precepts of Morality, of excellent rules of Piety and Holineſs, by which Man is acquainted with his duty to God and to his fellow Creatures, and has the promiſe of an Eternal State as a Reward of his Obedience.</p>
                  <p>What Man ever ſpoke or could ever ſpeak in the Stile of the Sacred Writings? It is every where Inimitable, and does not ſurpriſe by a numerous train of pompous expreſſions, but by a natural and inward Majeſty, which no mortal Oratory can perſonate. It ſpeaks to the Heart as well as to the Ears, and converts as well as inſtructs us. God has ſhew'd himſelf no where better than in his Word. In his operations he acts, but in this he ſpeaks like God. Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever reads attentively the Holy Scriptures, muſt needs upon the whole conclude that it is a Work which infinitely exceeds the moſt refin'd Reaſon, the moſt intenſe Capacity, and the vaſteſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry of Man.</p>
                  <p>I will ſay no more; only let me beg of you to lay this all together, and then tell me whether I am an Enemy to Reaſon, and whether it has re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd any injury from me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>Your way of ſpeaking ſhews the Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of Reaſon, and you make an admirable uſe of it againſt it ſelf. You leave me but one thing
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:51496:72"/>to deſire, and that is, that I could be ſo far ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy'd with what you have ſaid, as to aſſent to it. But it is not in my power; Nor think I my ſelf overcome, though I cannot anſwer your Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments. For when all is done my Reaſon muſt be the Judge, and it will not ſuffer me to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve your Myſteries. I know that you will tell me that this is obſtinacy, and that at this rate no Man will ever be convinc'd of his errors, but will make this his laſt refuge, that he cannot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed contradict the truth offer'd, but that his Reaſon will not ſuffer him to ſubmit. I grant all this: But ſtill as long as I act ſincerely in it, I may be pity'd, but I cannot be blam'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>You have often told me of your ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity in this matter: But I am afraid you have not the true notion of it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>I underſtand by it a ſerious mind, will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to know the truth, and taking all the ways that it can to attain it. I have ſtudy'd my own heart, and if I can pretend to any knowledge of my ſelf, I think that I am in that very diſpoſition.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>There is a great deal more in it than all this comes to. Self-love will turn it ſelf into a thouſand ſhapes and repreſent us to our ſelves quite otherwiſe than really we are. Informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on indeed is the way to Truth; But other qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications muſt be ſuppos'd without which it is not attainable. Bare arguing will never do. The Soul muſt be purify'd of thoſe luſts which are ſo many clouds interpoſing between us and the Truth. I ſhall never believe a Man ſincere in this, till a ſubſtantial Piety, with an uniform, humble, and mortify'd Life has made way to
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:51496:72"/>Divine Illuminations. I take the grand obſtacle to Faith, not ſo much to conſiſt in what we call Reaſon, as in the indiſpoſition of the heart which reſiſts the impreſſions of the Grace and Spirit of God. Sincerity in our obedience to <hi>CHRIST</hi>'s holy precepts, is the Touch-ſtone of that other which we pretend to. One may practiſe Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on though he underſtands it not; but it can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be underſtood, except it be ſeriouſly pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis'd. As long as we live a life of ſenſe and neglect the duties of Religion, we ſhall ever wrangle with the points propos'd to our belief. Oblige me in not ſeparating two things ſo wholly depending on one another.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>I perfectly agree with you in this. But I believe that God is merciful; and that there is an allowance for invincible errors.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>I believe ſo too. But the error which you have eſpous'd is certainly a damnable error, and is not Invincible. He who never had a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation of the Goſpel, and lives up to the light of nature, will no doubt find that the mercies of God are not ſo conſin'd as ſome Zealots have made them. But you have had it; and that too atteſted with the blood of Martyrs, and the voice of the Catholick Church, which at this very time from all the parts of the World exclaims againſt, and condemns you. How guilty is that confidence, which, under the pretence of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions and poor Criticiſms, dares refuſe an aſſent to God ſpeaking in his Holy Scriptures, and to his Church, declaring her ſence of thoſe matters in all her decrees! Your errour indeed is invincible, not becauſe you cannot, but becauſe you will not be overcome.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:51496:73"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>But who is a better judge than my ſelf, whether I can or no?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>All this is trifling with God and your ſelf. Every Man will give the ſame Anſwer, and by this defend not only the moſt pernicious er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, but even the moſt ſinful habits. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever take the great help which God has pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided in this caſe, and that is Prayer. Be never wanting in your publick and private Adorations of God, to pour your Heart before him with humility and fervency; that he would open your Eyes and remove from you blindneſs and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Heart. Alaſs, my Friend, the night of your Life and mine is far ſpent. The day is at hand. Few ſteps more and we launch into <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</hi> Have pity on your own Soul, and haſten to ſecure your ſelf.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>I cannot however but expreſs my ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment for your good and ſerious advice. I promiſe you that I will conſider of it in earneſt. But it grows late, and I fear we have no more time than what will ſerve to take another turn in this fine Garden, and then draw home.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>Beſure to be as good as your word.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Socin.</speaker>
                  <p>I will.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Orthod.</speaker>
                  <p>Then I am almoſt confident that you will have done <hi>Socinianizing.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:51496:73"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
